[BIRDSONG]
[ORGAN MUSIC PLAYING]
- Good morning.
Hello, Christine!
- Good morning, Herr von Grotjahn.
- Morning. Morning, sir.
Aren't you pleased with the way
Lina decorated the church for us?
Oh, she loved doing it,
Fräulein Christine.
Father is a long time.
I'm afraid this is for
the last time, Herr Pastor.
Oh, not the last time, Heinrich.
You'll be coming back
to Altdorf?
A Stormtrooper goes
where he's told.
Oh, you're a Stormtrooper now,
are you?
Well, it's a job,
Herr Pastor.
I've been out of work so long.
I'm glad you've got it.
Be fine to be working again.
And for Germany, too.
I wish you the
best of luck, Heinrich.
I shall never be able
to thank you enough,
you know, for all
you've done for me.
You will thank me
by doing well with your life.
Now, goodbye. I'm looking forward
to our next meeting.
So am I. I shall never
be able to thank you enough...
Oh, God bless you,
God bless you.
- Good day, Hans.
- Good day, Friedrich.
Morning, Werner.
I'm beginning to think
my sermons must be pretty good,
- to get you here so often.
- Yes, I enjoy them very much, sir.
Father, Uncle Paul
will be waiting.
Good Heavens, we mustn't
keep a general waiting.
Particularly this general!
- Friedrich, you're late again!
- I'm sorry, Paul.
Had me pacing up and down here
like a confounded sentry.
- You might have waited inside.
- What, me?
[SHIVERING]
Give me the willies.
Well, got a kiss
for an old soldier?
[CHUCKLING]
You look as radiant
as a rose in May.
Come on! Well, come on!
Don't be standing about here all day.
Don't be late home, you two.
I've got something special for dinner.
Oh, well, if it's a question between
his conscience and my stomach,
- stomach wins!
- [ALL LAUGHING]
Friedrich, what's our
good deed for today?
Well, I thought we might
call on Frau Kemp.
Mmm, it's a good deed.
A good deal too good for me.
Herr Pastor! Herr Pastor!
Oh, it's that infernal bore
Pippermann.
I was looking for you
at the church.
I have an important
matter to discuss.
You will excuse us, General?
Oh, you can rely on
the general's discretion.
Well, it's that barmaid
at the inn.
Oh, it's a shocking story,
but, of course, I've got
no actual proof, but it looks to me...
In that case, why waste
your breath repeating it?
- Yes, but, Herr Pastor...
- Herr Pippermann,
I'm sure your dislike
of scandal-mongering
is as great as mine.
Good day to you.
Poisonous rat.
Pity you stopped him, though.
He was just getting
to the interesting details.
My dear Paul, if I listened
to all the village gossip...
I know, I know, I know, but still,
she's a nice little piece, that barmaid.
A pair of fine legs.
- Oh, I haven't noticed them.
- Pity.
Here we are.
Well, it's your good deed,
you know.
I'm going to do
some of my sentry stuff.
- Oh, but you needn't, er...
- Oh, it's jolly good. Keep you fit.
Well, don't be long.
I'm as empty as a drum.
Yes, and almost as noisy as well!
[CHUCKLING]
[KNOCKING]
- Morning, Klara.
- Good morning, Herr Pastor.
- How's your aunt?
- She's always cheerful
- when she knows you're coming.
- Good.
[COUGHING]
Good morning, Frau Kemp.
Oh, it is nice
to see you here, Pastor.
You are looking better.
We'll be having you
in church again soon.
Here's something to
make you feel better still.
Thank you,
but you shouldn't
have done that, Pastor.
Oh.
Oh! A whole chicken!
What a beauty.
And what a size!
I shall never be able
to eat all that.
You needn't eat it
in one mouthful, you know.
- If my Erich were here, he would.
- Ah.
He's got such an appetite, that boy.
- Well, how's he getting on?
- Oh, he's getting on wonderfully well.
- I've got a new picture of him...
- Now, now, now.
There's no need to go
racing round the room
just because we're talking
about your boy.
It's on the table there.
Oh!
- Why, he's getting bigger than ever.
- And important, too.
Do you know, they've made him
one of the special bodyguard
- of Captain Röhm.
- Oh?
I expect he'll be home
to see me soon,
so I'm knitting this pullover
as a surprise for him.
You need quite a bit of wool
for my Erich.
Almost twice as much
as for anyone else.
He's so strong and big,
Herr Pastor.
You wouldn't believe it,
but he takes me up in his arms
like as if I were
a bundle of feathers,
and calls me his
"little mother".
- [CHUCKLING]
- His "little mother"!
I remember when he
was a little boy...
- ...and all that Erich said was, "Well..."
- [KNOCKING]
Goodness gracious, what's that?
I'm afraid that's
General von Grotjahn,
beating his drum for lunch.
I must go.
Now, take good care of yourself.
I'll be along
to see you soon.
Thank you, Pastor.
Thank you for coming.
[DOOR CLOSING]
Oh, Erich...
- Must you do this?
- Yes, of course, silly.
They'll be back in a moment
and Julia's busy with the dinner.
No, not that way.
Look, Christine...
I wanted to ask you something.
Yes, what is it?
You'll put down
one beside each place.
How can I talk to you when
you won't keep still for a moment?
There, that looks right.
Oh, no, I forgot the flowers.
- Oh, Christine, please listen.
- Oh, I am listening.
Be serious for a moment.
I can't talk to you
when you won't keep still.
All right, now
I'm perfectly serious.
What is it you
wanted to tell me?
Well...
You know I'm
leaving here tomorrow,
and I shall be gone for
several weeks, perhaps longer.
But there's something
I've got to tell you.
Something I've been wanting
to tell you for a long time.
- Is it so difficult?
- It is, Christine.
I mean, it's difficult
to tell you.
It's upsetting to have
known a girl all your life.
Whenever you came home,
she was there,
just a little bit different,
but the same Christine.
Part of one's life.
And now, everything's changed.
Has it?
You see, if we'd only just met,
and I'd fallen in love with you,
well, it would be
easier to say.
But you have said it.
Yes.
Seems I have.
You don't mind, Christine?
You know,
there should be new words
that no-one's ever
used before.
I love you, Christine.
- I could eat a horse.
- Could you?
Yes, I had two in the last war.
Father, Pastor,
we've got a surprise for you.
Surprise, nonsense!
I've known it for years.
Why didn't you ask her months ago?
I don't know. I should.
I shall be sorry
to lose you, Christine.
But I'm very glad
it's you, Werner.
Well, this calls for
a celebration.
- A schnapps?
- Did you ever know me refuse?
You're marrying the son
of an old drunkard, my dear.
Pity, but the regiment...
er... oh...
No, let me do that.
JULIA:
Look! Look!
It is empty!
I opened the pot,
and my beautiful chicken has gone!
Nineteen years I've been
with you, Herr Pastor,
but this is the end.
I can set a trap to stop
the mice from taking my food,
but what can I do about you?
GENERAL: Good Lord,
you haven't pinched the dinner?
- Who was it this time, Father?
- Frau Kemp.
You ought to be
horse-whipped.
Don't worry, Uncle Paul.
I've learned to keep
something in reserve.
PASTOR:
No, no, no, old boy.
Didn't seem so very funny
at the time, you know.
How was I to know
she was the Colonel's daughter?
- Oh, Paul.
- It's all right. Don't worry.
She'll soon learn a thing or two,
marrying into my family.
I hear we're going to have some
Stormtroopers stationed in the village.
Stormtroopers? Rubbish!
A lot of riff-raff in uniform.
Created an awful lot of trouble
in Berlin, you know.
Don't you think those stories
are exaggerated?
Not a bit.
Got friends in the Ministry.
They couldn't stand 'em.
Well, I suppose such
a vast change of administration
is bound to bring with it
some early violence.
Well, we haven't
felt much of it here.
Well, I don't believe in being
dictated to by an ex-corporal.
Bad discipline.
Anyhow, we've got something
more important to talk about today.
- Eh, Werner?
- Mmm?
When are you two
going to get hitched up?
- There's no hurry, Paul.
- There you go again.
What a passion you have
for keeping people waiting.
[CHUCKLING]
- When will you be back?
- I don't know.
Perhaps in only
a few weeks' time.
- Make it soon.
- Yes, you'd better.
They tell me the Stormtroop Leader's
a very good-looking fella.
[ALL CHUCKLING]
["HORST WESSEL SONG" PLAYING]
- Good morning, Herr Pastor.
- Good morning, Herr Veit.
The New Order
catching up with us, eh?
Yes, I'm losing
my little Lina, too.
- Oh?
- You won't be losing me, Daddy.
Yes, she's off to
a labour camp.
I shall only be gone
for a short time.
And, besides, I shall be
helping to build a greater Germany.
Really?
Our Führer says
it's the young people
that will lift our country
to its rightful place in the world.
Well, these are big thoughts
for such a little girl.
Oh, she's become a great politician
since the Stormtroopers came.
But, you know, I'm afraid
she's not strong enough
to go to a labour camp.
You wait, Daddy. When I come back,
I shall be very strong.
Well, I hope so. Come along,
say goodbye to the Herr Pastor.
- Goodbye, Herr Pastor.
- Goodbye, Lina, and good luck.
We'll all miss you,
especially Christine.
This is Pastor Hall's house?
Yes, sir.
Just a minute, please.
Fräulein Christine,
there's a Stormtrooper here.
Well, show him in.
[CLICKING HEELS]
Heil Hitler.
The Herr Pastor, please.
Stormtroop Leader Gerte.
Good morning.
I'm afraid my father isn't in.
You are his daughter?
Er... Yes.
Would you care to sit down?
No, thank you, no.
I'm exceedingly busy.
I've no time to wait about.
But if you're quite sure
he won't be long?
Oh, I'm sure he won't.
Will you have a cigarette?
Thank you.
What do you think
of our village?
Very backward, I'm afraid.
Quite untouched by the
new spirit of National Socialism.
That's why I'm here.
To put new life into the place.
We're very happy here.
Perhaps that's why
we're not so keen on changes.
Happiness is not our main concern.
Then, what is?
The greatness
and the glory of Germany.
And, to this end,
all petty personal happiness
must be sacrificed.
Everything that stands in the way
shall be crushed.
Sounds very ruthless.
Rather like digging up
all the plants in one's garden,
and only trying to grow one.
Rather a stiff and
prickly looking plant, too.
We have a colossal task
ahead of us,
and we shall achieve it.
If we receive voluntary help,
we shall be thankful.
If not, we shall find
other means to get it.
But Germany must be great,
and must be feared.
Well, why should Germany,
or any country,
want to be feared?
You are a woman. Women were
not meant to understand.
[CHUCKLING]
You don't approve of women?
On the contrary.
[HEELS CLICKING]
- [DOOR OPENING]
- Oh, here's Father.
Hello, Christine.
Father, this is
Stormtroop Leader Gerte,
who's going to change
our village completely.
- This is my father.
- Heil Hitler.
How do you do?
Sit down, we must have a chat.
Then, I think I'll leave you.
I'm sure you two men
have things to discuss
far beyond
my poor woman's brain.
Do you know, I believe
she's pulling our leg?
- Huh?
- Sit down.
Thank you.
Herr Pastor,
I am told that you have
great influence among the villagers.
Well, I've always tried
to earn their friendship.
My purpose in coming here
is to secure your co-operation.
Of course.
Anything I can do.
Co-operation for what, exactly?
To bring Altdorf into line
with the rest of the Reich.
To instil the one doctrine.
"Nation and Fatherland."
As our Führer has told us,
we are fighting for our security.
For the existence
and increase of our race.
For the nourishment of its children.
The purity of its blood.
The fulfilment of the mission
appointed for the Fatherland
by the Creator of the Universe.
I see, yes.
It's rather a tall order.
Of course,
I'm not interested in politics.
I'm so full of the villagers,
and their little worries and troubles.
- They're quite big to them, of course.
- That is just where you can help.
I've always believed
in rendering unto Caesar
that which is Caesar's.
And, in this village, it seems
that you are to be Caesar.
Exactly. Now, we can
get down to business.
First of all,
who are the people
who should be dealt with?
"Dealt with"?
Communists, socialists, pacifists,
Jews, enemies of the State.
Oh, I'm afraid I don't
regard the villagers
as either socialists or communists
or even nationalists,
and the few Jews we have
are quite good people.
We don't recognise
"good Jews" or "bad Jews".
Just "Jews".
But I certainly don't know
any "enemies of the State".
You're not being very helpful,
Herr Pastor.
I'm sorry,
but I can't help it.
You see, I know these people.
I like them.
I don't regard them as saints,
but there isn't one whom
I'd describe as "wholly bad".
In that case, Herr Pastor,
I am afraid I'm wasting my time.
I wish you good day.
Goodbye. I don't think you'll find
your task so sweeping as you suppose.
There's nothing much
the matter with our village.
We shall see.
Well, come in again, won't you?
Any time you feel like it.
Thank you.
Heil Hitler!
[HALF-HEARTEDLY]
Heil Hitler...
Good morning.
Oh, morning.
Gardening?
You're very observant.
May I help?
But surely it's beneath the dignity of
a Stormtroop Leader to stoop so low?
- Fräulein Hall...
- I thought you'd gone.
What do I do?
Well, you...
You pull them out like this,
and then, you...
you throw them there, like that.
Nice little garden
you have here, haven't you?
Yes, I love gardening.
Don't you?
Oh, I have my duties,
which take most of my time.
You take yourself
so seriously, don't you?
Life is serious, Fräulein.
Yes, but you must relax sometimes.
I'd like to know what you do
when you're off duty.
I'd like to see you
rolling in the grass, or...
or making yourself
sick with toffees.
I'd like to see you
at meals.
Do you click your heels at table,
and hold your fork like a bayonet?
Perhaps if the Fräulein
were to invite me?
Oh, yes, of course. Um...
Perhaps you'll be busy?
I have no special duties
on Tuesday,
if that night
would be convenient.
Tuesday'll be fine.
♪ Angels in the height, adore him
♪ Ye behold him face to face
♪ Saints triumphant, bow before him
♪ Gathered in from every race
♪ Alleluia! Alleluia!
♪ Praise with us the God of grace
♪ Amen ♪
Now, you sang that
very nicely, children.
Now, the lesson
from the Scripture today
is the story of
David and Goliath.
Now, this story shows that
it isn't always the big and the strong
- who win the battle of the...
- [DOOR CLOSING]
Herr Ritter wants to see you,
Herr Pastor.
Well, will you please
tell Herr Ritter
that I haven't finished
the Scripture lesson yet...
Herr Ritter said that
the children must get ready
for the outdoor exercises.
All right, I'll see Herr Ritter.
And remember, you are in
the Hitler Youth movement,
to be trained as future soldiers
for the Fatherland.
[KNOCKING]
Well, you may go now.
I'm busy.
- Heil Hitler.
- [KNOCKING]
- Come in.
Morning, Herr Ritter.
You wanted to see me?
Yes, I've wanted to establish
contact with you before, but...
You can't imagine what a state
I found this place.
I simply don't know
where to start.
Well, couldn't Herr Körner help you?
Herr Körner's been superseded.
I see.
He's taught in this school
for thirty years.
Precisely.
There are new things
to be taught now,
and that's what I wanted
to see you about.
- Now, regarding the Scripture lessons...
- I'll sit down, if you don't mind.
As I was saying,
regarding the Scripture lessons,
the new regulations contain
nothing against them in principle,
provided they're taught
along the Party lines.
And what exactly are
"the Party lines"?
Well, briefly, avoid the Old Testament
as much as possible,
try to connect the text of the Bible
with current events,
develop love of the Führer
and the nation...
Oh yes, avoid any reference to
the Jews as "the chosen people",
but don't enlarge on
"pity" too much.
And never refer to "love" in the
sentimental, humanitarian way,
but rather in the active,
Nordic sense.
Give the example
of Winter Relief.
Is that all, Herr Ritter?
Yes, I think so, Herr Pastor.
If you like, you can take this
little booklet along with you.
It may help you to understand
the Party lines.
Oh, I think I do understand.
Very well.
If you have any questions
in the future,
I shall always try to
spare you a few moments.
Thank you. I don't think
I'll disturb you very much.
Good day.
["HORST WESSEL SONG" PLAYING]
[SHOUTING]
[DESTRUCTION CONTINUES]
[STORMTROOPERS LAUGHING]
What has happened, Herr Marah?
Nothing much, Herr Pastor.
What is the reason for it?
My mother's mother
was Jewish.
Why didn't the neighbours
do something?
They've learned to keep away
when unpleasant things happen.
They couldn't have
done much, anyway.
Well, let me help you.
Thank you, Herr Pastor,
but there's not much
to be done now.
Good night.
Or, should we say,
"Heil Hitler"?
"Wilhelm Scharf.
"Investigations indicate that he is
suspected of communist sympathies."
Shall I have him arrested?
No.
Have him watched.
See who his friends are.
We may get a bigger bag.
Yes.
"Number 33.
Franz Went, smallholder..."
- [KNOCKING]
- Come!
Heil Hitler!
Pastor Hall to see you.
I'll get rid of him.
No need for you to see him.
I'll see him.
This pastor has
a lot of influence here.
Herr Stormtroop Leader.
A number of things have
happened in this village.
I can't believe it, but I'm told that
your Stormtroopers are responsible.
What is your complaint,
Herr Pastor?
Well, firstly, a number of obscene posters
have been put up in the village.
As a direct consequence,
a band of hooligans
have smashed old Marah's shop.
Everybody knows that Marah's
a harmless and decent old man.
I ordered the posters
to be put there, Herr Pastor,
and I'm also aware of
what happened to his shop.
- Surely you don't sanction...
- He is a Jew.
There is no place for Jews
in the Third Reich.
I believe that every man
has the right
to live in friendliness
with his neighbour,
no matter what
his race or creed.
- These are dangerous beliefs.
- Quiet.
I suggest, Herr Pastor,
that it would be better for you
to keep such views to yourself.
The new Germany
does not tolerate criticisms
of its most sacred beliefs.
I put this to you as a friend.
I thank you,
but I cannot be silent
in the face of this attempt
to bring to the fore
the worst instincts of our people.
As I say,
I wish to be friends with you.
I recognise that you have a task
which demands a certain attitude.
But I must warn you
not to go too far.
I take it there is
to be no redress?
In this case, I'm afraid not.
But I'm sure you will
soon see our point of view.
By the way, I happened to
see your daughter the other day.
She was kind enough
to ask me to dinner.
I see.
- Good day, Herr Stormtroop Leader.
- Heil Hitler.
These religious people.
Got to handle them
with kid gloves.
And their daughters,
too, Fritz?
[GROANING]
Easy round the liver.
Friedrich!
You want to let Stefan
have a go at you.
You'd never be
the same man again.
Friedrich?
I don't believe you've heard
a damn word I've been saying.
I'd never have believed
such things could happen in Altdorf.
First, the Stormtroopers
smashing up the shops,
then setting on people
whose politics they didn't like.
And now, it's spread,
like some dreadful disease,
to my own people.
I don't seem able to...
to reach them anymore.
Yes, that's enough.
That's enough.
Enough is as good as a feast.
Now, Friedrich,
what's worrying you?
The baker, Scharf, was
beaten up in the inn last night.
Mmm, I heard.
He said that Hitler
might be wrong.
Oh, blasted rabble!
Same thing's going on
all over the country.
Look at this.
I got this from a friend.
Today, in Amsterdam.
Oh, horrible, horrible!
Shooting one's own comrades.
Fellows who've fought
by one's side.
When I think of what
Germany meant to the world...
This couldn't have happened
in our day.
We had values
and loyalties then.
I've tried to see
their point of view.
There must be something in it,
if a whole nation can be
swept off its feet.
I've even had that
Stormtroop Leader to the house.
You've what?
Yes, I'm asking him
again tonight.
It was magnificent.
Sixty thousand people,
cheering like mad.
But when the Führer rose to speak,
you could hear a pin drop.
No-one dropped one, did they?
It's not a joking matter,
Fräulein Hall.
No, Stormtroop Leader
is right, Christine.
Please, go on with your story.
I think not, Herr Pastor.
Seems to me that
the ideals of National Socialism
find little sympathy
in this house.
Because we don't
understand them.
If, so far, I have not been
attracted to National Socialism,
it's because it seems to me
to encourage the two things
I've always tried
to fight against.
Lust for power,
and fear.
Perhaps I'm wrong.
We believe in
the rule of the strong.
The glory of Germany
can only survive
if we cut the canker
from the organism.
As doctors, you're not
always very gentle.
Surgeons must have
courage to cut.
True, but they must also have
a thorough knowledge of the human body.
Otherwise, they'd be
merely murderers.
- Herr Pastor...
- Oh, don't worry about Daddy.
He's always dropping bricks.
Oh, please, please.
I didn't mean anything personal
in any way.
I'm afraid we can find
no common ground.
Unless you admit the right
of a superior race
to shape its life
according to its historic mission.
Well, we Christians believe that
the spirit dominates, or should.
And anybody who believes with us
is one with us.
There are many pastors
who understand their task
as our Führer wishes it
to be understood.
You despise men, don't you?
No, I don't think so.
A man has only to obey
to be happy.
Obedience is not
the final virtue.
With us, it is.
I take orders from one
who knows men,
and yet doesn't despise them.
He trusts them with
this great danger of freedom.
He gives them choice,
though they often choose wrong.
For when a man
loses his freedom,
he ceases to be a man.
If you please, sir,
Klara is here.
Herr Pastor, please, come quickly.
Frau Kemp!
- Please, come quickly!
- Yes, yes, I'll come at once.
Excuse me.
Look after our guest, Christine.
[SOBBING]
Frau Kemp...
Frau Kemp,
it is Pastor Hall.
Tell me about it.
I will help you.
Now, tell me what happened.
It may not be so bad
as it seems.
He...
is dead.
They've killed him.
He's gone.
Tell me everything.
I was sitting here,
in this room,
knitting a pullover
for Erich.
So big, he is.
And a man
came to the door.
He asked for Frau Kemp.
Klara brought him in,
and he told me
to send her away.
Oh, then...
[SOBBING]
Then, he brought me this.
And there's a paper, too.
PASTOR:
Almighty God.
And the man said,
I wasn't to tell anyone
that Erich was shot,
or to have him buried,
as he was a traitor.
He said it twice, I think.
That I wasn't to tell anybody
that Erich was shot.
Oh, Pastor.
I can't understand it.
It can't be.
Erich was so tall and strong,
they made him one of
Captain Röhm's bodyguards.
And now...
[SOBBING]
PASTOR: These are
the mortal remains of Erich Kemp,
who was a fine man,
and a good son.
One we shall always
be proud to have known,
and to have called our friend.
And, if we bury him
in the dark of night,
it is not to his shame
that we do so.
No grudging hatred of man
can keep from him the place
which, by his merit
and his faith,
he will hold
in the Kingdom of Love,
which passes understanding.
Ashes to ashes,
dust to dust.
[ORGAN MUSIC PLAYING]
- Good morning.
- Hello.
- Oh, Herr Veit, I had news...
- Excuse me.
- Hello, Uncle Paul.
- Morning, Christine.
You don't look too happy.
It's hard to believe that people
could change in so short a while.
Oh, no guts, that's
what's the matter with them.
Afraid to be too pleasant,
because of the stand
your father's taken up.
Oh, by the way, I've got
some news for you about Werner.
Yes, I know.
He's coming home.
Mmm. About time.
- Tell Father I've gone home, will you?
- I will if I wait.
He's late again, you know.
He's been late every Sunday
for the last five years.
Or have you been early?
Never thought of that.
Fräulein Hall!
Will you come inside
for a few minutes?
- I want to speak to you.
- I'm sorry. I'm busy.
The Pastor and the General
haven't gone by yet.
I think you'd be advised
to hear what I've got to say.
It's about your father.
Very well.
Won't you sit down?
I've waited specially for you,
because you seem most anxious
to avoid me whenever possible.
Quite frankly, I don't believe
we've got very much to talk about.
What was it you wanted
to tell me about my father?
Can't we have a talk like friends?
Cigarette?
Why don't you say what
you've got to, and let me go?
- Very well.
- [SNAPPING CASE SHUT]
Perhaps you'd care
to have a look at this.
This is an account of your father's
activities against the State,
beginning with the funeral
of the Kemp boy,
the speech he made then,
and everything he has
said and done since.
Today, Fräulein Hall,
I received a letter
found on a Mr Marah,
as he was about
to leave the country,
which, for reasons
of no interest to you,
we did not consider
the right course for him to take.
No doubt, you recognise
your father's handwriting?
What about it?
He asked a friend of his
to help Marah.
This can't be a crime, even
according to your ideas.
Your father has recommended,
as his personal friend,
an enemy of the State.
Have you called me here
to display your powers?
To admire
your horrible spy system,
which has turned
a happy village
into a crowd of informers
and frightened people?
Do you want me to congratulate
you on your achievements?
Really!
This is not like the Pastor's
lovely, gentle daughter.
Now, listen to me, will you?
Every paper in this file is enough
to send your father to prison.
Men have been beheaded
for much smaller offences.
Perhaps you'd like to know
why your father wasn't taken away
after we found out
about the funeral?
Why he was allowed
to continue with his activities?
I'll tell you why.
Because someone
has protected him.
No, not the Father in Heaven,
as you might suppose,
but Stormtroop Leader
Fritz Gerte.
Why have you done all this?
You know very well why.
What do you expect me
to do about it?
You're a clever girl, Christine,
and I want you to use your brains.
Ask yourself whether yours
is the right attitude
towards someone who is
risking so much for your sake.
I'll talk to Father.
I promise you
he'll be more careful.
That is very good, Christine,
but I'm afraid it is not quite enough.
What do you want?
Think of me as someone...
who has helped you,
and who does not enjoy
being treated like a piece of dirt.
Take your time to
think over what I've said.
- Can I go now?
- Certainly.
CHRISTINE:
Father?
Yes, my dear?
- You weren't sleeping.
- No, I couldn't get off somehow.
You're worried, aren't you?
Yes, I am a little.
Pippermann came to me
after the service today.
Said they all wanted me
to stop my criticisms.
Will you?
I don't know. I don't want to
make it hard for the people.
Father...
Perhaps you could be a...
Well, a little more careful.
Oh, is the new spirit
winning you, too?
No, of course not. But...
I do think
you underrate the danger.
Oh, I don't think
there is any, my dear.
By the way, I didn't see
little Lina in church this morning.
I know.
She practically used to live here.
Since she came back
from the labour camp,
she hasn't called once.
I would never have
believed that the Reich...
Well, don't begin now.
When you start doubting friends,
there's only one thing to do,
and that's to go straight to them
and have it out.
- Is it?
- Yes, my dear.
That's what we're going to do.
Come along.
Oh.
- Hello, Herr Pastor.
- Good afternoon, Herr Veit.
I wanted to speak to you
at church today,
but you left so quickly.
You see, I...
had some urgent business,
Fräulein Christine.
Well, aren't you going to
ask us in, Herr Veit?
Of course, Herr Pastor.
Come in, please.
I'm sorry. You see,
I wasn't expecting you.
Uninvited guests on the Sabbath,
eh, Herr Veit?
Oh, it isn't that. I...
Where is Lina? We haven't
seen her since she came back.
- Oh, Lina isn't very well.
- Oh, the poor dear.
- That's why I, er...
- Is she in her room?
- I'll go up and see her.
- Fräulein...
She's asleep. I...
I don't want her disturbed.
Oh, don't worry, Herr Veit.
I'll go very quietly.
Fräulein Christine...
I'm sorry there isn't a fire.
Herr Veit, we've been
friends for a long time.
Won't you tell me
what's the matter?
[SOBBING]
Christine...
- Christine...
- Oh, Lina, darling.
Yes, ssh. Quiet.
It'll be all right.
- Christine...
- Ssh...
Lina...
Lina, tell me
what's the matter.
Oh, I can't believe it.
Lina's little more
than a child herself.
I couldn't believe it either,
but it's true.
It's true.
I should never have let her
go to the labour camp.
I didn't know
what was the matter.
I didn't understand.
Now, I've brought
disgrace on Daddy.
He can't hold up
his head anymore.
Do you know
the name of the boy?
Yes.
Lina did tell me.
Helmut Weber.
And the camp?
Kombach.
My dear Pastor, hundreds of girls
pass through this camp every month.
You can't expect me to enquire
into the morals of each one of them.
It isn't a question
of morals in this case.
I've known the girl all her life.
- She's only a child.
- Yes, yes, I know.
A young, innocent girl
suddenly finds herself in trouble,
through no fault of her own.
It's an old story.
I hear it every day.
And you do nothing about it?
This is a labour camp,
not a kindergarten.
My job is to turn
these boys and girls
into virile, obedient
German citizens,
conscious of the
destiny of their race.
Herr Kommandant,
I fear that you and I
speak a different language,
but this, I hope, I can
make you understand.
This girl, Lina, came here
filled with pride in the belief
that she could serve her
Führer and her Fatherland.
She has returned home,
broken in spirit,
humiliated, dismayed.
Surely that is not the way
you're going to make her
"conscious of the
destiny of her race"?
Well, what do you
suggest I can do?
We can, at any rate, try and undo
some of the evil that's been done.
I'd like to speak to
the boy responsible.
Very well, if you
think it worth your while.
- The name?
- Helmut Weber.
Helmut Weber?
Why, you must be mad.
This boy is the nephew of one of
the biggest men in the country.
Someone right at the top.
I am not concerned
with his social position.
I want to ask
if he'd be prepared
- to marry her.
- Marry? You are mad.
A boy with a
brilliant career ahead of him?
And what of the girl's career?
She seems to have
fixed that for herself.
The supreme career
of every true German woman,
to be the mother
of future Germans.
Herr Kommandant, this girl
is only fourteen.
- She isn't old enough...
- Biologically speaking,
she has proved that she is.
Herr Pastor, you're making
a lot of fuss about nothing.
What has happened to this girl is,
after all, what she was made for.
To call it a tragedy
is reactionary nonsense,
and National Socialism has
no time for that sort of thing.
Now, I'm afraid I'm busy.
Good day.
[BELL JANGLING]
Hello, Father.
Well?
Dr Köhl is up with her now.
I've been looking after her
while Herr Veit was out.
- And how is she?
- Father, she's so miserable.
- Hello, Hans.
- Ah, Friedrich.
Christine told me where you'd gone.
- Any news?
- They'll do nothing.
Hmm, I was afraid of that.
Father, I'll go up to her.
How is she?
I must tell you the truth.
- I don't think Lina's going to live.
- What?
It's an ordeal
even for a grown woman.
She's such a
delicate little thing.
She hasn't the strength,
or the will.
But there must be
something we can do?
Yes, we can pray for her.
That's about all there is to do.
The only real way we
could help her, we daren't.
It's a crime against a state
wanting soldiers for the next war.
But isn't there anything
I can do?
If you can alter
her frame of mind,
make her feel happier,
free her from shame and fear,
she might have a chance.
But you mustn't
worry about it, Lina.
- [KNOCKING]
- Who's that?
It's me. Pastor Hall.
Don't let him come in.
Oh, don't be silly, dear.
Come in, Father.
Hello, Lina.
Well?
Haven't you got a smile
for an old friend?
Oh, Herr Pastor,
I'm so ashamed.
Now, you have nothing
to be ashamed of.
No-one can blame you for something
that's happened without your fault,
or your understanding.
They will, Herr Pastor.
I know they will.
They'll say I've been wicked,
and they'll point at me
and stare.
They'll say I'm bad,
and I've brought
disgrace on them all.
I couldn't stand it,
Herr Pastor.
I couldn't stand it!
I'd rather die!
PASTOR:
Quiet, Lina, quiet.
You're imagining horrors
that'll never happen.
The people here are your friends.
They're not going to
turn against you now,
just because you had
a little trouble.
No, it'll make them
love you all the more.
- Do you really think so, Herr Pastor?
- I know it will.
You're just frightening yourself.
Why, you were even
scared of me.
Now, you're coming
to church next Sunday.
I'll look out for you,
and you'll sit there,
as you always used to,
listening to the sermon,
with your big blue eyes
wide open.
Do you mean
I may come to church?
I insist. You must.
Now, I shall be
disappointed if you don't.
You won't disappoint me,
will you?
I promise.
And, Lina...
I want you to remember
one thing more.
It's the world's
most beautiful story.
How a young mother,
almost a child, like you,
had to ride on a donkey.
And she was so poor,
and friendless,
that she could only
find shelter in the stable.
There were people
who despised even her,
refused to let her in.
There've always been wicked
and silly people in the world.
I'm afraid that hasn't changed much
in two thousand years.
But here, you're
among friends.
And even if one should be unjust,
or say cruel things to you,
just remember
what they said to her.
Will you do that for me?
I promise.
PASTOR:
Now, forget about such things.
What may seem
ugly and frightening now
can become a thing
of great beauty.
Goodbye, dear.
Now, get dressed, Lina,
and come downstairs.
- And don't forget next Sunday.
- I won't forget.
Why, Herr Veit.
Are you ill?
No, I'm not ill.
If you're worrying about Lina,
I can ease your mind.
I've convinced her
that the people here
will be sympathetic
and understanding.
They won't, Herr Pastor.
It isn't true.
Now, you're imagining things.
VEIT: It isn't imagination.
I've heard the things
they're saying about Lina.
PASTOR:
What things are they saying?
Oh, cruel, heartless things.
But I don't believe
that anyone even knows.
Oh, they all know.
They're all talking about it.
Pippermann's
got hold of it somehow.
He says she's a Jezebel who ought
to be turned out of the village.
PASTOR: I shouldn't pay
any attention to Pippermann.
- We all know what he is.
- It's not only Pippermann.
The Frau Linde says
that even if she shows
her face in the street...
Don't worry.
They won't do anything.
I'll see to that.
What can you do?
I'll go to every one of
the villagers if need be.
I'll make them see how unjust,
how despicable they're being.
Oh, people aren't like
they used to be.
They've become bitter and cruel.
Herr Veit, I implore you,
don't let Lina even suspect
the things that are being said.
But she will hear.
I promise you, I will
stop these evil tongues.
- Thank you, Herr Pastor.
- I'll go up and tell her you're home.
Now, she'll be down
in a minute.
Don't let her see
that you've been upset.
No, I won't.
Well, you're very good
to us all, Herr Pastor.
[SCREAMING]
PASTOR:
Lina didn't kill herself.
She was murdered
by National Socialism.
CHRISTINE: There's nothing
we can do now.
PASTOR: I can do what
I should have done before.
If I hadn't failed in my duty,
Lina might be alive tonight.
CHRISTINE:
But they're too strong.
PASTOR: Truth is strong.
Honesty and faith are strong.
My weapons are
the weapons of God.
I will make my people see the evil
of this faith they're embracing.
Father, you mustn't!
These people will stop at nothing.
Already, they have records
of things you've said and done.
I, too, have a record
of what they have done.
Oppression, brutality.
On Sunday, in the pulpit,
I will read it.
It will be its own indictment.
I will pray my people to join me
in fighting this vile disease.
CHRISTINE:
Father, I'm afraid.
Christine,
we can think of ourselves
no longer.
It is the test that I knew was coming,
and I shall not cry,
"O Lord, why hast thou
chosen me?"
One litre today, please.
Sorry, only half a litre allowed.
New order of the Nazis.
We have to draw in our belts.
They'll be drawing
their belts around their necks
before our Pastor's
finished with them.
He's going to give them
something to think about.
What's the Pastor going to do?
He's got a whole list of
everything bad that's happened
since the Stormtroopers came here.
He's going to urge the village
to fight National Socialism.
And do you know
what else she told me?
Thanks for the information,
Pippermann.
I shan't forget.
Thank you,
Herr Stormtroop Leader,
but, with me,
duty is its own reward,
and I have never been one
to try to profit
by the small services
I give my neighbours.
Yes, yes, yes.
Good day.
But, if the Herr Stormtroop Leader
feels impelled to make some return
for the favour I have done him,
then, er... perhaps the next time
his men's boots need repairing?
I can assure the Herr Stormtroop Leader
I use only the very best leather.
All right, Pippermann.
They shall come to you,
even if you use
the very best cardboard.
- Now, get out.
- Thank you, Herr Stormtroop Leader.
That finally cooks your
Pastor's goose, I suppose.
Shall I arrest him?
No.
Now, keep your eyes shut.
Now, you can open 'em.
Uncle, what is this?
- Werner!
- Christine!
Darling!
Let's have a look at you.
There's a line that
wasn't there before.
And a wrinkle round your mouth.
You've been laughing too much.
Darling, it's lovely
to have you back.
- So many things have happened.
- I know, darling.
I've heard of nothing else
since I came back.
Don't let's worry
about that now.
[CLEARING THROAT]
There's nothing I enjoy more
than disturbing a couple of lovers.
I suppose it is because nobody
wants to hug me nowadays.
- Don't be silly, Uncle Paul.
- It's funny, you know.
You only get the
nicest bit of the joint
when you've got no teeth left
to bite it with.
By the way,
have you told her?
- Well, do you think I should, sir?
- Well, why not?
- She's got to know some time.
- All right.
- Well, you're going to be married.
- Yes, I know that.
Ah, but you don't know you're
going to be married tomorrow.
- Don't be silly.
- No, I mean it. Look.
Christine, I've been offered
the most wonderful job in America,
and they want me
to leave at once.
Oh.
I know it's
a bit of a rush, but...
Well, it's the chance
I've been waiting for,
and I mustn't lose it.
Well, Friedrich,
it's all fixed up.
Oh, splendid, splendid.
Daddy...
Werner, I can't go yet.
- Not until I know...
- Paul, this little girl of mine
imagines I can't get on
without her protection.
Nonsense. I'll look after
the old scoundrel.
I can do. I may be an old warhorse,
but I'm not a lame one.
No, I...
- I can't go.
- But, Christine...
Nonsense.
My dear, you're overwrought.
What you want's
a change of air.
You're right, Paul.
You're right.
Well, let's get to the wedding feast.
Come along!
Unless, of course,
you've pinched the dinner again?
The Pastor, please.
- He's engaged at the moment. I...
- Where's his study?
It's there, but he's not in it.
Please tell him
I'm waiting for him.
Would you come out a moment,
Herr Pastor, please?
Excuse me, please.
Now, he's going to
keep us waiting again!
So it is true you've
decided to denounce
National Socialism
from the pulpit.
Your information,
as usual, is correct.
I have come here to warn you
for the last time, Pastor.
Please put those notes
back on my desk.
No. I have the right to
confiscate dangerous documents,
wherever I find them.
You're wasting your time,
Herr Gerte. I shall still speak.
Very well.
Will you please call
Fräulein Christine here?
I wish to speak to her.
No, I'm afraid
that's impossible.
It would be in your interest
as well as hers,
if you call her here at once.
I am not going to interrupt the
little family party we're now having.
Christine is getting married
to General von Grotjahn's son.
They're leaving Altdorf immediately.
I don't think there'll be
time for another talk.
I see.
You'll excuse me.
"A little of what you fancy
does you good,"
as the girl said
to the soldier.
Don't you think you'd better
try another kind of story, Father?
No, no, Werner. Your father's going to
be allowed to say what he likes tonight.
Nobody's going to be shocked.
Oh, well you won't get
another whistle out of me.
Primitive Puritan!
What's the good of saying things
if nobody's going to be shocked?
Well, thank Heaven this isn't going
to be one of your sniffy weddings,
with uncles and aunts staring
every stitch off the bride's back.
Look at all the presents
I shall be missing.
Pretty tough on me, you know.
I shall have to be
inside the church tomorrow.
Can't go pacing about
waiting outside for you, Friedrich.
Well, I promise I'll make it short.
Well, that's something
to be hoped for.
CHRISTINE:
It doesn't seem real at all.
You know, I simply can't believe
I'm going to leave Altdorf.
Oh, don't get sentimental.
I shall cry into me wine.
Oh, there's no harm
in looking back
when there's so much
to look forward to.
We'd better toast
the young couple, Paul.
- What, me?
- Mmm.
I can fight, and curse,
and command, and spit,
but don't ask me
to make a speech.
- Besides, that's your job, anyway.
- Oh, all right.
Here's to you, Christine.
And to you, Werner.
And to your future
in a free and great country.
Here's to your strength
and your happiness,
and the lives that you build
for yourselves, without interference.
And here's to the day when
we shall come back
and take you both away with us.
And here's to our
future grandchildren.
The little soldier,
the little parson,
and the kicks they'll give each other
all day long.
WERNER: I shouldn't be surprised
if the little parson
got the better
of the little soldier.
Well, at least you know
what's coming to you, me boy.
[ALL LAUGHING]
Pastor Friedrich Hall.
You are now a prisoner of the State.
Please, come.
May God be praised.
Daddy! You can't take him!
He hasn't done anything!
How dare you?
Pastor Hall is an enemy
to National Socialism,
and a traitor to the State.
March!
Why are they waiting?
What are they going to do?
Prisoners party, forward!
- [HEAVY BLOWS]
- [PRISONERS GROANING]
Line up here.
Here they are.
Thirty-two of them.
- Heil Hitler.
Now, listen to me,
you dirty scum.
What some of you
have experienced before
is nothing to what
you're going to get here.
You're coming inside
a concentration camp,
and that means
you're coming to hell.
Any attempt at
opposing authority,
and you'll be shot
out of hand.
And you'll be wise if you keep away
from the wire fence around this camp.
It's charged with
a thousand volts of electricity.
The guards have orders to
shoot anyone who approaches it.
Every bullet
costs twelve pfennig,
and that is just
what you're worth.
No more, no less.
Now, get over to that shed.
We're going to make you look pretty.
Oi, you there.
You with the cap.
You mean me?
Yes. Come here.
GUARD: You see what I mean
about keeping away from that fence.
What are you hanging about for?
Get into that shed!
You are finished.
Next.
[WHISPERING]
Watch your step with that man.
He's the Black Superior,
put over prisoners like you and me
because he's a hardened criminal.
He's got a free hand.
Please, you mustn't cut my beard.
It's against my religion.
A Jew with a religion!
Put your head back,
or I'll cut your blasted throat.
Next.
- Name?
- Friedrich Hall.
- Profession?
- Pastor.
Well, you'll soon
get out of that here.
Don't expect to be treated soft
because you've got a degree
and know the Lord's Prayer
by heart.
Watch your step.
Next.
I've got a pleasant
surprise for you.
You've been assigned
to Barrack Seven.
My barrack.
Mind you jump to it
when I tell you what to do.
Barrack Seven, left dress!
Number Two,
pull your belly in.
Number Four,
half a pace to your rear.
You!
Did you hear me?
- I didn't know you were addressing me.
- Well, you do now.
That should be good enough
to draw back your right shoulder,
and place your hands
down the seam of your trousers.
We don't stand for
any individualism.
PRISONER:
Here, Freundlich!
Put him in the rear rank.
He'll spoil the whole damn squad.
Shut your ugly mug.
Were you put in charge
of this squad, or was I?
We're now going to join
the rest of the camp.
Barrack Seven,
left turn!
Quick march!
He's been there ten hours.
They said he was
slow with his work.
GUARD: Left! Left!
Left! Right! Left!
Pick 'em up, you lazy little...
Squad, halt!
Right turn!
Wake up, there.
Wake up!
Heinrich Degan!
Why, Herr Pastor!
Get back in the line there!
What the hell do you
think you're up to?
GUARD:
Squad, left dress!
Squad, hut!
Heil Hitler.
- Anything to report?
- Fifteen men ill,
twenty-seven in detention cells,
twenty-two new arrivals.
Punishments?
- Johann Herder.
- On what grounds?
Because, while peeling potatoes,
he started making
propaganda against the State.
Herder, step forward.
What exactly did you say?
No lies, please.
We were...
We were peeling potatoes.
Then, a phrase came
into my mind,
which the Apostle Paul wrote.
"A seed shall be sown
in unrighteousness,
"but shall arise in glory.
"It shall be sown in weakness,
"but shall arise in strength."
That's meant to be
a threat, isn't it?
A warning, Herr Kommandant.
The world is full of sin.
Antichrist rules on Earth.
By "Antichrist", perhaps
you mean our leader?
I mean the spirit of evil, sir.
Corporal Ludecker.
Twenty-five lashes,
tomorrow morning.
The entire camp to be present.
See to it.
But I'm too old
for such treatment.
I gave my sons to the Fatherland
during the war.
I'm seventy-four years old.
That's something you should have
thought of before. Fall in.
Get back into line.
There are a number of
new arrivals here today,
and I want to make it quite clear
that I'll have
no slackness in the camp.
Greater Germany
allows no weakness,
no failures,
no excuses.
You will learn to realise that the
State is greater than the individual.
There will be special exercise
before the evening meal.
Corporal Ludecker,
you will take over the squad.
Heil Hitler.
Squad...!
Left! Right! Left! Right! Left!
Come here, you.
Can't you run?
What's your name?
- Erwin Kohn.
- Immigrant, aren't you?
Yes, sir.
Didn't the Paris ladies
in their undies please you?
What did you come back for?
What do you think's
going to happen to you?
That I'll be allowed to live.
You'll be lucky if you're
allowed to die.
Get back in the line and run!
Left! Left!
Left! Right! Left!
Left! Right! Left! Right!
[DOOR BEING LOCKED]
[LABOURED BREATHING]
[COUGHING]
There's your lot.
Sit up, my boy.
Here, this will
make you feel better.
Thank you.
Isn't it yours?
No, no, I couldn't eat it.
I feel a little sick.
FREUNDLICH: Here, you fat-bellied
swine. Give me some of that.
We're all equal here, you know.
And someone's pinched
that half-loaf of bread of mine.
Was it you?
Well?
You stole it from Herder.
You damned liar!
Not so quick with your hands.
I've knocked off better men
than you in my time.
All right, Karsch,
you've been asking for it!
Shut up, the pair of you!
Haven't you anything better to do
than bash your own faces?
Don't we see enough violence
without that?
You shut your mouth, or you'll
see some violence, all right.
Oh, God, if I could
only get out of here.
Why the devil
did you come back,
if you were safely in Paris?
Why?
Every morning in Paris, I went
for a walk in the Bois de Boulogne.
One morning in April, I saw
buds on the branches of a tree,
and everything smelt of spring,
and everybody was laughing
and happy for no reason.
I...
don't know why.
Suddenly, I felt homesick.
I couldn't bear
the thought of everybody
speaking in a foreign language.
I saw the birches on the Wannsee
and smelt the scent of the Mark.
I rushed back to my hotel,
packed my bag,
borrowed my railway fare,
and came back here.
Can you understand it?
Not me.
I prefer my freedom.
But isn't it your Fatherland also?
My Fatherland is...
wherever freedom is.
ERWIN: I didn't want
to believe any longer
what was written
in the French newspapers.
"It isn't possible,"
I said to myself.
"I've known these men,
Müller and Schmidt.
"They were kind-hearted men
who lived and let live.
"They can't have become
murderers and sadists overnight."
I felt I had to see them,
take them by the hand.
"There you are, runaway,"
they said.
Then we'd go to...
Alexanderplatz,
and have a beer.
There was one Jew here
whom they boiled, salted and pickled.
I can't stand it.
I can't stand it any longer!
Tried to make them understand,
but they won't listen.
Oh, God, get me out of here!
[SOBBING]
Steady, boy, steady.
Stop that.
[WAILING INTENSIFIES]
Did you hear what I said?
Stop blubberin',
or I'll lay you out.
I'm sorry.
You'll soon settle down.
But don't start that stuff again.
Hey, you.
Come out here.
Come out here,
you stinking pig.
He's talking to you.
Get outside.
Lights out!
Why have they taken him?
To be beaten up.
To make a bit of private sport
for the guard.
They come and pick
their victims every night.
[MAN SCREAMING]
[SCREAMING CONTINUES]
"Our Father, which art in Heaven,
"Hallowed be thy name.
"Thy kingdom come..."
[INAUDIBLE]
[DOOR OPENING]
- [DOOR CLOSING]
- [KEYS JANGLING]
[FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING]
GENERAL: Don't let him see
that you've been worrying too much.
[WEAKLY]
Christine!
Daddy! Oh, Daddy!
Oh, my Christine, my Christine.
How are you?
Are you all right?
I'm all right.
- Hello, Paul.
- Hello, old man.
It's good to see you.
Is it...
Is it very bad?
Not so bad
I can't endure it.
That's the important thing.
Father, we're going to
get you out of here soon.
Uncle Paul has been
working like mad,
seeing his friends,
and pulling strings.
It's only a matter
of time, old fellow.
Thank you, Paul.
And you too, Christine.
Seeing you has
given me fresh courage.
Sorry, Fräulein,
it's time for you to go.
But we've only ju...
But you're Heinrich Degan!
Visiting time's up.
Goodbye, Christine.
I shall think of you.
Don't let them
get you down, old man.
Please God, I won't.
Herr Pastor...
[INAUDIBLE]
Mmm, this is a surprise.
I haven't seen you since...
the time I asked you here.
- I've seen my father.
- Have you?
That's why I've come to you.
This is flattering.
Do you think your
future husband would approve?
Listen, Fritz Gerte, I'm not
in a conversational mood.
I've just come back
from a visit...
to hell.
Last time I was here,
you told me to think.
Well,
I've done some thinking
these last few weeks.
And the conclusion
you've come to?
Fritz Gerte,
you got my father
into a concentration camp.
You must get him out.
So that you and young von Grotjahn
can take him off to America?
I might have appealed to you once,
but I've learned things lately.
If you get my father out,
I'll do whatever you say.
You have a
generous nature, Christine.
Very well,
I'll get him out of the camp.
That's how it is, isn't it?
Yes.
That's how it is.
Very well,
Stormtroop Leader Gerte.
The terms of the order
are quite clear.
Conduct the Stormtroop Leader
to Barrack Seven.
He wishes to speak to
the prisoner Friedrich Hall.
Very good, Herr Kommandant.
Heil Hitler.
Get up.
In there.
Stay outside.
I want a few words with you,
unofficially.
Yes.
Please, forget for a moment
that I am your superior officer.
You aren't a young man
any longer, Pastor Hall.
This camp is hard,
and we can't make exceptions.
I have done everything I can.
Thank you.
But I intend to do more.
At great risk to myself,
I am going to get you out of here.
- Get me out?
- Yes.
Merciful God.
You've only to sign this,
and you will be released.
What does it say?
Just a paper, saying that
you will in future refrain
from any criticisms of
the Party or the Führer.
Naturally, you'll have to keep quiet
about everything you have seen.
Well?
I will not keep quiet
at man's behest
when God commands me to speak.
Don't be a fool, Hall.
God can't help you here.
No, no, I will not sign.
When I leave this place, I'll shout
its horrors from the house-tops.
You are making things
damnably difficult.
PASTOR: These evils cry aloud to Heaven
for a voice to denounce them.
GERTE:
Silence!
PASTOR:
No, there'll be no silence now.
You and I stand face to face,
unmasked in the sight of God.
The words I speak
will belong to another.
Not to me,
but they shall be spoken.
GERTE: You damn fool.
If they hear you, you will be flogged.
PASTOR:
I dare you to do it.
They're here...
The time has come!
Hall, I implore you.
I denounce you
in the name of God!
And, with you, I denounce
the rulers of this country,
their whole system, this vile growth
bred in darkness and hate,
which tortures bodies' lives
and murders souls, decrees that
men should be kicked and beaten
like beasts of the field,
drags them on their face
when they're too weak to walk,
and flogs them to death when
they whisper the words of God.
- Stop that man!
- I denounce this Hitler,
architect of evil.
Creator of human misery.
- [HEAVY BLOW]
- [PRISONERS GASPING]
Damn you, you swine.
COMMANDANT:
Put him in solitary confinement.
Tomorrow, he's to receive
twenty-five lashes
before the assembled camp,
and the same every morning
until further notice.
I suggest, Herr Stormtroop Leader,
that you go.
COMMANDANT:
Prisoner, forward.
[COUGHING]
Well, his number's up.
Damn fool, to start
preaching like that.
Shut up. If only
Germany had more like him.
Start the punishment.
The prisoner will count.
[WHIP CRACKING]
Stop.
I ordered the prisoner
to count.
Count, d'you hear?
Count!
Begin again.
- [WHIP CRACKING]
- One...
- Speak up.
- Speak up!
- PASTOR: Two.
They'll flog him again tomorrow.
I can get him
out of the camp, all right,
but that's about all.
The rest's up to you.
But it must be done tonight.
Is this a trap?
Do you want to see him shot?
Why do you want to help him?
They'll flog him
again tomorrow.
I can't bear it.
[QUIET CHATTERING]
[KEYS JANGLING]
Hey.
You, there.
Him?
Kick him awake!
He wants you.
Get up.
[GROANING]
[PRISONERS MUTTERING]
He's had lashing today.
You can't do any more to him.
Have your fun with someone else.
Any other volunteers?
- Who's there?
- It's me.
- You got a cigarette?
- Sure.
[WHISPERING]
Herr Pastor, quick.
[ALARM BLARING]
What the devil's that?
Keep your eyes open.
Shoot anyone
who tries to escape.
Come on, down.
Keep away from
the doors and the windows.
Anybody seen
will be shot.
Get to the wires. Quickly!
[ALARM CONTINUES BLARING]
[GUNSHOT]
[BRAKES SQUEALING]
Werner, quick!
[MULTIPLE GUNSHOTS]
[BIRDSONG]
Christine!
Father.
Father, dear.
Where is this?
It's all right, darling.
You're at Uncle Paul's.
Why am I at Uncle Paul's?
We brought you here last night,
after you escaped.
Escaped, I remember.
There was...
the lights,
and then the wires.
Degan.
Where is Degan?
Degan was killed.
[GROANING]
Father...
Uncle Paul is going to
get you away from here,
and you're going to
stay with a friend of his.
And then, when Werner and I
go to America,
you're coming with us.
- Isn't he, Werner?
- Of course he is.
- We're just going to kidnap you, sir.
- Thank you, Werner.
God has been very good
to me and my friends.
Where is Paul?
He's planning your escape,
just as if it was a major campaign.
And, as soon as he's got you
safely hidden away,
he's going to the Minister of War,
in full uniform,
just to insist on
your being set free.
Free...
- [MARCHING FOOTSTEPS]
- MAN: Squad, halt!
Right turn!
WERNER: It's Fritz Gerte
and his Stormtroopers!
We were, at least,
allowed to dream.
Werner, help Father to get dressed.
Then, tell Uncle Paul.
We must get him out
by the back way.
I want to see
General von Grotjahn.
This way.
Wait here.
Christine.
Well?
Have you any news?
- Is he going to be released?
- Released?
My father. You promised...
Don't tell me you don't
know what's happened.
To Father?
What have they done to him?
Tell me.
He's escaped.
- When?
- Last night.
He hasn't been
recaptured?
Not yet.
Where's the General?
- You're not suggesting that...
- The General has a car.
A car was used
in your father's escape.
Aren't you being
rather ridiculous?
I intend to examine his car.
PASTOR:
That won't be necessary.
- Father!
- You're my prisoner.
Why did you come down?
Degan has been killed.
I am not going to let anyone else
suffer for my sake.
What the hell's going on?
Pastor Hall is my prisoner.
He's nothing of the sort.
Pastor Hall's under my protection.
I'll answer for him.
Please, Paul,
and you, too, Christine,
you mustn't become
involved in this.
- Let me go with him.
- I won't.
I won't!
If you dare touch him,
I'll tell the whole story
of how you bargained
for Father's safety.
Come on, you.
Gerte, I'm master in this house,
and I never did like
rags about the place.
You're all under arrest.
About turn!
Even you won't get away
with this, General.
Werner, take this toy soldier
down to the cellar.
He'll probably drink
some of my Tocai.
I don't think so, Father.
The Stormtroop Leader's
going to be rather busy
for the next quarter of an hour.
Get on!
Go on!
- [BELL TOLLING]
- Well, that's that. Now...
Better get a move on, quick,
before they come after their leader.
- Are you ready, Friedrich?
- Why, it's Sunday.
You and Werner,
take him out the back way.
Better push the car
as far as the road,
and then make for
Colonel von Kohl's house...
I'd forgotten
there was such a day.
CHRISTINE:
Uncle, you must come too.
GENERAL: Don't worry, lady.
They won't touch me.
- Morning service is beginning.
- CHRISTINE: You can't stay here now.
- At any moment...
- GENERAL: Oh, don't worry about me.
I'm enjoying myself.
You go along to von Kohl's,
and get him to lend
your father some clothes.
Paul?
Could we get
as far as the church?
What do you mean?
- My place is in the pulpit.
- Father!
Not wise, old fellow.
They'll shoot you on sight, you know.
Were you wise in what you did?
Yes, that's it.
Paul, would you desert your men
on the eve of a great battle?
Don't be damn silly.
That is what you're
asking of me.
Father, darling,
please listen to me.
I've always stood by you.
Even when I realised the dangers
into which you were running,
I didn't ask you
to give in, keep silent,
because I knew, in my heart,
that you had to have your way.
But now, what you
want to do is insane!
Would you have me creep through
my own back door, like a criminal?
Yes, because you have
the right to live.
Because we need you, too.
I cannot sacrifice the truth,
even for you.
But they won't let you preach.
GENERAL:
She's right, old man.
There's a new pastor.
Nazi brand.
Father, they'll kill you.
I shall live.
It will be a fire
that no might can put out.
Even a very little flame shines
very brightly in the darkness.
The meek will tell the meek,
and they will become strong again.
One man will tell another
that Antichrist rules,
and they will find strength
to follow my example.
Shall we go?
You make me very proud.
I've got my pride, too.
I've been proud of my uniform
all my life.
My father was proud of it,
and his father before him.
So, if you don't mind,
old fella,
I'll come too.
NAZI PASTOR: The Gospel according
to Saint Matthew, Chapter Ten,
Verses Thirteen, Fourteen,
and Fifteen.
"And whosoever shall not receive you,
nor hear your words,
"as ye go forth out of that house
on that city,
"shake off the dust of your feet.
"Verily, I say unto you,
"it shall be more tolerable
from the land of Sodom and Gomorrah
"in the Day of Judgement
than for that city."
[CONGREGATION MURMURING]
The Pastor's here.
Can't you see?
Get out.
I have little time
in which to speak to you,
and so I want you
to listen with your hearts.
The text for this,
my last sermon to you,
is from Saint Paul.
"Put on the whole armour of God,
"that ye may be able to stand
against the wiles of the devil.
"For we wrestle not against
the flesh and blood,
"but against principalities,
against powers,
"against rulers of
the darkness of the world,
"against spiritual wickedness
in high places.
"Stand therefore,
gird loins about with truth,
"and having on the
breastplate of righteousness."
Some of you may have heard me
quote those words before.
But I want you today
to understand them as,
perhaps, you never have before.
I myself have never
understood those words
as I do at this moment,
in the great clearness
of evening light,
with the shadows approaching.
Do you really think it'll be
necessary to use violence?
You'll keep out of this.
You've done your part, I'll do mine.
Remember my orders.
He's to be shot trying to escape.
- And if he doesn't try to escape?
- He'll be shot trying to escape.
We all know that we are men,
and it does not seem
anything special to us.
Yet, at one moment
in our lives,
the realisation
that we are men
may fill us with
an ecstasy of happiness,
of wonder,
and of meaning.
Men were meant to fight
with the shining sword of the spirit.
Men are not mute animals,
who have to bear injustice silently.
They have been given a voice,
and that voice is meant to be used
as a sword, to fight against
the evil things.
Lies,
wickedness,
cruelty.
The enemies have not changed
since Saint Paul wrote those words.
Only their disguises change,
and the voice of man,
raised in protest,
must be a trumpet of God.
And it will be heard.
You can shut one mouth,
a hundred mouths,
a thousand.
But the voice will be heard.
in spite of stakes,
pillories, barbed wire,
stronger,
louder,
more irresistible.
You have heard of men
enduring the agony of death
with a smile
upon their lips.
Because they have the knowledge
of something bigger
than the mere strength
of life, of the body.
They die as soldiers
on the battlefield of the spirit.
Listen...
Halt!
The same sound
of tramping feet
was heard by
a far greater one than I.
Does it matter,
that they have come to fetch me?
You know I shall be with you,
here, when I have gone.
You know that my voice
will be in your hearts.
You will give my message
to your children.
I shall be with you
every Sunday when you pray.
when you stand up
and fight against that
which you know to be wrong.
I shall be with you
when you cry in despair,
and I shall be with you
when you triumph
over the enemies of God.
Let us pray.
SUBTITLES BY POWERHOUSE FILMS LTD