In 1833, nothing was faster
than horse hooves.
Passengers and letters depended
of horses and men.
And the news wasn't faster
than a fast horse.
But then, like today,
the journalists
they searched without ceasing
the fastest ways
to broadcast the news.
"Swift and truth" was
the axiom of the profession.
Julius Reuter, dedicated his life
to this axiom.
Today the great men of
journalism,
still live for these 2 words:
truth and speed.
It's them, the men
of the fourth power,
what this film is dedicated to.
Here it comes!
- Can I help you?
- No, thank you.
Can I help you?
No, no, no!
Okay!
Welcome, sir.
Could you tell me where it is?
the Bender bank?
- The Bender bank?
- Yes.
Do you see the boy
with the hat?
Yes.
He works there.
Thanks.
I've waited long enough!
Can I have my mail now?
- You'll have to wait.
- Boy.
My name is Julius Reuter.
Sorry, Mr. Reuter. Could you
take me to the Bender bank?
- As soon as you have my mail.
- Thanks.
Uncle! Uncle!
The London and Paris mail
is delayed because of the storms.
When it's not the rain,
It's the drought!
There's always an excuse...
to the inefficiency of
our courier service!
But, wait!
- It's uncle!
- Silence!
That knight wants to see you.
Pardon me.
- It's okay.
- What do you want?
- I want to raise money.
- How much?
100 florins.
Do you have a letter of credit?
Yes.
I am Carew, earthly messenger
from India to England.
From India over land?
It's faster than by sea.
When I arrive in London I bring news
from India at just 1 month old.
When I'm luckier than this time...
But I will make up the time
when you arrive in Cologne.
Cologne?
It's shorter for Hamburg!
A special train
take me to Ostend,
and there, I will cross the English Channel.
Like a special train?
That must cost a fortune!
Julius! Don't be insolent!
It's okay.
Look, boy.
I mean, Mr. Reuters...
that the Times
It is the richest newspaper.
Money is not a problem.
The news is the thing
most important in the world!
Even at 1 month old?
Yes, because you can't have
earlier!
Very soon it will be faster!
There is a teacher who
calls Gauss.
Sends signals via cable
to your friend Weber.
He says they communicate
It's the speed of light.
- Cable!
- If it works.
It will work!
Julius!
Focus on your
work!
But Professor Gauss says...
But can he do what he says?
I am sure!
I need to see it to believe it.
Judge for yourself.
Professor Gauss!
You must not disturb the teacher!
- He's working.
- We come?
Not now.
There he is, with his telescope.
- What's the matter?
- Hans!
What does the teacher do?
Look at the receiver...
because your friend Weber
try to send
cable signals.
If the signals reach here,
will make you vibrate
the magnetic coil
and the teacher will decode the message.
It works!
The signal arrived perfectly.
I knew!
You must write it in
your newspaper!
What should I say?
"Prof. Gauss invented a way
to send signals.”
When the world knows,
will use this invention.
And the threads will multiply!
I did a lot of good coming here.
- What is this?
- Anything.
"Reuter's pigeons
deliver messages faster
than those sent by
stagecoach or messenger."
- It's fascinating!
- Indeed.
I'm talking about pigeons!
Is it something new?
Tell me more!
Let's forget about work.
There is something...
Hang on! What's your name?
Max!
Good morning, Julius!
I entrusted you with a job!
I was going to put up a poster.
And why not here?
People should know
our service.
Didn't I put it here?
No, not even in front of the Chamber
nor at the station.
- Not even in hostels?
- No.
Why make things more difficult?
I can't count on you?
Julius...
Pigeons don't fascinate me as much
like you.
If you help me, you can see them
fly with a paid message.
This would allow us to eat.
This makes me hungry!
Is it useless?
Go back to the office!
You do it very well, Julius!
Send a telegram
to Arnheim.
There is no telegraph line.
Pass through another city.
There is no other line between
Belgium and Germany.
It's a question of
life or death.
An employee put
a wrong label.
I sent the poison to Mrs. Magnus,
and she has already left for Arnheim!
The diligence must stop.
Just one thing to do.
Send a messenger!
Quickly!
Hurry, please!
It will never arrive in time.
- Never!
- But if the horse is fast!
Impossible, due diligence
It takes 6 hours in advance.
When you arrive in Bremen,
these people will be poisoned!
Did Arnheim say?
Come, I can help you.
Who is it aimed at?
Dr. Magnus,
Arnheim hospital.
The message,
please!
"Dear doctor,
I have to..."
No.
This is not a letter!
"Fever medicine
poisoned.
Do not use."
Sign, please.
Is it really 200 km from here?
Yes, by the road.
But don't look at it like a bird.
Max! Max!
This is it...
Why two?
Three will be sent.
To be sure
that a pigeon will arrive.
Risks must be avoided.
- And this one!
Max, where are you?
Max. Why not
to respond?
What happened?
You called, didn't you?
I stumbled
and the door...
They all flew...
Was it all?
Lenchen, my friend,
don't disappoint me.
Human lives are at stake.
Lenchen,
Can I count on you.
You understand!
You can become a hero,
or a heroine...
Do you trust me, Lenchen?
Of course, isn't it?
There it is.
Fly as fast as possible.
Why so much fuss?
A message, Max!
Finally!
Our future flies with Lenchen.
Arnheim.
Your father wants you to go to
the hospital.
Okay, Emma.
Take care of the bags.
- Hi, Geller!
- Hello Miss Magnus.
Hurry, Heinrich!
You have to send them
to Brussels.
These pigeons all arrived today.
Business must be good!
I wish so,
but they arrived together
and no message.
It shouldn't...
trust beginners.
These idiots from Brussels,
they let us escape.
There's another one.
Lenchen!
You too? Come here.
What happened in Brussels?
Why don't any of you
Do you have a message?
You have one!
Give it to me.
"Doctor Magnus,
Central Hospital.”
- Do you have the medicine?
- Yes father.
I hope this eases your mind.
Can I help you?
No, no.
Don't take useless risks.
Fever is contagious.
Send Lenchen with the others!
I gotta go!
Read this.
It could have been horrible.
But... How did it come to
message so fast?
By Reuters.
- Who?
- Julius Reuter.
They call it
"The Pigeon Madman".
Arnheim.
Pigeon crazy!
Hello, Adelaide!
Hello, Geller!
Nice to see you.
Lenchen has arrived
with a message?
Yes.
Wonderful!!
It was what we needed.
- See you soon.
- Where you go?
Business at last
they start to go.
Reuters, come!
I have something to say.
Be brief.
He saw what happened,
understands the advantage of
use my pigeons.
Pigeons!
We did tests...
You said you would tell me
how to make a lot of money!
It's true, but!
It takes 10 hours to go
from Brussels to Arnheim.
I guarantee that my pigeons
takes less than 2 hours.
I'm a banker,
not a pigeon expert!
Your projects do not
interest me.
You haven't heard...
No reasonable business can
depend on pigeons.
They didn't tell you
of the medicine?
I don't listen to more than my common sense.
Don't bother me anymore and leave,
or I'll throw you out on the street!
Don't you know what my pigeon did
faster than diligence!
I don't want to hear any more
of your pigeons.
Outside!
Pigeons!
Geller, he didn't know.
The greatest banker!
We could wait years for a
opportunity like this and kept it secret!
I thought I had sense
to spread the story.
Why didn't you disclose it?
I couldn't.
No?!
Why?
I promise.
Who asked you
this promise?
I'd rather not say.
It was the doctor!
He asked him to keep it secret.
They make mistakes and
Should I pay for them?!
Where are you going, Julius?
Father!
Mr. Reuter is here.
Good. Come in.
Come in, Mr. Reuters.
Mr. Reuter, nice to see you!
Sit down.
What happened?
Did I offend you in something?
Professor Magnus,
I don't like to talk bad
of others,
but my life
It depends on my pigeons.
People laugh at me,
but I didn't give up.
Finally I would have been able to prove that
my pigeons were useful.
But you denied me
this opportunity.
I? As?
- Don't you know?
- No.
Mr. Reuter talks about something
of which I am responsible.
- You?
- Yes.
I asked Geller
to keep it secret.
Sorry, I didn't know that
would harm him.
That doesn't help me,
Miss Magnus.
My business counts more to me
than your secrets.
It's not an intimate secret.
Try to understand.
We save lives
but progress is slow.
Some people still see us
like sorcerers,
and prefer to cure themselves with
superstitions instead of science.
What does it have to do with me?
If this is known, all deaths from
fever will be attributed to poison,
even the ones that happened
a long time ago.
My father and his colleagues
they would pass for murderers.
We couldn't go on
our investigations
and the progress made
they would be lost.
I'm sorry, but I think
that my daughter is right.
Saving lives is more important
than business.
But deciding to tell this story
There's nothing we can do.
Don't worry.
I'm not angry anymore.
When I'm not angry
I can see other people's problems.
Good days.
It's not fair to Reuter,
Aren't you dad?
What can we do?
My Friend, I'm afraid...
I owe you an apology
for your patience and help.
Reuter, won't you think about giving up?
To give up?
It would be very difficult.
But I know I lost.
Lost!
In between.
O Miss Magnus!
What a surprise!
Most of all, in this weather.
I like rain.
But it rains a lot,
and stopped here to dry.
Sit down...
near the fire.
It's a good day to
sitting by the fire,
isn't it?
And it's time to
drink coffee.
Pardon me.
Stay, I'd like to talk
with you.
I have a lot of work.
Mr. Reuter, I came,
because I'm worried
with your visit to my father.
Maybe speaking...
Let's find a solution.
As?
We could find a solution...
that will help you.
Help me find
my slippers.
Slippers?
I am really sorry.
Thanks.
Mr. Reuters.
Don't hate us.
Hate you?
But why?
They did well.
I seem worried, because
I have things to think about.
I don't renounce my pigeons, and...
As?
- What is it?
- A pigeon.
I must go and see.
No, stay.
I go.
Will this carry a message?
And if you bring it?
Mr. Reuter, can I go and see
the dovecote?
Yes, if you want.
Thanks.
Lenchen!
That bird!
He has the heart of a lion.
So this is how they are sent
the messages?
Yes.
Come, Lenchen,
you must be hungry.
Yes, in this little bag.
It's very well folded,
but see,
opens up
to get
a large piece of paper.
See?
Here is the message.
More stock quotes!
Look the other way.
Certainly a word from Max.
What counts, then?
Russia's intervention
Hungary has just been confirmed.
Russia intervenes to
restore peace in Hungary and
maintain order in Poland.
This can create difficulties
in Prussia!
If Poland revolts,
That would be the crisis in Russia,
in England, in France.
Is there a risk of provoking a war?
We could get there,
but anyway,
the stock market will sink tomorrow.
It has just been confirmed.
We won't know anything
in Arnheim until tomorrow.
If the bankers listened to me,
would sell before tomorrow.
But they won't do anything.
You are safe
of this news?
My agent never made a mistake.
That might interest
to my father.
- Goodbye, Mr. Reuter.
- Goodbye.
Goodbye, Mrs. Magnus.
Goodbye, Mr. Geller.
Until the evening?
Of course!
How is it,
Professor Magnus?
Mr Bauer, I was looking for him.
Did you sell my shares like I asked?
Yes, but I don't understand why.
Russia will invade Hungary.
Ah, these are rumors for
weaken the Stock Exchange!
Absolutely.
It has been confirmed.
- Where?
- In Brussels.
In Brussels! Today!
And how did it arrive
the news?
- By heaven.
- The sky?
This is stupid!
Rumors like that
can cost you dearly.
The news arrived here
thanks to a pigeon.
A Reuter's pigeon.
Now I understand!
What does this strange man do?
with Ida?
Strange man?
It's my friend, Julius Reuter.
Why strange"?
Because it doesn't have a look
prosperous...
But after all!
Exactly! After all!
I didn't behave very badly,
why not?
It's okay.
You'll do better next time.
I hope so.
My daughter.
Mr. Stein, Mr. Frank, Mr. Von Constad,
and Mr. Bauer, here is Mr. Reuter.
I already know Mr. Reuter.
M. Reuter, wants to convince us
this nonsense
brought by a pigeon
for some reason invented by you?
Mr. Bauer,
I can tolerate lack of respect
for my desire to innovate,
but not for my integrity.
I hope your apology
after reading the morning newspapers.
French troops are
At the gates of Rome.
Brussels confirms the
Russian intervention in Hungary.
The Hungarians are at their limit
and ponder the uprising.
The Grand Duke of Posen
threatens to take sides
in this movement.
Now, they will believe in you.
Those fools!
Perhaps.
I don't know.
People take a while to see
what goes on in front of their noses.
In between.
Beautiful day after yesterday's storm!
Yes, beautiful day!
How about it, Geller?
Very good, Mr. Bauer.
Exceptionally well.
Great.
Pardon me.
Yes?
I know how to recognize my mistakes.
You were right
and Dr. Magnus
made a good profit.
I'm afraid I misjudged him.
After all, making mistakes is human.
Yes?
Good.
Anyway, sorry.
Now, let's talk business.
It says that pigeons are
faster than a messenger.
I guarantee.
But your service
depends on the electric telegraph.
Soon we will have agents
in every capital of Europe.
They will telegraph the quotations
at the nearest terminal.
Arnheim is the most
close to Eastern Europe.
Brussels is the closest
to the West.
My pigeons will gather
both terminals.
But the telegraph
It's very expensive.
Only the big banks have
the means to use it.
That's what makes my idea original.
A telegram
will be sent to each agent.
The cost will be shared
between bankers and brokers,
and thus it will be more economical.
You have a practical spirit,
not like me.
I accept.
You will be the first to sign.
Please.
I will sign, but with one condition.
Yes?
I will pay for exclusive use of your service.
- Exclusive?
- Absolutely.
Impossible!
Think about it, Reuters!
With this advantage,
we will make a fortune.
Thanks for coming,
Mr. Bauer.
What's wrong with you?
Your proposal doesn't help me
interest.
is smarter than
I thought.
Gave him part of my profits.
No.
What if we join together?
Mr. Bauer,
If I explore this idea,
I will have all the profits.
Without sharing them with you.
But I have other ideas.
I want to build my future
at the service of others.
And that too
could help you.
- Hello Bauer.
- How are you, Constadt?
Constadt, please.
Mr. Reuter, may I have the honor of
Be your first user?
Come, gentlemen.
Mr. Reuter will receive it.
Geller!
- How is Mr. Reuter here?
- Yes, Miss Magnus.
Sorry,
but only subscribers
can enter.
Me neither?
Mr. Reuters said
no exceptions.
Business is business.
Knights,
the first pigeon
You should arrive at 1:30 pm.
Since your arrival,
the door will be locked.
When you finish copying the numbers,
the door will be opened.
Closed?
So that each one
be treated equally.
If you think this is unfair,
he can go.
Sit down, please.
Only 15 minutes left to wait.
I still don't believe it.
It's 13:15 and you
he promised us
Paris, Brussels quotes
and London.
Let's see if he fulfills his promise.
It's here!
Geller, open the door!
Miss Magnus.
I was prevented from entering,
so I came up here.
Was it you who rang the doorbell?
Yes.
I knew you would come.
I'm going to Brussels.
I would like to see you
before leaving.
Why?
To wish you
good luck.
Thank you Miss
Magnus.
If I fail,
It won't be your fault.
You forgive me this
false alarm?
Of course,
but not the subscribers down there.
- I'll warn them.
- Goodbye.
No, no, please.
You can't see it.
I would prefer you to stay.
I'll stay as long as I can.
- Oh, gentlemen!
- So?
It was a false alarm.
He said they would arrive in minutes!
I said at 1:30.
It's already...
Why don't they arrive?
Come.
What if Max let me down?
- What was the scheduled time?
- 13:30.
It's almost 2pm.
Julius! Julius!
What it was?
- They're leaving!
- As?
- Oh, wait!
- The pigeons will come.
- I've waited too long.
A little patience!
I've had a lot of patience.
There they are!
Close the door, Geller!
3% loan 82.40 francs,
5%, 117.40 francs.
They will have London quotes
at 16:00.
Did you write everything down?
Open the door, Geller.
Julius.
For success
of your carrier pigeons!
Must be the man
happier.
Max. My best friend
and my worst enemy.
But, Julius,
Maybe it wasn't your fault.
The quotes were incomplete.
Nobody noticed.
Except me!
We need to be trustworthy.
I don't know what to do.
I must stay here,
but also go to Brussels
to talk to Max.
I could do it!
You?
Yes.
I didn't want to bother her.
But I'm going to Brussels!
I must write a letter.
Death threats
and destruction.
On the contrary, I will tell you
that breaks my heart.
Poor Max, we have to treat him
like a child!
Write the letter,
and deliver it to me before my departure.
Almost forget!
I did something for you.
For me?
Yes.
A little bag.
For your pigeons to carry messages.
But, I don't deserve it...
Now, finish the letter...
before leaving the stagecoach.
Bon voyage!
Thank you, Mr. Geller.
I must say...
I don't know what she sees in you.
What murmurs?
She likes you.
You're crazy.
For God,
What could that beautiful girl do?
to see in me?
- Exactly.
- Clear.
What?
Nonsense!
Gave me one
explosive message.
"Even a saint
I would lose patience with you."
What violence, huh?
I thought you were friends with Mr. Reuter.
Since always!
You should be ashamed.
I suppose I should.
You should pay attention to these signs!
They're good, aren't they?
Excellent.
Mr Reuter did not put them
there to ignore them.
No, I made them.
Look:
"Reuter, the king of speed."
If you have written this,
be up to par.
Does an engineer have to sleep
in the tunnel he built?
It's not funny.
Sorry. Making slogans
I forgot about business.
- Give me a broom.
- What are you going to do?
I'm going to clean this trash can.
Where can I find a broom?
Find one!
Don't throw away my poems!
These are not poems.
No, this is a message
to Reuters.
Poor Julius Reuter!
What time do pigeons come out?
To arrive on time.
- About...
- Be precise.
When exactly?
There it is!
Close the door.
It's catching wind,
Mr. Bauer.
Do I close the window?
No thanks, I prefer some
of fresh air.
Well, as you wish.
Max is perfect.
I did well to write the letter.
What happened?
Bauer's employee
It's here too.
What are you going to do?
Teach Bauer a lesson.
Gentlemen, let's start with London.
These quotes are flying high, my friends
pigeons will lose sight of them!
Stop the jokes!
Give us the numbers.
Consols: 78.5.
Funding Loan: 113 et 4.91%.
Great Western Railway:
2.56.
Liverpool and Birkenhear: 9.05.
That's all London.
Attention,
I made a mistake.
I'll say the numbers again.
Great Western: 2.47.
And Liverpool Birkenhead: 89.
What a fall! More than 3 points.
Stein, write down the numbers for me.
- Open it.
- No, I'm sorry.
I must leave immediately.
No, no, you can't.
Mr. Reuters.
Tell him to let me out!
Of course, if gentlemen
are in agreement.
Here are the numbers for Paris.
Charleroi mining company:
169.75 francs.
Shares of St. Tienne:
278 francs.
Orleans Railway Company:
11.84; 3% slope...
To the bank!
Quickly! Quickly!
Did you see his face?
This will teach you
not to overtake others.
Professor Magnus!
Are you okay?
- Did you come from Brussels?
- Yes.
Did you have a good trip?
Like always.
There were interesting people
in diligence?
Always the same.
Didn't you feel lonely?
Why?
Sometimes, when you travel alone...
No, not my daughter
came with me.
I had a job.
It's a shame.
That tell you that my letter
for Max it worked.
Really?
Oh yeah. Messages arrive
punctual 2 weeks ago.
She will be happy to hear that,
because she runs her office
in Brussels.
But it's impossible!
I also thought,
before seeing her work.
I didn't know, Prof. Magnus.
This is terrible!
What must you think of me!
That's lucky.
But I'm not impartial.
Write to him to thank him.
I knew she was crazy
for you!
She has a quick one.
The bag she made.
Fly as fast as possible.
Put them in
next due diligence.
Why do you send them?
to Arnheim?
Why don't they fly?
When it comes loose
a carrier pigeon,
always returns to your home.
And these pigeons' home is here.
I already understand!
Max!
Did a pigeon arrive?
Silence! I'm in the middle of
composing a poem!
It's desperate!
The answer to the question
that I'm afraid to do
Is it yes or no?
It's no good!
It's better to help her!
Goodbye poetry!
I promise I will dedicate myself
to the pigeons!
Hurry, Lenchen,
He's waiting!
Since he never rests,
brought the food.
- I'm not hungry.
- With the. I watch.
Here it comes!
May I congratulate you?
YES
How did you get it?
The hole between Arnheim
and Brussels is closed!
The lines will work
in a month.
Time passes quickly
when the outcome is uncertain.
It's not fair.
After everything you've done.
Despite prejudices,
the obstacles...
In the end you had won,
and now this...
Lenchen!
What happened?
I found her on the road
killed by a line
by telegraph!
Before, there was nothing there.
One of the workers saw everything.
She has a broken neck!
Back to work, gentlemen.
Crying is no use, dear.
But Lenchen...
Built our future,
wasn't it?
And now, she's dead.
The pigeon mail
died with him.
It's progress, baby.
No one can
oppose progress.
Let this be his epitaph:
"Victim of progress".
The progress
will not destroy us?
Of course not.
Destroyed my business,
but at the same time,
makes the world smaller.
I believe in progress.
How do I believe in a world
what do men
are closer.
The goal of progress
It is knowledge.
And through him,
the truth!
Ah, Max, we're not getting anywhere!
Right.
We should be happy
for earning a living.
But when I go to Paris,
I can't take
my wife!
There are many men
strolling,
except me!
Ida is valid for all women!
Julius, we're in Paris!
Stop praising your wife.
My friends wouldn't understand it.
You should be ashamed of your friends!
I can't offer anything else
with my salary!
I'm a director,
employee, everything!
Ida is not in charge of the
London office?
She has you.
You're right, Max.
There they are!
Yvonne, how about it? Jeanette!
Let me introduce you to my friend, Mr. Reuter.
The news is not very
encouraging, right?
War, always war!
During my life,
it has always been like that.
And I'm already old!
You have seen many changes!
Yes sir. Lots of.
But most of all, the world
advances faster and faster.
Everything arrives so quickly!
My newspapers don't have
more than a day late
and they don't tell us anything.
Sevastopol was taken,
our troops are in Crimea
willing to kill.
We have to read what is hidden.
See here below.
Are you here?
"There will be a meeting
between the Allied General Staff
and the Russian generals."
Is it a sign of peace?
You'll know in a week.
Why?
Louis Napoleon will speak
to deputies.
He will announce peace himself.
The whole world waits
this speech!
The whole world...
Why does Paris always do
Tremble, my heart?
Excuse me!
What's up?
I'm an idiot!
The biggest!
- It's incredible!!!
- Sit down.
- Let's go!
- I can't go.
One moment!
- Will you come back?
- Wait for me.
What's up?
Got crazy?
Worse! I'm an idiot!
You already said it.
You don't understand, Max.
- I should have thought years ago.
- What?
The news!
It's the most important thing in the world!
With the telegraph, the words
they fly at the speed of light.
What does it have to do with you?
Precisely.
Every city in Europe
It is served by the telegraph.
Why not broadcast the
news
as far as messages
personal?
How would you get
all the news?
We have correspondents
all over Europe, don't we?
What about?
They are not reporters.
They are in the heart
of an organization.
You could go visit them
and check your competence.
We need good reporters.
- Let's start soon.
- One moment!
It's a radical idea.
The telegraph works
since years ago.
But no one uses it
for the latest news!
There's a reason for that.
Nobody ever thought about that.
Max, let's telegraph news!
The world will be up to date
fast enough.
Allow me not
be in agreement.
London will be informed
24 hours later!
Without giving advice
to His Majesty,
the best thing would be for you to know
The English react quickly!
What do you propose?
I will reserve the telegraph
between here and London.
Telegraph the speech
to London?
Yes sir.
No one will stop you,
once the speech has been delivered.
Sir.
Yes but...
It will be too late, sir.
Time will be wasted translating
the speech into English.
Sorry, there is no other solution.
Yes, there is, sir.
I need to have the
speech before.
- This has never been done.
- Naturally.
And no speech
It was never telegraphed.
One innovation creates another.
It's progress.
The world must know quickly
what the leaders say,
how they decide their destiny.
And the leaders will know right away
people's opinions.
I would like to create
a new genre of journalism.
And they will know that Louis Napoleon
participated in this creation.
Excellent idea.
His majesty!
I would like to know more about
his "new journalism".
Follow me.
The hotel.
Yes sir.
So?
- They agree.
- Formidable!
On one condition.
Let us wait for
beginning of the speech.
- Will we have enough time?
- If you book the telegraph now.
- Who? I?
- Yes, you.
Nonetheless,
I will prepare everything in London.
Something else?
Lord Palmerston
canceled your appointment.
The man thinks he is more important
than the Times of London?
You will regret it. Anything else?
Mr. Reuter is waiting for you.
I don't have time.
He insists and waits for you.
I will be back in an hour.
Mr. Delane?
- It must be Rooter.
- Julius Reuter.
Forgive me, sir.
I have an important appointment.
You know my proposal.
- But....
- Let me talk.
The Times already has reporters
who write the news.
But that costs a fortune.
You're wasting your time,
it's mine.
The Times will not run
this risk.
Try one month for free.
The Times has its ways,
Mr. Rooter.
- Reuter, Reuter!
- And more,
the idea of ​​a news agency
It's absurd.
We want exclusivity
to be the first!
This is journalism!
The news must
be fresh.
Even a newspaper like the Times
cannot support exclusive use
of the telegraph.
If you use...
I understand.
But we already have one
service abroad.
Which costs £40 a month.
I propose for 30 pounds.
It's a huge risk.
Try one month for free.
Free?
I just ask that you use the name Reuter,
And use your name as the first customer.
That seems fair.
God bless the Scots!
The Advertiser was the first.
Then it was the Post,
the Herald and the News.
- The Times?
- Not yet.
Here's the whole story.
It will be very expensive to rent
the cable from Paris to London.
We don't have that sum.
The money given by newspapers
help us.
- We won't have anything this month.
- What?
I offered the service free of charge
for them to accept.
I'm sorry, Ida.
- Why?
- Stay!
I'll go before I lose
calm and a friend.
As?
- You are completely crazy.
- Perhaps.
Even if it covers the
whole world,
and it works,
the Times will reject it!
These newspapers accepted it for free.
The Times isn't even free!
Every cent you receive
it will be for expenses.
And God knows
who received little.
Your wife deserves better!
Can you lend me
1000 pounds?
As?
We provide you with stock quotes
6 years ago.
He made a fortune,
as well as others,
Thanks to our reliability.
For the first time, I find myself obliged
asking him for something.
- But...
- I know what I do.
Just say yes or no.
- When do you need it?
- Tomorrow.
You will have the money!
Thank you, Sir Randolph.
I won't forget him.
Sir Randolph doesn't like it
of the idea?
I don't think so.
That won't come.
You will have to ask for a loan.
I already did.
How did you borrow it?
Dear,
Let's take a big risk.
It's all or nothing.
You believe in this idea.
The world is still very big.
Let's make it smaller.
And now,
since the news
are under our dominion,
we have to include "news"
in the name of our company.
Yes, Reuters Agency
or something similar.
Or something like that.
The director of the Reuters Agency,
or whatever name you choose,
must be aware
current affairs, right?
As much as possible.
Here is the first task
to perpetuate in our records.
This is nothing exceptional,
but it will always
a good effect.
What?
Know...
from a safe source...
that Julius Reuter,
president and founder
from the Reuters Agency...
Yes?
will be a father.
I? Father?
The Reuter agency is always reliable.
Ida, it's wonderful!
It's the most beautiful news
of the world!
- What are you going to do?
- I'll wire Max.
The business is different now.
We cannot allow
take risks now.
Not with a baby.
From now on, the baby is
the most important thing.
It will be exactly as planned.
We will go on the adventure together.
The three.
Gentlemen Senators
and deputies!
In our last interview,
the circumstances were complex.
The allied troops
were being closed
with an obstinacy that left
glimpse doubts in his final victory.
A message to the Reuters Agency
from London.
I was waiting for you.
I hope too
let the emperor begin.
The emperor! That's why it was rented
the cable for an hour!
The Mourning Herald!
The proclamation of peace!
Special edition!
I need to write to my father...
and Geller too!
I wish they were here.
Julius!
It is a triumph that
transforms journalism!
It's a revolution for
the written press
Let us not exaggerate, my friend.
This man brings the news
of peace to a world at war
without an "I already told you".
I love him even more.
The Times! Special edition!
How did you get the
Times of this speech?
I sent it.
You told me that Delane
refused to subscribe.
He will accept.
Not Delane. He's very stubborn.
He could have been ridiculed if he hadn't...
Mr. Reuters!
Yes?
Mr. Delane would like to see you.
Delane!
- Come in.
- Yes sir.
I want to cry.
Wait for Delane to leave,
we will cry together.
I leave them alone.
- Sir Randolph!
- How are you?
Mr. Rooter...
Reuter, Mr. Delane.
Forgive me, Mr. Reuter.
I would like...
- I want to introduce you to my wife.
- My respects.
- I want...
- Please sit.
The Times is grateful,
Mr. Reuters.
For the first time,
our newspaper
publish a news
from an external company.
"The emperor's speech..."
"received by Reuters Agency."
It's an immense honor,
Mr. Delane.
Come on, say it!
"Delane, what an idiot you are."
I deserve it!
Our agency is accurate
and impartial.
Only the present counts,
the past is ancient history.
What news
bring, Mr. Delane?
Mr. Reuters.
You can add the Times
It's your customer list.
Thanks,
Mr Delane!
I...
I'm afraid I won't be able to wait.
Lenchen!
"An honor that never
renounce.
"Who always rejects.
"Which is called by error
Rooter.
"Weave your skein
"around the world where
we inhabit.
"The oceans will murmur your name.
"That for the whole world,
"Be a guide, a tutor.
"May you be blessed
"as much as Reuters
as much as Rooter."
Amazing!
But where did you learn this?
Are you good for anything?
It's just a small thing...
published by Gazeta
of Saint-James.
All Europe speaks
from you, Julius.
Got your name in the newspapers
more often than anyone.
Baby, you recited
perfectly.
It's time to go to bed.
Say goodnight to dad.
Father. My name will also be in us
newspapers when I'm older?
One day, you will take my place,
and Reuter will be you.
I want that to be the only reason
to get your name in the newspapers!
- Goodnight.
- To the bed!
At your service.
At your service, Mr. Reuter.
He is his father's son.
Julius.
What a beautiful surprise!
My respects, ma'am.
I'll sit by the fire.
It's cold tonight.
Going for coffee?
Thank you very much.
I always liked your coffee.
Julius.
get ready to
a fight.
Fight?
Against the Anglo-Irish Company
of Telegraphs.
I work with them.
Exactly.
Hence their idea.
You can't ban me
to use your lines.
But you can build a
for their exclusive use.
They wouldn't!
They already did.
A private line from Roches Point
to Queenstown.
Where is Roches Point?
Here.
This is where the US mail arrives
and then go to Queenstown.
From there, we ship it to London.
Tell me, Julius,
how long it takes
your messenger to Queenstown?
2 hours.
You will win for 2 hours.
They built this line in secret
a few weeks ago.
Even I ignored it until I
proposed their services.
From when?
Tomorrow.
This is the end of the Reuters Agency.
I want to cancel immediately
my contract.
If you wait until Mr. Reuter arrives.
It's useless.
Why should I pay for news
who arrive 2 hours late?
- Hello, Grant.
- How are you?
Max! Could you see him for a moment?
Of course you do, Mr. Grant.
It's the fifth today,
Isn't that Bruce?
It's true.
- And 3 yesterday?
- Yes.
If cancellations continue,
I'm looking for another job.
Isn't it?
Wrong.
I bet you'll never make it
overtake Reuter.
Thanks, Bruce.
Attention, it could take
part of your bet.
Everything you want.
You are kind.
I need someone
in New York.
Someone trustworthy.
- Would you go?
- Clear.
Great.
Try to understand...
- Oh, Julius!
- Nice to see you.
It won't be much longer.
I know.
The Anglo-Irish beat us
for 2 hours in London.
Many of our customers
they abandon us.
- How do you know?
- That's what you should do!
They pay. If they are not
Satisfied, they leave.
Don't put on that face!
I'm not finished yet.
Your contract is
temporarily suspended.
You will continue to receive free
our messages
until the Reuters Agency
return to the first position.
Inform our customers.
You can't do that!
In time of war
We cannot accept defeat.
Bravo, Reuter!
I hope you win
the Anglo-Irish!
Here's one to cheer
by Reuters Agency.
Where were you? Have you seen Ida yet?
Not yet.
Didn't you write?!
Is Sir Randolph in London?
He is with Ida.
He called when she got a letter
of Anglo-Irish.
What they want?
It's better to read the letter.
- Where is it?
- Ida has it.
"In these circumstances.
we think it's very generous
offer 20,000 pounds
for your company."
- At 20,000 pounds!
- The offer is reasonable.
They have you where they want.
That's what they think!
"We propose what remains
as director
with a salary that will be negotiated."
What audacity!
They want to steal my company!
The money will not be
a problem.
That pleases you, doesn't it?
I'm sorry, but...
You could retire...
Idleness?!
This is my life!
They might as well bury me!
Start a newspaper!
No, I have no opinions to sell,
just news.
What are you going to do, Julius?
- Tidy subject.
- That doesn't answer Ida.
I will respond if you lend me
5,000 pounds.
5,000 pounds?!
It's best you know:
I don't have a penny.
Maybe it needs a lot more.
- Do you want to take a risk?
- I have little.
I invested a lot in the stock market.
The Civil War
continues in America.
What if the South loses?
I would be in a delicate situation.
Take cover.
At least 5,000 pounds.
You are fearsome, Julius.
Accordingly.
Thanks.
We can start!
Julius.
We'll never make it in this weather!
Every day counts, Max.
Men already work
12 hours a day.
Put in another shift.
Let's work 24 hours a day!
More cable!
80 km is a lot!
In 2 weeks we will be finished.
Working night and day.
And if we really end
in 2 weeks?
The mail boat
It doesn't stop at Crookshaven.
It has to stop!
How will we get the mail?
I'll think about it, Max.
- It works!
- It's dry.
Bruce...
You will be my agent
in America.
"Tell my daughter
in my presence!"
"I offer everything I have:
my heart and my hands."
"Go to your room, sweetie."
"Yes, mother.
You bastard!”
"I know you don't know
politeness."
"It's the only excuse
for your impertinence."
"I don't know any manners, do I?"
Lincoln is assassinated!
Please contact immediately
the mail boat!
New York Reuters Agency!
The boat leaves from New York
tomorrow morning.
The Times of London!
The Anglo-Irish!
United States Embassy!
Reuters Agency in London!
Sit down, Mr. Randolph.
A cup of tea, thank you.
What are you afraid of?
- Have you been reading newspapers?
- Yes.
The market turns against me.
I will pay dearly if I am mistaken about
the result of the American War.
Lincoln is not a monster.
It's smart.
Investing in the South is good as long as
Lincoln is president.
I expect!
However, the market is
It's on the verge of collapse.
I'm screwed, Julius,
very contrived.
You want your 5,000 pounds.
Thank you for saying this for me.
I don't have them.
You have to recover them.
In a few days.
The mail boat!
Give a signal!
Mr. OMalley?
- What's up?
- A signal.
It's Reuter's sign.
- Take the package.
- Yes sir.
Operator!
Are you ready?
The lines do not
were tested.
Use this message as a test.
I'll try.
But I don't guarantee anything.
Try it, anyway.
Mr. Reuters.
Who is it now?
- Mr. Reuters
- Yes?
- It's a message from Cork!
-Cork?
Ida, a message from Cork!
What is it?
I would like to open the line
with other news.
It's terrible!
It should spread quickly.
We still caught the opening of the Stock Exchange.
You can't wait,
until Sir Randolph sells?
No, Ida.
It will be ruined.
Have you forgotten what you did for us?!
Of course not.
This belongs to the public,
not to Sir Randolph or me.
I can't keep this
to protect a person.
Get ready everyone!
Special newsletter!
Free all lines.
All translators!
Russian, French, Italian!
Quickly!
The Morning Herald!
Lincoln is assassinated!
President Lincoln,
murdered!
Special edition!
Lincoln is assassinated!
Sell!
The American ambassador
should know that!
I can only say that this news
has not been officially confirmed.
I don't even know where it came from,
the American mail boat
It hasn't arrived yet!
According to Anglo-Irish, the
ship has not yet been sighted.
Mr. Reuter will not broadcast
deliberately false rumor!
Sirs!
Rumors!
I spoke to the ambassador
American,
and the Company
Anglo-Irish.
The mail boat
hasn't been seen yet!
Reuters invented this
to sink the market.
But why?
You're crazy,
is almost bankrupt!
Without a doubt, try
earn money
using your reputation
of reliability.
Damn you!
- Isn't Reuter your friend?
- It was!
Buy!
They raised the flag again.
They don't believe me!
Damn you!
I would be ruined
if it had sold!
Sell ​​as quickly as possible!
Please,
don't waste time.
Don't be complicit.
- It's true!
- It's impossible!
The mail ship
hasn't been seen yet!
Not in Queenstowen,
but it was already in Crookshaven.
Max took the messages and
sent them through Cork.
There is no line between
Cork and Crookshaven!
Yes there is.
Thanks for your money!
So did the Anglo-Irish win?
In 7 hours!
Why didn't you tell me?
You are a member of many
clubs.
I could let a word slip.
It was a big secret!
Go sell your shares!
Immediately!
Julius!
I don't know what to say.
Don't say anything
and sell!
Keep the secret. I want the
Anglo-Irish confirm!
Accordingly!
See you soon!
He seems restless.
I am.
Your telegram will be named
in Parliament.
- I became a national scandal?!
- Oh, Julius!
Why did it?
Reuter is always the fastest.
Have you gone crazy?
You'll soon find out!
You are Reuter's friend.
Why did he spread this rumor?
Julius Reuter never disclosed
false rumors.
How will the Times react?
- Not yet.
- What if the news is fake?
So, no one will be left
at Reuters Agency for processing.
- I'll accompany you.
- Don't worry.
Reuters!
How much did they pay you
to spread this rumor?
- What country was it?
- Millions stolen!
Reuter was reliable!
You ruined me!
Kill him!
Will the government
is willing
to sue this Rooter?
The government does not control the
country's press.
I propose a law to
control the press.
The government will oppose it.
Freedom of the press and freedom
of expression are inseparable.
And the thousands of people who
were ruined today.
Not to mention those...
that will be indirectly affected.
Don't these people have rights?
Who is responsible
of this ruin?
Julius Rooter!
A pirate!
Rooter!
Such a shameless man
who dares to sit on the press bench!
They make a serious mistake.
Mr. Reuter is your friend,
Isn't that true?
I'm proud to say it.
How much did you lose on the stock market?
Nothing, not a penny!
Are you sure the news is true?
I hope so!
Let's deliberate
this subject.
How can this man continue
machining,
protected by freedom
press?
The entire press
should not be censored
by an individual.
The press is
responsible for Rooter!
It's what makes her live!
The press must accept
the consequences!
My government
Are you willing to fight...
for freedom of the press.
But you don't have to forget
investor losses.
Gentlemen, please.
I just received a message
of the US ambassador.
Abraham Lincoln, president
in the United States,
was killed, murdered!
This tragic news
has been confirmed
for the company
Anglo-Irish.
Mr. Rooter!
Her Majesty's Government
offers his apologies,
as well as members of the
Parliament.
For your skill
and its veracity,
saved the press
of yet another attack...
against his freedom.
Thanks.
Gentlemen, may I speak?
A censored press
It is an instrument of corruption.
A free press symbolizes
a free people.
Since truth is freedom,
and without truth,
There can be no more than slavery
and degradation.
And gentlemen, please,
my name is Reuter!