Thirty thousand.
From the Russians ?
No, from the French.
From the Russians, we capture more than that every day.
Mr. Postman.
War is war and schnapps is
schnapps, but business must go on.
You didn't leave the mail yet this morning.
Ah, I'm sorry, Mr. Meyer.
Hello, Himmelstoss. Anything for us today ?
No, no, Master Peter.
C'mon, there must be something.
Here, here you go, young rascal.
There. This is the last mail I deliver, anyhow.
What ?
Tomorrow I change uniform.
You're going in the army ?
Yes, I was called.
I'm a Sergeant in the reserves, you know.
I'll be called myself, if it doesn't end in a few months.
It will, though.
I'm sure you're right, Mr. Meyer.
...and join the mighty army
that is defending our country, our fatherland.
Now, my beloved class, this is what we must do.
Strike with all our power.
Give every ounce of strength
to win victory before the end of the year.
It is with reluctance that I bring this subject up again.
You are the life of the fatherland, you boys.
You are the iron men of Germany.
You are the gay heroes who will repulse the enemy
when you are called upon to do so.
It is not for me to suggest that any of you
should stand up and offer to defend his country.
But I wonder if such a thing is going through your heads.
I know that in one of the schools
the boys have risen up in the classroom
and enlisted in a mass.
But, of course, if such a thing should happen here
you would not blame me for a feeling of pride.
Perhaps some will say
that you should not be allowed to go yet,
that you are too young, that
you have homes, mothers, fathers,
that you should not be torn away.
Are your fathers so forgetful of their fatherland
that they would let it perish rather than you ?
Are your mothers so weak that they cannot send a son
to defend the land which gave them birth ?
And after all, is a little experience
such a bad thing for a boy ?
Is the honor of wearing a uniform
something from which we should run ?
And if our young ladies glory in those who wear it,
is that anything to be ashamed of ?
I know you have never desired the adulation of heroes.
That has not been part of my teaching.
We have sought to make ourselves worthy
and let acclaim come when it would.
But to be foremost in battle
is a virtue not to be despised.
I believe it will be a quick war,
that there will be few losses.
But if losses there must be,
then let us remember the Latin phrase
which must have come to the lips of many a Roman
when he stood embattled in a foreign land,
"Dulce et decorum est pro patria mori."
"Sweet and fitting it is to die for the fatherland."
Some of you may have ambitions.
I know of one young man who has great promise as a writer
and he has written the first act of a tragedy
which would be a credit to one of the masters.
And he is dreaming, I suppose,
of following in the footsteps of Goethe and Schiller,
and I hope he will.
But now our country calls.
The fatherland needs leaders.
Personal ambition must be thrown aside
in the one great sacrifice for our country.
Here is a glorious beginning for your lives.
The field of honor calls you.
Why are we here ?
You, Kropp, what has kept you back ?
You, Mueller, you know how much you are needed ?
Ah, I see you look at your leader.
And I, too, look to you, Paul Bäumer,
and I wonder what you are going to do.
I'll go. I want to go.
Count on me.
Me, too.
I'm ready.
I'm not gonna stay home.
Follow me ! Enlist now !
No more classes !
Don't be a quitter. Come on, Behn !
Stick together. That's what we've got to do.
Let's all stick together.
Come on, Behn.
All right. All right.
I'll go.
That's the way !
Let's go !
Sing ! Let's sing ! Come on !
Keep in line, there, soldiers.
Anything you say, General.
Detail, halt !
Left face !
Get into uniform, ready to report. Fall out.
I bet you a place like this gets you in good condition.
You have to be for the long marches.
I'm gonna get in the cavalry and ride.
No cavalry for me.
Infantry's where you see the fighting.
Where are all the guns ? That's what I want to know.
Oh, you don't get a gun for a long while yet.
Well, if I'm gonna bump off the
enemy, I gotta have some practice.
Ow !
Bayonet drill. That's what I want.
You won a medal that time, Mueller.
You wait. In about a month, I'll be covered with them.
Say, keep your boots out of my face.
Why, it's an honor to have those boots in your face.
They're the best pair in the army. My uncle gave them to me.
Just look at that special imported leather.
Put them anyplace you like, except in my face.
Not even a kitchen maid'll look at me in this.
Attention !
Well, for the love of... It's Himmelstoss !
So it is.
And all dressed up.
Hello, Himmie.
You didn't think you'd see me again so soon, did you ?
You see my rank ?
Sure.
Fall back, then !
Himmelstoss, we certainly are glad to see you.
What did you say ?
I was going to say... Never mind !
What's the matter with you, Himmelstoss ?
When you address your superior officer, say "Sir."
Where'd he get such a nice uniform ?
Will there be any mail for us, Himmie ?
Quiet !
My dear fellow, you're shouting.
Come on, Himmelstoss. We know you.
Take off the false whiskers.
I believe you mean it.
You'll find out that I mean it.
But only three days ago you were our postman.
Silence !
Come back here !
Line up !
Line up ! Get in some kind of a
line ! Don't even think about it.
All of you ! Line up, I say !
Hmm.
What a pretty sight that is.
Have you never heard of standing in line ?
You make a fine mess of it.
Well, I'll have to teach you.
We'll spend the whole day on it, huh ?
You may be stupid, but I'm used to that.
And then there'll be plenty of other things, too.
Oh, I'll not neglect you.
Hmm.
You're not much to begin with, but I'll do my best.
I see that we have come here with a slight misunderstanding,
and we'll correct that, too, won't we, huh ?
And the first thing to do is to
forget everything you ever knew.
Everything you ever learned, forget ! See ?
Forget what you've been and
what you think you're going to be.
You're going to be soldiers, and that's all !
I'll take the mother's milk out
of you. I'll make you hard-boiled.
I'll make soldiers out of you or kill you !
Now, salute !
Attention !
Detachment, lie down !
Down !
Head down !
Keep your head down, Bäumer !
Detachment, get up !
Advance !
Now, sing !
Do you call that singing ?
Detachment, halt !
So, we have no spirit, huh ?
We are in no mood for recreation.
Work is what we want. Good !
Then we'll go back to work.
Detachment, lie down !
Keep your head down.
Now, sing !
Men, halt !
Order, arms !
Inspection at 3:00. Dismissed !
Oh, that swine ! That means we get no time off.
It will take four hours to get ready for inspection.
I'd like to know what's in his mind.
He hasn't got any !
I'm gonna cut him open sometime and find out.
He's too thick-skinned. He won't cut.
This is the fourth time he's
made me disappoint that poor girl.
Arms !
Order, arms !
Left shoulder, arms !
Squad, right. To the right, march !
Left, left, left, left.
Column, left, march !
Left, hut...
Squad, left march !
Forward, march ! Left.
Detachment, halt !
Present arms !
Himmelstoss.
Excellent work. They're going up front tomorrow.
I recommend leave till midnight.
Very good, Sir.
Left shoulders, arms !
Forward march. Left, left, straight ahead !
Now, left.
We're clear.
Left, left, left.
Detachment, lie down !
Crawl forward !
He spoiled our leave. I'll never forgive him for that.
The rat !
Leave till midnight.
It'll take till midnight to dry our clothes.
There goes the filthy ape now.
While we slave over this mud,
he goes off to have a few drinks.
Someday I'm going to take one smack at him, just one.
Me, too. That's gonna be my life's work from now on.
Why only one ? I'm gonna take several.
I might even kick him when he's down. I feel mean.
What are you doing ?
You're not going to desert, are you ?
What ?
Listen. I've got an idea.
Crawl forward. Lie down.
Lie down. Crawl forward.
What ?
Here comes an officer.
Get him out of here.
Cover !
Paul, are you all right ?
You all right ?
Behn ! Behn !
Behn ! Come on !
Behn, come on. You fool, Behn.
Get up ! Come on.
Sounds like more replacements coming in.
Yeah. Tjaden must have gone home for that wood.
Here's some more, fresh from the turnip patch.
I suppose this is where we bunk.
That's me, "I. Westhus,"
and this is where he lives.
I didn't know.
Well, you know now.
Yes. Yes, of course.
It's all right.
Here's a bunk, Paul.
When did we eat last ?
Don't remind me.
I was fine until you spoke.
Where are we, anyway ?
I don't know. The name on the
railroad station's been shot off.
Well, there must be something to eat somewhere.
I'll tell you what I'll do.
I'll ask those fellows.
Sorry to disturb you, Mr. Westhus.
Oh, meet Detering. A better farmer never lived.
And Mr. Tjaden.
Sit down.
You see, we haven't eaten since breakfast.
We thought maybe you could
tell us what we ought to do about it.
Eat without further delay.
Well, what's funny about that ?
This is a bad town to bring an appetite to, soldier.
We've been here since yesterday morning
and we've been living on baled hay and razor blades.
We're willing to buy our food. Where's the canteen ?
The only canteen in these regions
is out looking for supplies.
Ever hear of Katczinsky ?
Who ?
Katczinsky. He's uncanny.
If there's any food within 25
miles, he'll be the one to get it.
Hey !
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Attention !
What is this ?
Volunteers for the future general staff.
Sometime I'm gonna take one of you volunteers apart
and find out what makes you leave school and join the Army.
At ease. This is no parade ground.
- Hungry ?
- Yes.
Wait ! Wait a minute. Wait a minute. That's no invitation.
Can you pay ?
Yeah, sure. I have some money.
No, not money. That's just pieces of paper.
Have you got any cigarettes, cigars,
or soap, cognac...
Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
Chewing tobacco ? Yeah, yeah.
Hey, Kat ! Yeah ?
Are you crazy ? There ain't enough here for us.
I wish you three would get bumped off.
I'm tired of feeding you for nothing.
Bring everything you've got.
I'm so hungry...
I'd be glad to give you...
Come on !
Is this enough, Sir ?
Kat ! Hmm ?
You've got the wiring detail tonight.
Where ?
Past the graveyard.
With this bunch ?
It's quiet tonight. You can teach them a couple of things.
Thanks. I'd rather do it alone.
These babes get killed off too fast.
Well, the lorry's waiting.
Last night I was too hungry to sleep
and tonight, when I get the wrinkles out of my gut,
they think up wiring duty.
Well, here's your chance, heroes.
For the fatherland !
Come on, get your stuff and let's get out of here.
Is that any way to drive ?
Let him drive any way he wants.
Suppose he breaks your arm. You get sent home, don't you ?
A lot better than having a hole in your guts.
If there's any of you left, I'll pick you up in the morning.
Well, if that ride you gave us didn't kill us, nothing will.
And be on time. I don't want to miss my breakfast.
Yeah ?
You better wait for your army, Papa.
Here, here. Don't be so backward.
Listen, children. All we got
to do is to string a little wire.
We pick it up at the dump and carry it to where we need it.
Now, you're gonna see some shellfire,
and you're gonna be scared, see ?
It's all right, boy. Get up.
Here. Never mind.
It's happened to better men
than you, and it's happened to me.
When we come back, I'll get
you all some nice clean underwear.
That kind of shell you don't have to pay much attention to.
Those big fellows just make a lot of noise
and land about five miles behind the line.
The things we've got to watch out for are the light ones.
They don't give you much warning.
They go "waah zing."
And when you hear that, down !
Mother Earth.
Press yourselves down upon her.
Bury yourselves deep into her.
Just keep your eyes on me.
When you see me flop, you flop.
Only, try to beat me to it.
Now, listen.
I'll show you how it's done.
Give me a couple of those. That's to kill the noise.
Tjaden.
See that ?
What's that mean ?
Bombardment.
My eyes !
I'm blind !
I can't see ! God !
My eyes ! I can't see !
Oh, God !
- It's Behn ! It's Behn !
- I can't see !
I'll go get him... You'll get killed !
Leave him. What ?
Let me... Lay down and stay there !
You'll get your head shot off.
He's dead.
Why did you risk your life bringing him in ?
But it's Behn.
My friend.
It's a corpse, no matter who it is.
Now, don't any of you ever do that again.
Put him over there.
Mind the wire.
All right, come on.
All right, come on. Get your packs and fall in. Hurry up.
Come on. Hurry up. Come on. Make it snappy.
Get your packs and fall in.
Kat, what are we doing ? What's happening ?
You heard him. Orders to march.
But where to, for the love of...
Another party.
And this one is gonna last a long time.
Come on.
Here we go.
Company, attention !
Shoulder, arms !
March right, march !
Take your hands off that !
Queen takes it !
Well, if you think that's a queen, look again.
It's a Jack.
Yeah.
Honest, these cards all look alike.
It's too noisy ! I can't play.
I suppose your delicate nerves... Get up.
...can't stand it.
That's Oscar. The son of a...
Look at that !
Don't be so snooty. You may wish you had this back.
About two more days of this
and this rat-bitten end of a piece of bread's
gonna taste just like a hunk of fruitcake.
It wouldn't... It wouldn't last two more days, would it ?
Didn't I tell you this was gonna be a bad one ?
I don't mind the days so much.
It's keeping up all night that's...
Two more days makes a week, kid.
Then you can say you've been under fire.
You're not scared, are you ?
No. I was just asking, that's all.
Want to play some more ?
Do you ?
Sure.
All right. My deal.
You better get your boot back before Oscar eats that.
The kid's all right.
Behn.
Yeah, yeah. Let him sleep. He's dreaming. Behn.
Oh, God. Can't you see it's Behn ?
He didn't want to come to war.
No, no.
It isn't Behn.
It isn't Behn !
It's Kemmerick ! It's me !
Shut up, will you ? It's bad enough in here as it is.
Every...
Everything's all right, Franz.
You're dreaming.
I see something.
You're just dreaming, I guess.
Attention ! At ease.
The barrage is getting worse.
Men in two more dugouts, gone.
However, we'll do our best to
get some food up here by evening.
Stop !
Let me out.
What did you do that for ?
Shut up ! Grab him.
No. Now hold him.
You all right now ?
I think so.
I couldn't hold out much longer.
Let me out !
It's going to kill me !
Very good.
Oh, my God, it's Franz ! This is terrible !
No, don't. He's been hit in the stomach.
He can't have anything to drink.
Get a stretcher.
Where'd they get you, Kemmerick ?
Here it is, Sir.
Take his head.
All right. Take him out.
Is it serious, Sir ?
I'm not sure.
Tell the others he's all right.
Yes, Sir.
If we're going to fight, why don't we fight ?
Why don't we go over ?
You could go crazy staying here.
Let's do something !
Let's go after them !
Sit down !
If that cook of ours had any guts,
he'd try to bring something through.
He's so far behind the lines he can't hear the shooting !
Here's Kat. Get anything ?
Any luck ?
We'll have to split this up among us.
Something to eat !
We need butter, too.
Yes. And dessert. And a feather bed to sleep on.
- Rats !
Rats. Rats.
Get out of the way !
That's enough.
That's enough, boys.
What's that ?
Come on !
Come on ! Grab your rifles !
Come along.
Come on, everybody.
Here they come.
Get your grenades here.
In this space.
Hurry up. This is an attack. Come on, hurry up.
Come on !
Aim. Fire.
Here you go, troops.
Let's go ! Let's go ! Let's move !
We can't hold this position, men. Back to your own lines !
We've got a lift from cavalry.
Now, then.
Fill it up. And hurry up.
I've got other things to do.
I've been waiting for this for three weeks.
When they all get here.
What do you want ?
Beans, you homely-looking son of a frog's leg.
What do you think I want ?
We're hungry.
Shut up ! I'll feed you when you're all here.
We're all here now.
Only half the company's here. Get the rest.
Wake 'em up.
Yeah.
I wish I could wake 'em up. There's 80 of us left.
The rest is in dressing stations or pushing up daisies.
Eighty ? And I cooked for 150 !
All right. We'll have enough for once. Come on, dish out !
You mean, you've cooked beans
for 150, and you've got bread for 150,
and sausage for 150, and tobacco for 150 ?
Everything ! It's all wrong. I should have been notified.
What a feast ! Everyone gets two issues.
Hey, get back in line ! Get back in line !
Oh, no ! That won't do.
I can't give 80 men what's meant for 150.
Listen.
You drew rations for the 2nd Company, didn't you ?
Yeah.
All right. We're the 2nd Company.
I've got my orders.
Kat's right.
We're the 2nd Company.
And if only half of us get back, that's our good luck.
Come on. Dish it out.
Come on !
No !
Hey !
You're the yellowest baboon that ever drew a cook wagon
and you're scared it shows.
All we want to hear out of you is one more little yip
and we'll cut you up and eat you raw.
Why, you keep your kitchen so far back of the lines
we never get anything to eat
until it's cold and we're asleep !
Now, you low-down rat, get out
or we wreck the joint, so help us.
Come on ! Give us our food.
Attention !
At ease.
What's going on here ?
He's cooked for 150, Sir, and he only wants to give us half.
Looks pretty good.
Yes, Sir.
Serve the whole issue ! The men can use it.
And bring me a plate, too.
Yes, Sir.
All right. Take it all. Take everything.
Give 'em honey. Give 'em what they want.
Fill it up ! Fill it up ! Fill it up !
Anybody else ?
All I want is to get going.
Don't mind me.
Oh, that's all right. Don't mention it.
You know,
I could do with some more beans.
Go help yourself. There's more over there.
It's too far.
I wonder, when are we going back to the front ?
Tomorrow.
It's enough to take away a man's appetite.
You know, if they're gonna march us in again tomorrow,
we ought to go see how Kemmerick is.
That's a good idea. Let's do that.
How far is the dressing station ?
About two miles.
We could take his things to him.
Good.
It seemed rotten to think of a
thing like that happening to him,
a nice fellow like Kemmerick.
The French certainly deserve to
be punished for starting this war.
Everybody says it's somebody else.
Well, how do they start a war ?
Well, one country offends another.
How could one country offend another ?
You mean, there's a mountain over in Germany
gets mad at a field over in France ?
Well, stupid, one people offends another.
Oh, if that's it, I shouldn't be here at all.
I don't feel offended.
It don't apply to tramps like you.
Good. Then I can be going home right away.
You just try it.
Yeah. You want to get shot ?
The Kaiser and me...
Me and the Kaiser felt just alike about this war.
We didn't either of us want any war, so I'm going home.
He's there already.
Somebody must have wanted it. Maybe it was the English.
No, I don't want to shoot any Englishmen.
I never saw one till I came up here.
And I suppose most of them never saw a German
till they came up here.
No, I'm sure they weren't asked about it.
No.
Well, it must be doing somebody some good.
Not me and the Kaiser.
I think maybe the Kaiser wanted a war.
You leave us out of this.
I don't see that. The Kaiser's got everything he needs.
Well, he never had a war before.
Every full-grown emperor needs one war to make him famous.
Why, that's history.
Yeah, Generals, too. They need war.
And manufacturers. They get rich. Hmm.
I think it's more a kind of fever.
Nobody wants it in particular
and then, all at once, here it is.
We didn't want it. The English
didn't want it. And here we are fighting.
I'll tell you how it should all be done.
Whenever there's a big war coming on,
you should rope off a big field...
And sell tickets.
Yeah. And...
And on the big day
you should take all the kings
and their cabinets and their Generals,
put them in the center dressed in their underpants
and let them fight it out with clubs.
The best country wins.
Well, now that Kat's settled
everything, let's go see Kemmerick.
Might cheer him up.
Something interesting might happen on the way.
Boys, me and the Kaiser want
you back in time to march tomorrow.
Don't forget.
We'll be back.
Give the boy my regards.
Whoa.
Oh, there he is.
Hello, Kemmerick. How are you ?
How's it going ?
How are things going ?
Are they looking after you all right ?
How are they treating you ? Franz ?
I'm all right.
They're robbers here.
Robbers.
They stole my watch.
I always told you nobody should
carry as good a watch as that.
And they took it while I was under ether.
Franz. Franz. You'll get it back.
Do you feel all right ?
Just look at my hand, though.
That's because you lost so much blood.
Just eat decently and you'll get well again.
Oh, no.
Franz, you must eat. That's
the main thing. It looks good, too.
I have such a terrible pain in my foot.
Every toe on my right foot hurts.
Well, how can your foot hurt when your leg's been...
Oh, I know what you mean !
I know ! I know now !
They've cut my leg off.
Why didn't they tell me ?
Franz ! Franz ! ...they tell me.
Now I can't walk anymore !
Franz, you must be thankful
that you've come off with only that.
I wanted to be a forester once.
You can yet. They make artificial legs that are wonderful.
And you're through, too. You can go home. Think of that.
We brought your things for you. See ?
Put them under the bed.
That's a marvelous pair of boots.
Look at that leather.
What comfort.
I was just thinking.
If you're not going to be using these, Franz,
why don't you leave them with us ?
What good are they to you ? I can use 'em.
My boots give me blister after blister.
Well, we'll be going, Franz.
Oh, don't go. Stay just a little while longer.
I'll come right back.
We'll be coming soon again, Franz.
I know you'll be feeling better, Franz. Bye.
Bye.
Goodbye, Franz.
You think he'll last till after mess ?
You don't think...
Done for.
Boys, you go along. I'll see you later.
- Goodbye. All right, Paul.
- Goodbye, Paul.
I'm sorry, Paul.
I wouldn't touch a thing of his if he could use it.
I'd go barefoot over barbed
wire for him if it'd do him any good.
Only why should some orderly get those boots ?
I understand, Mueller. We're all alike out here.
And good boots are scarce.
Tell the doctor to come, please.
Doctor, the man in the next bed would like to see you, Sir.
I've done everything I can for him. There's no helping him.
Poor little fellow.
He says next time, Franz.
Do you think I'll ever get well ?
Why, of course.
Do you really think so ?
Sure, once you get over the operation.
I don't think so.
Franz. Don't talk nonsense. Why, you'll be as good as new.
They fix up worse things than that.
Perhaps you'll go to the convalescent home in Klosterberg
among the villagers.
Then you can look out of the windows, across the field
to the two trees on the horizon.
The loveliest time of the year, now, when the corn ripens.
And you can go out without asking anyone.
You can even play piano if you want to.
Oh... Oh, but, Franz, you must try to sleep now.
Oh, God,
this is Franz Kemmerick, only 19 years old.
He doesn't want to die.
Please, don't let him die.
Paul.
Paul. Yes, Franz.
Take my boots home for Mueller.
Oh, no, Franz, no.
And if...
Paul, you can find my watch,
send it home.
Franz !
Doctor. Doctor !
Doctor !
Doctor ! Where's the doctor ?
Why isn't there a doctor here ?
Doctor, come quick. Franz Kemmerick is dying !
Which one is that ? Amputated leg.
I've amputated a dozen legs today.
Bed 26, Sir.
You see to it. I'm due in the operating room.
One operation after another since 5:00 this morning.
Sixteen dead today, yours is the 17th.
There'll probably be 20 by tomorrow.
You're looking good, very good today.
What's your hurry ?
Hey ! I'll bet he stole those boots !
Why didn't you stop him ?
I got it, Kat.
Huh ?
Listen, "The sum of an arithmetic series
"is S = A + L x N over 2." Interesting, isn't it ?
What do you want to learn that stuff for ?
One day you'll stop a bullet and it'll all be wasted.
I get a lot of fun out of it.
My boots !
Mueller.
I saw him die.
I didn't know what it was like to die before.
And then... Then I came outside and it felt...
It felt so good to be alive that I started in to walk fast.
I began to think of the strangest things,
like being out in the fields. Things like that.
You know, girls.
And it felt as if there were
something electric running from the ground up through me.
And I started. And I began to run hard.
And I passed soldiers and I heard voices calling, but...
And I ran and I ran.
And I felt as if I couldn't breathe enough air into me.
And... And now I'm hungry.
I don't mind the war now.
Be a pleasure to go to the front in boots like these.
It's a good invention, just the same.
If you crack each separate louse,
think of all the energy you use up. Watch.
Burned to death.
How was patrol ? Bad ?
Must've been terrible if they
had time to gather in the harvest.
We passed a cherry tree and
when he saw it, he sort of went crazy.
I could hardly drag him away.
It was beautiful.
I have a big orchard with cherry trees at home.
And when they're in full blossom,
from the hayloft it looks like one single sheet.
So white.
Perhaps you can get leave soon.
You may even be sent back as a farmer.
A woman can't run a farm alone. That's no good, you know ?
No matter how hard she works.
Harvest coming on again.
What's the matter with him ?
Got a letter yesterday from his wife.
He wants to get back to his farm.
We'd all like to get back home, it comes to that.
I wonder what we'd do if it were suddenly peacetime again ?
Get drunk and look for women !
I'd go looking for a Cinderella
that could wear this for a garter.
And when I'd found her, nobody would see me for two weeks.
I'll go back to the peat fields
and those pleasant hours in the beer gardens.
And there's worse things than cobbling, too.
Look. My family.
I ought to give you a kick in
the backside for starting all this.
It's all right for all you to talk.
You've got something to go back to.
Wives, children, jobs...
But what about us ? What have
we got to go back to ? School ?
Why not ? You know everything already ?
A man can't take all that rubbish they teach you seriously
after three years of shells and bombs.
You can't peel that off as easily as a sock.
They never taught us anything really useful,
like how to light a cigarette in the wind,
or make a fire out of wet wood,
or bayonet a man in the belly instead
of the ribs where it gets jammed.
What can happen to us afterwards ?
I'll tell you. Take our class.
Out of 20, three are officers,
nine dead,
Mueller and three others wounded, and one in the madhouse.
We'll all be dead someday, so let's forget it.
Hurry up ! Get in there ! Hurry up !
Himmelstoss !
What's up ?
What are you, crazy ?
It's Himmelstoss !
Himmelstoss ? There is justice in the army !
Well, well. So, we are all here, huh ?
A bit longer than you, Himmie.
And since when have we become so familiar ?
Stand up there and click your heels together ! All of you !
Take a running jump at yourself !
Who's your friend ?
Would somebody get General
Ludendorff a nice, comfortable chair ?
I command you as your superior officer !
Do you want to be court-martialed for this ?
I do !
There's going to be a big attack tonight
and I'd just love to get out of it.
Will you obey my orders ?
Kiss my foot.
It isn't customary to ask for salutes here.
But I'll tell you what we'll do.
We're going to attack a town
that we tried to take once before.
Many killed and many wounded. It was great fun.
This time you're going with us.
If any of us stops a bullet, before we die,
we're going to come to you, click
our heels together and ask stiffly,
"Please, Sergeant Himmelstoss, may we go ?"
You'll... You'll pay for this, you...
Here it is.
Right on time. Better get ready, boys.
I'm wounded. I'm wounded !
It's just a scratch, you yellow
rat ! Up ! Get on with the others ! Up !
No ! No ! No !
You yellow rat !
You stinking yellow rat ! Let the others do it, eh ?
Get up ! Get up !
Forward, forward ! Get out here !
The command was forward.
Command was forward !
Forward !
Forward ! Forward !
Counterattack.
I want to help you.
Stop that ! Stop that !
I can bear the rest of it. I can't listen to that !
Why do you take so long dying ?
You're going to die anyway !
Oh, no. Oh, no. You won't die.
No, no. You won't die. They're only little wounds.
You'll get home. You'll be all right.
You'll get home long before I will.
You know I can't run away. That's why you accuse me.
I tell you, I didn't want to kill
you. I tried to keep you alive.
If you jumped in here again, I wouldn't do it.
You see when you jumped in here you were my enemy,
and I was afraid of you.
But you're just a man like me, and I killed you.
Forgive me, comrade.
Say that for me. Say you forgive me.
Oh, no. You're dead.
Only, you're better off than I am. You're through.
They can't do anymore to you now.
Oh, God, why did they do this to us ?
We only wanted to live, you and I.
Why should they send us out to fight each other ?
If we threw away these rifles and these uniforms
you could be my brother, just like Kat and Albert.
You'll have to forgive me, comrade. I'll do all I can.
I'll write to your parents. I'll write to...
I'll write to your wife. I'll write to her.
I promise she'll not want for anything.
And I'll help her and your parents, too.
Only, forgive me. Forgive me !
Forgive me. Forgive me.
Forgive me.
Terrible thing happened yesterday.
I stabbed a man. With my own hands, stabbed him.
I know how it is. Your first time.
Never mind. The stretcher-bearers will find him.
No, no. He's dead, Kat. I watched him die.
You couldn't do anything about it.
We have to kill. We can't help it.
That's what we are here for. Look there, for instance.
That got him. You should've seen how he leaped in the air.
That fellow headed the shoot
with us for today with three hits.
If he keeps it up, he'll have a decoration
for his buttonhole this evening.
Now, don't you lose anymore sleep over this business.
Maybe it was 'cause I was out there with him so long, huh ?
Sure, that's it.
After all, war is war.
March !
Forward, march !
Quickly ! Forward !
Company, halt !
Dismissed !
Noncommissioned officers, enlisted men, dismissed !
Hooray ! Come on, let's get out of here !
Give me your best sausage.
Two.
Give me a beer.
One, two, three, hoorah !
Hey, come on. A beer.
Hey, get out of here !
Come on. Give me a beer.
A beer. One...
Prosit !
Well, here's hoping we get falling-down drunk tonight.
Here's how it started.
I'd forgotten there were girls like that.
There aren't.
Just look at those thin, little shoes.
She couldn't march many miles in those.
Paul. Don't speak about marching.
You're boring the young lady.
A thousand pardons.
How old do you think she is ?
Oh, about 22.
No, you know, that'd make her older than us.
She's 17.
A girl like that. That'd be good, eh, Albert ?
We wouldn't have much of a chance with him around.
We could take a bath, wash our clothes...
All right.
I might even go so far as to get deloused.
Wait a minute ! Wait a minute !
She's a long way from here now.
Look at the date. May 1917.
Four months ago.
That's true.
Well, here's to her anyway.
Here's to 'em all, everywhere.
Albert, we might as well wash up anyway.
All right.
Personally, I like them bigger around.
This conversation was on a high moral plane up to now.
Now we do need a bath.
A bath ? For what ?
You wouldn't understand.
This water's freezing. This
romantic business has gone too far.
But think of her beautiful eyes !
Oh, and her hair.
Here we are ! We're not gonna miss a thing !
Go away !
What are you doing here ?
Bathing !
They tell me there's some people in this world
takes a bath every week !
Women !
Mademoiselle, you want to swim ?
Mademoiselle, you could be me !
Oh, baby !
Kiss me !
No, girls ! Don't go away !
Oh, mama !
Please don't go !
Don't go away !
Mademoiselle, we want you.
Food ! Food ! Whoo !
Halt !
You know you're forbidden to cross.
You fellows stay on this side or
you'll get yourselves in a lot of trouble.
What are they jabbering about ?
They want us to swing over tonight. They're expecting us.
That's fine ! We'll do it !
That blonde's crazy about me.
But there's four of us and only three of them.
I was the one that stopped 'em !
That blonde piece of work is mine.
You three fight for what's left.
Fight's the word. All's fair in love and war.
Huh ? What do you mean ? What are you gonna do ?
You'll find out.
She means the door.
Not only modest, but dashing !
A perfect fit.
It might've been made for me.
An officer's coat. We're calling, distinguished company.
Have another little drink, comrade.
Is this your birthday or mine ?
Why ?
You've been buying me drink after drink for two hours.
What I'm trying to figure out is why.
Why ? Why ?
Oh !
It's just that the boys
told me to amuse you for a little while.
Oh, nice boys.
Yeah !
Yeah, they said you'd understand.
I've been betrayed !
Yeah, you certainly have.
Take that for a minute !
I'll give you more !
It's too loud.
Darling.
What's your name ?
Name. How do you say name ?
Georgette ? Camille ?
Suzanne.
Paul.
Suzanne, I wish I could tell you something.
I wish you could understand.
Darling, I'll never see you again. I know that.
And I wouldn't even know you if I did.
And yet, I'll remember you always.
If you could only know how different this is
from the women that we soldiers meet.
No, no, no. Not the war.
You. That's what I'm talking about.
It seems as though all war, terror and grossness
had fallen away from me, like a miracle.
Like something I never believed.
Call Paul.
We're going, Paul.
Have a look. Nice, new coffins.
For us.
I must say, that's a very cheerful
preparation for this offensive.
That's very considerate of them.
But I don't see any long enough for our comrade, Tjaden.
Mind you, I'm not speaking to you, you traitors.
But no coffin's gonna get me.
I should say not, heartbreaker.
You'll be thankful if they slip a waterproof sheet
around that Aunt Sally of a carcass of yours.
My side !
My side.
Catholic hospital, Albert.
They say you always get good food and good treatment.
We're lucky.
After that rainy dressing station
and 24 hours on the train, we deserve to have some luck.
I'm Hammacher.
Yes, that's my name.
I got a crack in the head and
they gave me a certificate stating
that Joseph Hammacher is periodically
not responsible for his actions.
And ever since then, Hammacher has been having a grand time.
I hope you boys are not too badly wounded.
The others die off so quickly we
don't have time to get acquainted.
You'll get to know us very well.
Thank you. You, too.
I'm sorry, my dear. It's time to go now.
Yes, Sister.
Watch.
If they take his clothes away, you've seen the last of him.
See ? They're taking him to the dying room.
Dying room ?
When you're ready to kick the bucket,
they get you out of the way so they can use the bed.
In the corner of the building
there's a little room right next to the morgue !
It's so convenient. It saves a lot of trouble.
But suppose he gets well ?
I've seen a lot of them go in that dying room,
but nobody ever comes back.
Sister. Sister. Sister.
Sister.
Is that you ringing, Paul ?
Yes.
Is something wrong ?
I think I have a hemorrhage.
The bandage is all wet. I've been
ringing forever and nobody comes.
I think I'm bleeding.
Sister, get me a sterile dressing and an ice pack.
Why didn't someone call me ?
He's been ringing.
Nobody can walk, Sister.
Sister, is it bad ?
No. No, we'll be all right.
We've got it in time.
What's the matter ? What are you doing ?
We must rearrange your bandages.
Where are you taking me ?
To the bandaging ward.
No, no ! I'm not going ! I'm staying here !
Paul ! Paul !
Now, now !
I'm not going to the dying room !
But we're going to the bandaging ward.
Then why are you taking my clothes ?
You're lying to me ! But I'll come back ! I won't die !
I'll come back ! I won't die !
I'm not going to die ! I'll come back !
Sister Libertine, how is he ?
Poor boy. They had to amputate his leg.
Paul.
Paul. Paul.
Oh, he is gone.
Gone.
Hello. Welcome home, Albert !
How do you feel, kid ?
All right.
But I've got such an awful pain.
My foot...
Hammacher. Did they cut my leg off ?
Of course not ! How many did you have ? Two ?
You still got 'em ! One, two !
Don't play the fool, Hammacher. Tell me truthfully.
Of course not. And you look fine.
Look. See ?
I won't be a cripple. Now, now.
I won't live like that ! Be calm.
I'll kill myself the first chance I get !
Albert !
I won't live ! I won't live ! Yes, you will.
Albert ! Albert !
Albert, I've come back !
I told you I'd come back. Look, everybody ! I've come back !
Paul ! Paul !
That's not where I'm going. I live over there.
Paul, I'm so happy.
Hammacher, I've come back from the dead !
It's most irregular. Never happened before.
Albert, we must get well quickly so we can go home soon.
Albert, everything will be all right now.
Yes, Paul. Everything will be all right now.
Paul ! Paul ! Paul !
Paul.
What's the matter, Paul ?
Nothing. Nothing.
Paul.
Give me your handkerchief.
Mother ?
Here I am, Paul. Here I am.
Mother's ill.
Are you wounded ?
No, Mother. I got leave.
Here I lie and cry instead of being glad.
Anna, get down the jar of blackberries.
You still like them, don't you ?
Yes, Mother. I haven't had any for a long time.
We might almost have known you were coming.
I'm making potato cakes.
Don't let them burn.
Paul, sit down beside me.
My Paul.
My baby.
I almost forgot, Mother. I've
got some little presents for you.
Look, Mother. Bread, sausage and rice.
Paul, you've been starving yourself.
Hadn't I better go and tell Father Paul's home ?
Paul could watch the things on the stove.
No, no, child, I'm getting up.
Oh, Paul, you're a soldier now, aren't you ?
But somehow, I don't seem to know you.
I'll take these off, Mother.
I'll get your suit, Paul. It's in the
wardrobe, just where you left it.
Are you really here, Paul ?
You won't...
You won't disappear, will you ?
No. I'm here.
Your things are ready for you, Paul.
I remember when you caught that one.
Yes. And you took it away from me, didn't you ?
Yes, I did.
We're behind the lines,
but we know how to honor the soldier
who goes on in spite of blood and death.
Gentlemen, my son.
Prosit. Prosit.
I'm glad to know you, young man, I am glad to know you.
And how are things out there ? Terrible, eh ? Terrible.
But we must carry on.
After all, you do at least get decent food out there.
Naturally, it's worse here. Naturally.
But the best for our soldiers
all the time. That's our motto.
The best for our soldiers.
But you must give the Frenchies a good licking !
And if you boys want to come home,
let me show you what you must do before you can come home.
Give us a hand there, men.
Now, then, there's the line.
Runs so, in a "V."
Here is St. Quentin. You can see for yourself.
You're almost through now. All right ?
Shove ahead out there and don't
stick to that everlasting trench warfare.
Smash through the Johnnies ! And then you will have peace.
When you get in it, the war
isn't the way it looks back here.
You don't know anything about it.
Of course, you know about the
details, but this relates to the whole.
You can't judge that.
Of course, you do your duty and you risk your life.
But for that, you receive the highest honor.
I said that every man in the
war ought to have the Iron Cross.
First, the enemy lines must be broken through in Flanders.
On to Paris !
Push on to Paris ! Right.
No, not in Flanders. Now I'll tell you
just where the break should come.
Here.
The enemy has too many reserves there.
I insist upon Flanders !
I know, but, my dear man, why should they do that
when they're halfway through St. Quentin already ?
Why go the other way ?
Because Flanders is a flat country.
There are no mountains, no obstructions.
But there's many rivers there.
From the farms they have gone,
from the schools, from the factories.
They have gone bravely, nobly, ever forward,
realizing that there is no other
duty now but to save the fatherland.
Paul ! How are you, Paul ?
Glad to see you, Professor.
You've come at the right moment,
Bäumer. Just at the right moment.
And as if to prove all I have said,
here is one of the first to go.
A lad who sat before me on these very benches,
who gave up all to serve in the first year of the war.
One of the iron youth who have
made Germany invincible in the field.
Look at him, sturdy and bronze and clear-eyed.
The kind of soldier every one of you should envy.
Paul, lad, you must speak to them.
You must tell them what it means to serve your fatherland.
No, no, I can't tell them anything.
You must, Paul. Just a word.
Just tell them how much they're needed out there.
Tell them why you went and what it meant to you.
I can't say anything.
Can't you remember some deed
of heroism, some touch of nobility ?
Tell about it.
I can't tell you anything you don't know.
We live in the trenches out there. We fight.
We try not to be killed, sometimes we are.
That's all.
No. No, Paul.
I've been there ! I know what it's like.
That's not what one dwells on, Paul.
I've heard you in here reciting that same old stuff,
making more iron men, more young heroes.
You still think it's beautiful and sweet
to die for your country, don't you ?
We used to think you knew.
The first bombardment taught us better.
It's dirty and painful to die for your country.
When it comes to dying for your country,
it's better not to die at all !
There are millions out there dying for their countries,
and what good is it ?
Paul.
You asked me to tell them how much they're needed out there.
He tells you, "Go out and die."
Oh, but if you'll pardon me,
it's easier to say, "Go out and die" than it is to do it.
Coward !
And it's easier to say it than to watch it happen.
Coward ! Get out !
No ! Boys, boys !
I'm sorry, Bäumer, but I must say...
It's no use talking like this.
You won't know what I mean.
Only, it's been a long while since
we enlisted out of this classroom.
So long I thought maybe the
whole world had learned by this time.
Only now they're sending babies, and they won't last a week.
I shouldn't have come on leave.
Up at the front you're alive or you're dead,
and that's all.
You can't fool anybody about that very long.
And up there we know we're lost and done for,
whether we're dead or alive.
Three years we've had of it... Four years.
And every day a year, and every night a century.
And our bodies are earth, and our thoughts are clay,
and we sleep and eat with death.
We're done for because you can't live that way
and keep anything inside you !
I shouldn't have come on leave. I'll go back tomorrow.
I've got four days more, but I can't stand it here.
I'll go back tomorrow !
I'm sorry.
Mother, you'll catch cold here. You must go to sleep.
There'll be plenty of time to sleep when you're gone.
Must you go tomorrow, Paul ? Must you ?
Yes, Mother. Orders were changed.
Are you very much afraid, Paul ?
No, Mother.
There's something I want to say to you, Paul. It's...
Just be on your guard against the women out there.
They're no good.
Where we are there aren't any women, Mother.
Be very careful at the front, Paul.
Yes, Mother, I will.
I'll pray for you every day.
And if you could get a job that's not quite so dangerous...
Yes, Mother. I'll try and get in the cookhouse.
That can easily be done.
You do it then, and if the others say anything...
That won't worry me, Mother.
Now you must go to bed
and you must get well quickly before I come back.
I put two sets of underwear, new ones, in your pack.
They'll keep you nice and warm. They're all wool.
That's sweet of you.
Good night, my son.
Good night, Mother.
Oh, Mother, Mother. You still think I'm a child.
Why can't I put my head in your lap and cry ?
Is this the 2nd Company ?
Yes, Sir.
Is this all of it ?
We had 150 men, but this is all that came back yesterday.
But now they're going to give us enough to make 150 again.
How old are you ?
Sixteen.
No use. I couldn't find anything.
We'll have to eat the sawdust.
Not me ! I'll go hungry first. This makes me sick.
Now it's gonna be a real war again.
Paul ! How's old Paul ?
Here I am.
You know, the 2nd Company's getting hard to find.
Nobody seemed to know where you were.
I'm glad you found it.
I guess I don't get much of this.
There used to be some food in
the sawdust. Now it's all sawdust.
No joke, either. Eats you up inside.
This doesn't look much like the old 2nd Company.
The replacements are all like that.
Not even old enough to carry a pack.
All they know how to do is die.
I guess some of the old-timers are here yet.
Paul, they're trying to invent
something to kill me right now.
Where's Westhus ?
Messenger dog was wounded. He went out to get it.
Is it true about the armistice, Paul ?
Doesn't look that way back there.
You mean they want us to go on fighting ?
That's what they say.
They're crazy !
Germany'll be empty pretty soon.
Where's Detering ?
He got homesick. You remember about the cherry blossoms ?
I guess he never got over that.
He started out one night to go home
and help his wife with the farm.
They got him behind the lines,
and we never heard of him since.
He was just homesick, but
probably they couldn't see it that way.
Where's Kat ? Is he...
Not Kat !
If he were out, the war would be over.
You remember what he always says,
they're saving him for the last.
Where is he ?
He's out looking for food,
trying to collect something to make soup with.
Which way ?
Down the road about two miles that way.
I'll see you later.
Kat !
Paul !
Hello, Paul.
How's the side ?
Oh, it's all right now. It's fine.
Have any luck ?
No, the General's staff's been
over this country with a rake.
Let's sit down a minute.
Tell me, Paul, how was it at home ?
Have a good leave ?
In spots.
What's the matter ?
Oh, I'm no good for back there anymore, Kat.
None of us are. We've been in this too long.
The young men thought I was a
coward because I told them that
we learn that death is stronger than duty to one's country.
The old men said, "Go on. Push on to Paris."
My father even wanted me to wear my uniform around.
It's not home back there anymore.
All I could think of was, "I'd like
to get back and see Kat again."
You're all I've got left, Kat.
I'm not much to have left.
I missed you, Paul.
At least we know what it's all about out here.
There're no lies here.
Push on to Paris ?
You ought to see what they've got on the other side.
They eat white bread over there.
They've got dozens of airplanes to our one
and tanks that'll go over anything.
What've we got left ?
Guns so worn they drop shells on our own men.
No food, no ammunition, no officers.
Push on to Paris !
So that's the way they talk back there.
I guess we'd better be going.
How I lied to my poor mother.
I told her it wasn't so bad out here because
there was always a lot of us together.
Now that I'm with you,
I'm beginning to believe that I told her the truth.
Down !
That's another one that missed us. Come on. Let's go.
Wait a minute.
Looks like the old bread wagon's broke down.
I guess I don't walk the rest of the way.
Did that get you, Kat ?
I think it broke my shin.
That's not so bad. Hold it together.
Just my luck, huh ?
Good luck. That means the war is over.
Oh, no, Sir.
This war don't end till they really get me.
Now this one.
Easy, now.
Hey !
Easy !
Come on. I'll take you in. Give me your hand.
Easy.
All right.
Well, kid, now we're gonna be separated.
Maybe we can do something
together later on when the war is over.
Yes, kid.
You give me your address and I'll give you mine.
You can't get both of us in one day !
We'll surely see each other again, Kat.
Remember that day when you
brought the whole pig into the factory ?
And that day in the woods when
you taught us how to dodge shells ?
And my first bombardment. How I cried.
I was a young recruit then.
Here we are. Here we are.
All right now, Kat.
You could've spared yourself the trouble. He's dead.
Oh, no. He's just fainted. He was hit in the shin.
He's dead.
Would you like to take his paybook ?
You're not related, are you ?
No, we're not related.
Your deal. Did you get his name and number ?
Yeah, Corporal Stanislas Katczinsky, 306.
I don't get it.