[instrumental music]
Some months ago,
various persons appeared
in the federal courts
of New York City
and the Panama Canal zone
charged with
the crime of espionage
against the armed forces
of the United States.
Called to the witness stand
they swore to tell
the truth
the whole truth,
and nothing but the truth
so help me, God.
The story brought out
at those trials
is stranger than fiction
revealing the existence
of a vast spy ring
operating against
the naval, military
and air forces
of the United States.
We don't know all the facts
and we probably never will
but we do know that so far
as this country is concerned
the story began in a small
Scottish town early in 1937.
There, in a quiet
residential district..
[man whistling]
Good morning,
Mrs. Macpherson.
Thank you and
good morning to you.
Good morning, postie.
Good morning,
Harry, my laddie.
How are you?
Good morning Mr. McGregor.
Good morning, Arnold.
[doorbell rings]
[whistling]
It's a fine morning,
Mrs. McLaughlin.
- Yes, isn't it?
- Mrs. McLaughlin,
about the mail you getting
there's so much of it
every day
and it seems to come
from all over the world.
I've many friends
who still remember me.
- Ah, here, Mrs. McLaughlin?
- Yes?
If it's not
too much trouble
would you mind saving
some of the stamps
off your letters
for my wee son Willie?
He's fond of collecting 'em.
I collect them, too.
Very sorry.
Good day, Mr. McGregor.
That's too bad,
Mrs. McLaughlin.
[dramatic music]
German-American patriots
since my arrival
from Germany ten years ago
I have learned to love
the United States.
Yes, I love America
and I love it all the more
because I realize
that its deepest roots
are essentially German.
In all its ways we can see
flowing the German spirit
the German sense
of duty and endurance.
[applause]
Many people
in this country say
that we of German birth
or extraction
are only eight million
in the United States.
But they
deliberately falsify.
We actually constitute
a total of 30 million here.
Yes, America is founded
on German blood and culture.
[cheering]
And as a citizen
as a reserve officer
in the United States Navy
I say that we must unite
all those of German blood
who believe in
the German destiny of America...
[applause]
...and to bring this destiny
to a swift reality
by fighting relentlessly
the sinister influences
that would destroy us
and the new Germany.
[applause]
We are proud
of our new Germany.
Proud of its Great Fuhrer
proud of our glorious
blood and soil.
I tell you,
Germans must seize the power
that's rightfully theirs.
We Germans
in the United States
will soon demand
adequate representation
in city, county, state,
and federal government.
And those who fight us
must perish socially
as well as economically
because of our determination
to destroy our enemies
completely and without
any consideration whatever.
[applause]
Germans must save America
from the chaos
that breeds in democracy
and racial equality.
We Germans must make
the United States
and their America
our America.
(all)
Sieg Heil!
[band music]
[indistinct yelling]
[doorbell rings]
Special delivery,
Dr. Kassell.
I'll sign for it.
Okay.
Thank you.
[telephone rings]
Dr. Kassell's office.
Oh, yes, doctor.
Oh, Mrs. Kassell's
right here now.
Just a minute, please.
A special delivery letter
just came in.
Thank you.
Yes, Karl?
I'm so happy
the meeting went so well.
Where are you now?
I'll be right over.
No, I'm sorry.
I have some work to do.
No, not professional call,
it's party business.
But why can't
I be with you, Karl?
I have a right to share
all this with you.
Or maybe
it's something else
something you just
call party business.
Oh, Lisa, it's no use
getting into all this again.
Now stop worrying
and please go to bed.
Yes.
Yes, I will.
Yeah.
[whispering]
Wait for me outside.
Yes.
Huh?
What's that?
There's a special delivery
letter for you.
It's from Scotland.
It just came.
I'll get it later,
but don't leave it around.
Put it in the top
drawer of my desk.
Yes, goodnight.
No, don't wait up.
[instrumental music]
Wonderful speech,
Herr Doctor.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Simply marvelous. Congratulations.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you.
Bravo, doctor. Bravo.
Wonderful speech.
Will you join us?
No, thank you.
I have a call to make.
- Hello, Greutzwald.
- Hello.
Didn't you care
for my speech?
Mm, yes and no.
I'd like to talk to you
about it sometime.
Oh, by all means.
Sometime.
Goodnight, gentlemen.
Goodnight.
There's a man
who is somebody.
Why does he say Germans
must have power here?
Aren't we all supposed to be
Americans in America?
If you'd read and listen
you'd know Adolf Hitler
said the fatherland
is where the German feet
touch the ground.
German cooking,
the best in the world.
Eating, that's all you've
got on your mind.
Why not?
There are more
important things
to think about
these days.
Ideas like
you heard tonight.
How to serve
the fatherland.
Yeah, but we're in
America now.
Yes, and that's
our opportunity
which you shouldn't miss.
The trouble
with you, Werner
you don't have any ambition.
Ambition?
Ambition for what?
What? You will see.
Yeah, pretty soon now.
(male narrator) During
the month of March 1937
a young man appeared
several times
at the New York
Public Library
and referred to a copy
of the book entitled
"German Espionage
in the Last War"
authored by former Reich's
military intelligence chief
Colonel Ulrich von Hartman.
Describing himself falsely
as an ex-officer
in the United States Air Corps
with access to military
and aviation secrets
Schneider offers
his services as a Nazi spy.
Addressing his letter
to Hitler's personal newspaper
the "Volkischer Beobachter"
in Berlin
from where it is forwarded
to the offices of
the German Ministry of War.
Here, with methodical
thoroughness
the letter is referred
to the German Naval
Intelligence Service
where finally it comes
to the personal attention
of Captain-Lieutenant
Wilhelm Straubel
who submits it in a report
to his superior
Captain von Eichen.
We'll discuss these later. Next.
As requested, our agents
in Central America
made a topographical map
of the island
of Escudo de Veragua.
How far is it from
the Panama Canal?
About 100 miles, sir.
Got it.
- Hoover?
- Yes, sir?
Have this sent to
the naval ministry.
Yes, sir.
Is that all
for Central America?
- Yes, sir. United States.
- Next.
Our agents in Los Angeles
were able to get the blueprints
of a retractable
landing gear
used in their
new army bombers.
- What else?
- I also have a sketch
of a recent improvement
in the sight
used in pursuit of machine guns.
- Hoover?
- Yes, sir?
- Air ministry.
- Yes, sir.
What about the United States
army mobilization plans
for the eastern coast?
We haven't been able
to get them yet.
Why not?
You've had three months.
I'm sorry, sir.
We're doing
everything we can.
We're adding
new agents every day
in order to increase
our efficiency
in the United States.
In these files are reports
on 12 new men
for your consideration
and final approval.
I see.
What about this
Kurt Schneider?
Our men in New York
have been contacting him
for the last three months.
You will note
the reports are favorable.
I don't know, Straubel
but a man who
writes a newspaper
as if he were applying
for a clerk's job
sounds like
a simpleton to me.
Perhaps
but our investigations
show that he is very willing.
That's what counts.
After all, the Americans
are very simple-minded people.
It doesn't need a wolf
where a weasel will do.
Oh? How do we know he isn't a
United States government agent?
The United States government
doesn't think it necessary
to have a counter
espionage system.
Did you give this man
any specific instructions?
Yes, sir.
I ordered him to provide me
with the secret radio code
used between army airplanes
and ground stations.
The code, I believe,
is known as the Z code.
And I also ordered him
to provide me with a report
on the number of troops
stationed in the New York area.
But if you
are still doubtful
I suggest that you have
Schlager contact him
when he arrives in New York.
Very well.
Has the Bismarck sailed yet?
Yes, sir. It should be
well out to sea by now.
Von Eichen speaking.
Radiogram to Franz Schlager
aboard the S.S. Bismarck.
"Contact Kurt Schneider
1760 Griffin Street,
New York."
[dramatic music]
[keys clacking]
[knocking on door]
(Schlager)
...that the whole world
is united in its resolve
to keep Germany from
its place from the sun.
That is why
our beloved fuhrer
demands constant
vigilance of us.
That is why I call
you gentlemen together
at the beginning
of each crossing
to remind you that as good
national socialists...
...that as good
national socialists
you must keep your ears
and eyes open at all times.
If for any reason you suspect
anyone of being an enemy
you must report
that person to me immediately
because only by knowing
who are enemies are
do we know who to destroy.
And when
we've destroyed them
we can fulfill the promise
of our sacred force mission.
Tomorrow the world is ours.
Heil Hitler.
(all)
Heil Hitler!
One more thing
remember that no one,
no matter where he is
can call himself a German
unless he's
a national socialist.
And do not think that when
we land in New York
that you are
on American soil.
Can you escape,
shall I say
the protecting eye
of your government?
Dismissed.
What does he mean
by the protecting eye?
Talk too much.
You'll find out.
Well, gentlemen,
how did it seem to you?
Not enough interest.
No spirit, Schlager.
The men seem very quiet.
- Not enough enthusiasm.
- Yes, I know.
But you understand
that on board ship
we must consider
the passengers.
Was this your first
trip to Germany?
No, I was born in Germany.
Really? Where?
In Lunenburg.
Do you know it?
Yes, we always get our
Christmas candles from there.
They smell so good.
Yes, the smell
of honey and heather.
Hills almost as far
as the eye can see.
And new groups of sheep
white against the purple.
And the old square
with chestnut trees.
So old, so peaceful.
We used to play there
when we were children
my brother and I.
And you found it changed?
Changed?
The sheep are gone now.
Why?
There's Hitler's Storm Trooper
in the middle of heather.
My old pastor's in
the concentration camp.
My friends talk in whispers
when they talk at all.
You have family left
in Lunenburg?
Yes, my brother
and some relatives,
and their children.
Oh, I wish that...
You believe
in their system?
I believe in the purpose
and the destiny
of the Third Reich
and our Fuhrer, Adolf Hitler.
I have finished.
Another thing
we've been checking up
on the second engineer.
- Yes?
- You'll order him
- replaced by the third.
- Any reasons?
It should not be necessary
to remind you, Schlager
that the Gestapo doesn't have
to give reasons for its orders.
I'm sorry.
Franz...
Uh, Herr Schlager
may I talk to you alone?
Go ahead,
Fraulein Kleinhauer
these gentlemen
are friends.
I wish, I wish to
report someone.
- A woman.
- Her name?
Anna Keller.
- Is she a German citizen?
- I don't know.
Well, why didn't
you find out?
Well, I didn't think to.
No, of course not.
Women never think.
Did you find out if she had
family living in Germany?
- I did.
- Well, their names?
- Addresses?
- I don't know,
but her family lives
in Lunenburg.
Lunenburg.
Thank you.
You may go now.
[door shuts]
Hilda.
Oh, Hilda.
I'm sorry
I was so abrupt
but you understand
I had to be
- in front of those two men.
- Who are they?
- State secret police.
- Gestapo?
They're going to be stationed
in New York.
Gestapo in New York?
Yes, now don't say
a word about it.
I've got to
go back now.
They told me to install Fisher
as second
and remove Wilhelm.
I do not protest against
party discipline, captain.
It's none of my business what
the second has said or done
but it is my business
when they force me
to promote a man
over someone else's head
simply because
he's a good Nazi.
Don't worry, Klauber
I'll get your man
back for you.
I'm still master
of this ship
and no political leader
is going to destroy
the morale of my crew.
[knock on door]
Come in.
The captain sent for me.
Come here, Schlager.
Thank you, sir.
I'm given
to understand
that you ordered Wilhelm
the second engineer replaced.
That is correct, sir.
Would you mind telling me
by what right
you interfere
with the personnel
of this ship?
By my right
as political leader.
We're at sea, Schlager.
There will be no politics
aboard this ship
and only one master.
Wilhelm will be reinstated.
That's all.
I suggest the captain
use a little
more discretion.
You dare to suggest to me?
It is always unfortunate
to interfere with the acts
of the Gestapo.
The Gestapo?
Then they ordered
Wilhelm's removal.
But why?
I have long since
learned never to ask
why the Gestapo
does anything.
For his own good, I suggest
the captain do the same.
Is there anything else
the captain wishes?
No. You may go now.
Heil Hitler.
Perhaps we have lived
too long, captain.
We are dead already, Klauber
but our families
in Germany
are still alive.
Hostages
do not seek courage.
(male narrator)
August 30th, 1937,
Stuttgart, Germany.
Thousands of
national socialists
from all
parts of the world
gather for a congress
of Germans living abroad.
They hear..
[speaking in German]
(male narrator)
"...we national socialists
reject any German
whose ambition it is
to assimilate
with the people
of the country
in which he lives
because we only recognize
as a complete German
that citizen who always
and everywhere
remains a German
and nothing but a German."
Germans in the United States
must be brought back
to the racial unity
and common faith
of all Germans.
As racial comrades,
as Germans
we cannot help
but be revolted by this
basically
uncultured country.
And we know that
if America is to be free
we must destroy the chain
that ties the whole misery
of American
politics together
and that chain is
the United States Constitution.
[indistinct chatter]
And we also know
that there is a wall
in which a breach
must be made
before American's
problems can be solved
and that wall
is the bill of rights.
[indistinct chatter]
(man) Wait a minute, buddy!
Just how do you fellas
expect to get rid
of the constitution
and the bill of rights?
What are you?
A member of
the German-American Bund?
No, I'm not a member.
I belong to
the American legion.
Hold on here.
A lot of us Americans
went overseas
and fought you Germans
because we thought
that the constitution
and the bill of rights
was worth fighting for.
[indistinct yelling]
Hey! Hey!
Why don't you
answer his question?
Why do you
shout him down?
And who are you?
What do you want?
I am an American
of German birth
and there are hundreds
of thousands like me
who stand absolutely
against you Nazis.
You can't make these
ex-soldiers believe
that all the Germans
in America
are traitors like you.
We'll fight side by
side for democracy.
[clamoring]
You people made democracy
a fanatical faith.
It's no use
arguing with you.
Doctor, please.
Force is the only language
you will understand
and we'll speak to you in
your own language soon enough.
We don't want any ism's
in this country
except Americanism.
If you guys
don't like it here...
Wait a minute.
I've got a right
to speak up in open meeting.
This is free country.
Sure, and we're gonna
keep it that way.
You guys are worse
than gangsters.
[clamoring]
Stop them, doctor.
Stop them.
This is no way
to handle them.
If you feel so strongly
about it, Greutzwald
why don't you
complain directly
to the minister
of propaganda?
[crowd clamoring]
[dramatic music]
[knock on door]
(Werner)
Is anybody home?
Hello, Kurt.
Hello, Werner.
Hello, sonny boy.
Having fun?
What are you
so low about?
Where's Helen?
News from
the old country?
Nothing important.
What's the matter?
Rent due again?
Rent's always due.
What are you doing
home today?
I'm on leave
until Monday.
You home, too?
- Hello, Helen.
- It's fine.
Now I'll have
two of you underfoot.
As if one wasn't
too much already.
We are not bothering you.
I married you,
not your pal.
Just to see you sitting
around doing nothing
is enough to drive
a person crazy.
I'm not doing nothing.
I'm thinking.
Thinking.
The last time
he was thinking
he ended up by
deserting from the army
so he wouldn't
have to go to jail
for embezzling
company funds.
Now, look here,
Helen, I--
He didn't go to work today
because he had to think.
He's given up his night job
at the language school
so he'd have more time
to think.
Go to those awful
Nazi meetings.
You should think less
about some way to get rich quick
and more about
paying the rent
and getting milk
for the baby.
I'll get more than that.
You will see.
You'll be mighty proud
when people point you out
as the wife
of Kurt Schneider.
He's off again.
Oh, come on, Werner.
Let's get out of here.
No, you don't. You got to take
the baby for a walk.
Imagine, asking a man like me
to push a baby carriage.
You see, Werner,
the trouble with Helen
is she doesn't
understand me.
She doesn't realize
a man like me
has to be involved
in big things
or he's unhappy.
But I don't expect
people to understand me.
Even Hitler
had a tough time
before he showed them
what a genius he is.
- He sure did.
- And look at him now.
Let's sit down here.
There was a speaker
at the bund meeting last night.
He said Hitler would
rule the world before long.
- Cigarette?
- No.
Werner, I helped you out
of a lot of jams, haven't I?
Sure. Why?
Well, there's something
I want to tell you.
But first I'd like
to make sure I can trust you.
Who, me?
You can trust me, Kurt.
I'd never
let you down.
I'd have been
in an awful spot
if you hadn't given
me room and grub
all the time I was
looking around for a job.
I've got to be
absolutely sure about you.
Come on.
What's on your mind?
Werner, I'm in the German
Secret Service now.
You are?
Yeah, I'm one of
their most trusted men.
I get my instructions
from Hitler himself.
- You do?
- Yeah.
Pretty soon
I'll be in charge
of all German espionage
in the United States.
Golly, Kurt, you must be making
a lot of money.
Why, money isn't everything.
Now listen, Werner,
you've got to help me.
What do you
want me to do?
Swear you won't tell a soul
what I'm telling you.
Alright.
I want you to get me
the secret code
used between military
planes and land bases.
- The Z code?
- Yeah.
Oh, I couldn't do that.
Why, I'd be court-martialed
if they found out that I--
Don't be silly, Werner.
Stick with me
and I, I'll make you famous.
- Rich.
- Well, I--
Swell. I knew you wouldn't
let me down.
Golly, Kurt.
I don't know about--
Now listen.
That Z code is a cinch to get,
isn't it?
No, it's not so easy.
But you know
how to get it.
Sure, but--
Well, then get it
and stop worrying.
I've got a tougher job
than that to figure out.
How, how do you suppose
I could find out
how many troops are stationed
in the New York area?
Well, I don't know. I, I suppose
you could check each regiment--
Oh, no, no.
That's no good.
Don't worry about it.
I'll figure out
some way to get this stuff.
You know me, Werner
when I make up my mind
to get something
I get it.
(male narrator)
A few days later
the sick clerk at
Fort Wentworth Station Hospital
receives a telephone call.
[telephone rings]
Fort Wentworth
Station Hospital
sick clerk speaking.
Major Wilton?
Oh, yes, sir.
I'm delivering a lecture before
a group of physicians today
and I'll need the statistical
reports on army hospitalization
to make certain points.
Yes, sir.
I understand perfectly.
The statistical report
sent to the northeast corner
of 93rd and Lexington Avenue.
Deliver it
to your personally
and you'll be wearing
civilian clothes.
Yes, sir.
Right away, sir.
What'll it be?
Give me
a chocolate soda.
Yes.
- Hello, Werner.
- Huh?
Oh, hello, Kurt.
- Did you get it?
- Yeah.
Ah. Where is it?
Not here.
I'll get it
from you later.
That's right.
Did you get yours?
- They're on the way.
- Huh?
- What'll you have?
- Give me a pineapple soda.
- One pine in.
- What do you mean?
What's on its way?
The medical report.
What do you want
medical reports for?
You wouldn't know,
would you?
If you had to find out
how many troops
are stationed in
the New York area
you would try
to count each regiment.
Here you are.
But what do medical reports
got to do with
the number of troops?
Don't they always figure
the percentage of men sick
of the total number of men
station in the area?
Golly. I never thought of that.
Watch me, my boy.
And you'll learn plenty.
You've got to
have brains
to figure things out
in this business.
Brains and daring.
Yeah.
Stay here.
I'm Major Wilton.
You are ten minutes late.
Sorry, sir.
Held up by traffic.
Let me have
those reports.
Yes, sir.
- Good. Thank you.
- Beg your pardon, sir.
- The taxi.
- Oh, yes. How much?
$2.90.
Keep the change.
[bell ringing]
Yes?
- Is Mr. Schneider at home?
- No.
Do you expect him soon?
He should have been home
an hour ago.
Then may we wait
for him please?
Well, yes, I guess so.
Just go in the other room
and wait, please.
This way.
Just make yourselves comfortable.
Thank you.
Well, where have you two been?
I had important business.
I can imagine.
You got some visitors.
They just arrived.
Visitors?
Yes, and hurry up
and get rid of them.
Dinner won't be
fit to eat.
Do you suppose they,
they found out already?
Don't be silly.
Go in the kitchen
and keep Helen out of here.
Mr. Schneider?
Yes?
Allow me to
introduce myself.
Franz Schlager.
Ms. Kleinhauer.
How do you do?
How do you do,
Mr. Schneider?
We may talk without fear
of being overheard?
Why?
We have mutual friends
in Germany.
Colonel Nicolai,
Herr Schiller
Herr Jaegerschmidt.
You come from them?
I was sent by
Herr Schiller.
Just a minute.
Have you any means
of identifying yourself?
Will it satisfy you
if I tell you
that your last instructions
were to obtain a certain
air force code and figures
on the number of troops
stationed in the New York area?
Yes.
That's correct.
Thank you.
Now it's to business.
You got our last letter.
What have
you done about it?
Well, I volunteered
my services to the fatherland
but the fatherland has not
yet offered to pay me anything.
You must first earn it.
I'm ready, when I know
how much I'll get.
You have something?
Yes.
I believe these will be
of interest to you.
The Z code.
Very good.
But we didn't ask for
any medical report.
You will notice the
report states what percentage
of the manpower
of each regiment is there.
A little simple arithmetic
will give you the total manpower
of the whole area.
Well...
So you have accomplished
something after all.
Put these in
your purse, Hilda.
Not many would have had
the daring to do
what I did.
All right,
we will give you $50 a month.
That's, that's ridiculous.
I have to live.
I have to support
a family.
Do something worthwhile
and you will be paid extra.
Don't you consider
what I gave you worthwhile?
Yes, in a way.
But what we really want
are the blueprints
of the aircraft carriers
Yorktown and Lexington
the eastern seaboard
mobilization plans.
We also want information
concerning aircraft
detection experiments
being made at Fort Munmus.
For those things, you
will be paid extra, and well.
Here's your $50.
Goodnight, Schneider.
Well, I think the stuff
I've given you
is worth something extra.
We're not giving away
$50 for nothing.
But I--
Of course, if you don't want
to accept it.
- I'll take it.
- That's better.
It's up to you whether
or not you earn more.
And remember,
we're not easily fooled.
You can depend on me.
Good. Now one thing more
you will send all mail
concerning our business
to Mrs. Mary McLaughlin
One Cascade Road,
Argyle, Scotland
and you will sign
yourself "Sword."
I'll write that down.
No, you better keep it
in your head.
Do you have a telephone?
Yes. Over there.
Thank you.
[dialing]
Hello,
is the doctor there?
Franz Schlager.
Sword.
Mary McLaughlin,
One Cascade Road.
Hello, doctor.
I'll be over at the cafe
within an hour.
Yes, everything is arranged.
The two men I told you about
will be there.
Yes, doctor.
Well, goodbye, Schneider.
Well...
Heil Hitler.
Come, Hilda.
[door opens]
[door closes]
[instrumental music]
There was a time
I even admired Hitler
because I believed
he expressed the resentment
and humiliation
of the German people
against the injustice
after the war.
But now I see only pain
and those emotions
for his own purposes.
What has he not done to all
to want us back to Germany?
He made us appear savages
in the eyes of civilization.
If I were you, Greutzwald
I wouldn't express
such opinions too openly.
It might be dangerous.
But he's perfectly
right, Helldorf.
We mustn't be misled
by men like Kassell.
Eh, Kassell.
Kassell thinks
he can spread the same hatreds
here in America.
We must realize that the
vast majority of Germans here
are ashamed of the black name
we are giving them
and are violently
opposed to these ideas.
Be careful.
Don't talk so loud.
Somebody might hear.
You see?
Right now he's talking
with two of our
most valuable agents
Helldorf, who works in
a big munitions plant
and Walter Westphal.
Now, you understand
I have nothing
against Greutzwald personally
but with
his constant criticism
he's endangering
our success.
Does he know those men
are our agents?
No, of course not.
But he might convince them they
are working for a lost cause.
And in any case, the
party doesn't want criticism
only obedience.
Dr. Kassell
see the gentleman
in the small room
in the rear.
[indistinct chatter]
Please understand that.
I love my fatherland
as much as anyone.
But how can Americans
possibly have decent,
cordial relations
with a regime whose
aim is to destroy
the very best of
German culture?
With a regime
employing methods
that have outraged
our own people?
Good evening, gentlemen.
- Good evening.
- Dr. Kassell.
You know Westphal.
Oh, yes.
How are you, Westphal?
- How do you do?
- May I join you?
- Oh, please do. Sit down.
- Thank you.
Greutzwald and I are
about to get into an argument.
Oh, Greutzwald.
Yes, he and I are
old platform enemies.
One may not
agree with him
but one must respect
his honesty and courage.
Thank you, doctor.
Oh, not at all.
I only wish I could add
discretion to that.
You have called me
an honest man, Dr. Kassell.
Yes.
You see,
I've given a great deal
of thought to what
you said to me
that night of
the legion incident
and I would like very much
to talk it over with you.
Alone.
Of course.
I'd be delighted to.
Well, we are
finished anyway.
Oh, no, no, no. We can go
to the private room.
Yes.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
Thank you.
You see, Greutzwald
we cannot afford to
have any differences...
Greutzwald is right, Max.
Art is becoming so bold
in this country, so outspoken.
Don't be a fool.
Nevertheless, I'm beginning to
wish I weren't mixed up in it.
I wouldn't talk like
that if I were you.
Yes, Greutzwald, it must
be realized that, after all
we need to think as one man
if our cause is to succeed.
Go ahead.
Thank you.
You said we were
going to be alone.
I thought these gentlemen would
help us adjust our differences.
These gentlemen?
Yes. We have instructions
for you, Greutzwald.
You are going back
to Germany.
Why?
What do you mean?
Who are you?
I'm sorry.
I forgot to introduce.
Herr Hintze
and Herr Wildebrandt.
- Members of the Gestapo.
- Gestapo?
Yes, Herr Greutzwald.
Your actions
have become much too dangerous
for you to remain here.
That isn't true.
All I tried to do
was to honestly
point out the dangers
of the wrong policy.
There's room for
honest criticism.
When you became a member of
the national socialist party
you swore allegiance
to the fuhrer
and blind obedience
to party discipline.
I believed in
national socialism
and I trusted our fuhrer.
But I disagree now
that the party is--
No one disagrees
with the party, Greutzwald.
You'll discover that
when you get back to Germany.
But I don't want to
go back to Germany.
I have done nothing. Please!
Please let me go.
You can't do this to me.
We, we are still in America.
I didn't mean
anything wrong.
Please, I don't want
to go back to Germany.
I don't want to
go back to Germany.
I don't want to go
back to Germany! Please Herr--
Please don't send me back!
I haven't done anything!
You can't do this to me.
Let me out of here!
I didn't do anything.
I swear I didn't.
Please don't send me
back to Germany.
You can't do this to me.
You can't!
You have no right.
Oh, please don't send me
back to Germany.
What I'm trying to do
was only...
Don't send me back.
I haven't done...
[dramatic music]
[machine clacking]
- We say goodbye here.
- I can't understand, Karl.
Why you don't let me
go onboard with you.
I'm telling you, I got orders
to keep this trip secret.
I don't want anyone
to see you with me.
- I don't see what--
- Lisa, please do as I ask you.
Goodbye, dear.
And take care of yourself.
I'll write often,
and don't forget
I've gone to Maine for
a month if anyone asks.
- I won't...
- Goodbye.
[foghorn blares]
[indistinct chatter]
[whirring]
[dramatic music]
(male narrator)
Arriving in Germany
Dr. Kassell finds
a totally different fatherland
from the one he left
ten years before.
Following faithfully
the program
of the new bible
of Adolf Hitler, "My Battle"
the Nazi party has created
a new fascist society
based on a devout worship
of the Aryan superman
a new fascist culture
imbued with the glorification
of conquest and war
a fascist system of life
where every man, woman,
and child
must think alike, speak alike,
and do alike
a rigidly censored press
with all news colored by
the ministry of propaganda
a fascist literature
shorn of its greatest writers
and poets
a new religion
ridiculing the brotherhood
and equality of man before God
a fascist economy
with its watchword
"cannons, not butter"
a fascist philosophy
with a supreme command
blind obedience
to the fuhrer.
For six long centuries
men throughout the world
have fought their way
out of the dark ages
of medieval barbarism
but in six short years
Hitler's Nazis cast
their ominous shadow
over the entire Earth.
[band music]
Inspiring.
Positively inspiring.
Makes one proud
to be a German.
Your enthusiasm
is reassuring.
But not unexpected,
I hope.
No.
You have done excellent work
in the United States
for the party, Herr Doctor.
Thank you.
Thank you very much,
Your Excellency.
That's all.
Dr. Kassell
we have decided
to place you in charge
of all national socialistic
activity in the United States.
I am deeply honored,
Your Excellency.
And I only hope that--
There will be a slight change
in our methods.
From now on
national socialism
in the United States
must dress itself
in the American flag.
It must appear to be
a defense of Americanism
but at the same time,
our aim must always be
to discredit conditions
there in the United States
and in this way, make life in
Germany admired and wished for.
Racial and religious hatreds
must be fostered
on the basis of
American Aryanism.
Class hatreds
must be encouraged
in such a way that labor
and the middle classes
will become confused
and antagonistic.
In the ensuing chaos
we will be able
to take control.
But that will take tremendous
sums of money and propaganda.
The money will be provided.
From now on, German boats
touching American ports
will carry three times as much
propaganda material.
Deliver it to our agents
in the United States.
Look.
The United States will be
divided into three parts
each to have
a provincial leader.
One will be stationed
in New York
one in Chicago
one in Los Angeles.
You will be given the names
of all our agents
and you will coordinate
all their activities.
You will see to it
that every city
town, village
in the United States
is provided with
our propaganda material.
So, from now on
your watchword will be
"America for Americans."
But never forget that
national socialism
is the hammer
not the anvil.
This new Americanism
is a formless iron...
...that we will beat
into another swastika.
[dramatic music]
(male narrator)
Nazi propaganda
printed in huge quantities
by the power presses
in Germany
carefully devised to fit
the official German concept
of mass stupidity
constitutes heavy cargoes
aboard German freighters
en route to the United States.
They are designed to alter
the fundamental ideas
of a kindly
and liberty-loving people.
This material is shipped
directly to American ports
unloaded with great secrecy,
put on trucks
and generally prepared
for wholesale distribution
throughout the United States
to New York, Boston,
and New Orleans.
To the vast midwestern
agricultural districts
of Minnesota, Illinois,
and Wisconsin.
To the coast cities of
San Francisco
Seattle, and Los Angeles.
To the great manufacturing
centers of Chicago
St. Louis, and Detroit.
To the great wheat centers
of Kansas City
Minneapolis,
and Saint Paul.
Huge shipments
a deluge of vitriolic,
scurrilous propaganda
circulated by the Nazis
and certain
American sympathizers
ready to violate
the basic principles
of their American citizenship.
Aided by the disgruntled
the dishonest,
and the disloyal
an intensive campaign
is launched to create
mass sympathy
for the doctrines glorifying
hatred and brute force.
[dramatic music]
[whirring]
The stream of Nazi propaganda
insidiously attempts
to penetrate
every nerve
and fiber of American life
inciting racial prejudice
ridiculing democracy
striving to shatter
that attitude of tolerance
and respect for minority rights
which entitle people
to consider themselves
as civilized human beings
while other forces
fostered by the long arm of
the Nazi intelligence service
are at work in centers of
the United States defense.
[airplanes droning]
Well, Werner, it's getting
so I hate to go home.
Bills, bills,
and more bills.
And Helen after me
all the time.
Seems I can never
get ahead.
Sure don't make
much money
working for the fatherland.
Hey, maybe you ought
to try to get back
to teaching German at night.
There's no money
in that.
[car horn honks]
What's happenin'?
It's Colonel Austin, commander
of Fort Colton, and his aides.
They're being flown down
to Washington on a transport.
I see.
Say, wouldn't an officer
in charge of the fort
have mobilization plans
for this area?
Oh, I guess he would.
I think I know
how to get $2,000.
What?
It's terrific.
It's daring.
What's daring?
What are you talking about?
I don't trust
that Schlager.
He'll not only
take the credit
but he'll probably gyp me
out of the money, too.
What money?
Money for
the mobilization plans.
But I won't give him
a chance to gyp me.
I'm going to write
to Germany directly.
That's what I'll do.
I hope I haven't forgotten that
woman's address in Scotland.
[doorbell rings]
Good morning,
Mrs. McLaughlin.
- Morning.
- Nice mail, as usual.
There's
an interesting stamp.
- Japanese, isn't it?
- Yes.
What is it, please?
You Mrs. McLaughlin?
- Yes.
- May we come in?
Why? Who are you?
British military intelligence.
You're under arrest.
(male narrator)
Because of
a postman's curiosity
British military intelligence
discovers Mrs. McLaughlin
is the European post office
for a Nazi spy ring
that spreads over
the whole world
and it finds a letter that
sends a British official
to the transatlantic telephone.
Yes.
And your Colonel Austin
is to be instructed to appear
at a secret emergency
staff meeting
and to bring with him
all mobilization
and coast defense plans.
Once in the room,
he's to be attacked.
Killed, if necessary.
And the plans stolen.
The letter is signed "Sword."
[dramatic music]
As soon as British military
intelligence called
we went to work trying
to find this fellow
who signed himself Sword.
Did you have
anything to go by?
- We thought so then.
- How long ago was that?
About three weeks ago.
Sword identified
himself in this letter
as a former army officer.
With important connections
at Monroe Field.
All right.
What then?
We went to work immediately.
Got a line on every officer
or person of any influence
at Monroe Field.
We did everything else we
could think of, but got nowhere.
That's why I'm asking the FBI
to take over this case.
We've got to find
this fellow Sword.
(male #1)
You see, that's a bit out
of our line, Major Williams.
As far as I know, the FBI
has never done
any counterespionage work.
Well, somebody's
got to do it. I can't.
The whole staff
of the United States
military intelligence service
in the New York area
consists of myself
and one assistant.
I don't suppose
the government thinks
the intelligence service is
very necessary in peacetimes.
That's what's so strange
about all of this.
You'd think from
the number of spies
they've been sending over here
that we're at war with Germany.
On the contrary, it looks more
as if Germany
were at war with us.
Nazi Bunds meeting
all over the nation
openly training men
for street fights
teaching them
how to use guns and bayonets.
The whole country's swamped
with Nazi propaganda
fresh from Germany.
Tie the two together.
It looks as if
the storm troopers
are training to finish off
what the propaganda starts.
It's a new kind of war
but it's still war.
Well, how does espionage
fit into that?
Well, uh, just look
at this letter.
The man who wrote this
is obviously a German
but he's not
a professional spy.
Well, we couldn't find
anything about him.
Well, perhaps you didn't look
in the right place.
Got any ideas, Renard?
Yes. I'd look into
every bund
and pro-Nazi organization
around these parts.
I told you I thought
this man is an amateur.
If he is,
why did he become a spy?
Well, because he's been
listening to speeches
and reading pamphlets
about Nazi Germany
and believing them.
Unfortunately, there are
thousands like him in America.
Half-witted,
hysterical crackpots
who go Hitler-happy
from overindulgence
in propaganda
that makes them believe
that they're supermen.
American Nazi organizations.
That's where we'll find your man
sword, Major Williams.
If we ever find him.
[bugle music]
[band music]
[crowd cheering]
(all)
Heil! Heil Heil Heil!
[indistinct shouts]
Attention!
Eyes right!
Up!
You see, this is the type
of German-American youth
we are striving to develop.
- Your name?
- Gottfried Simmons, sir.
- Rank?
- Squad leader.
Order service youth, troop C.
Do you subscribe
to the principles
of our glorious fuhrer?
- Heil Hitler.
- Very good.
- Thank you, sir.
Attention!
Eyes left!
Up!
What are the ideals
of German womanhood?
To be of service
to our fuhrer.
To be the custodian
of our children
until he should
call them to arms.
Very good.
No German abroad
may forget that he is
always and everywhere
a piece of Germany.
We must warn
the so-called democracies
that the fatherland
is not only ready
but strong enough to protect
Germans all over the world.
And to you, the national
socialist youth of America
I bring directly the hearty
greetings of our beloved fuhrer
Adolf Hitler.
Heil! Heil! Heil!
- [cheering]
- [whistle blows]
[drumbeats]
[band music]
My congratulations, Kranz.
It makes me feel
I'm really in Berlin.
You should begin to train them
with rifles
and revolvers, Kranz.
They are trained.
[instrumental music]
You can go in now.
Thank you. Come, Westphal.
Can you tell me
if Franz Schlager is here?
- Who wants to see him?
- Tell him Kurt Schneider.
Sit down, I'll let you know.
Tell Schlager there's
a Kurt Schneider out here.
Glass of beer.
I've been up all last night
getting this finished.
Man to see you.
His name is Schneider.
Who, Schneider?
- Tell him to wait.
- Yes, sir.
I told you, Helldorf
is one of our most capable men.
Now, with the Zenith
Munitions Corporation
in New Jersey.
You realize, gentlemen
there have been so many changes
in American anti-aircraft
guns since last year.
But I was first to work
on the ground-up helping them.
(Hintze)
Of course, you didn't construct
this at your factory.
No, I had to remember
each little part
as the work progressed.
I fit them all together
at home every night.
Excellent piece of workmanship.
(Helldorf)
And you will observe
the perfect timing
of the mechanism.
Constructed to exact scale.
Our air ministry will have
to express its appreciation
of American inventive genius.
Miss Kleinhauer,
I want you to be very careful
handling his model en route.
Don't worry, doctor
Hilda is absolutely trustworthy.
Schlager, when you
turn this over
to Captain-Lieutenant Straubel
in Hamburg
I want you to give due credit
to our friend Helldorf.
My sincere thanks, Herr doctor.
Now regarding you, Westphal.
Uh, Westphal is with the...
In Long Island.
I heard your plant
is turning out
a new-type supercharger
for pursuit ships.
Yes, we are.
How soon can we get
the blueprints?
I don't know.
They're very closely guarded.
It's very dangerous.
What's the matter
with you, Westphal?
- Are you afraid?
- Yes.
What if I should get caught?
You'll be properly protected.
But Dr. Kassell, I have a wife,
- two children.
- They should be proud of you.
But you don't understand.
They are Americans.
They'd consider me a traitor
instead of being proud.
Well, what do you want?
Come to the point.
Uh, I want to quit.
I want to wash my hands
of all this business.
Are you serious
about this statement, Westphal?
Well, I...
Now, Westphal,
have you ever heard
of an organization
known as the Gestapo?
Gestapo?
I think, gentlemen,
we don't need to be concerned
about our friend Westphal.
No. Of course not.
I don't know.
I didn't know what I was saying.
No, of course you didn't.
I really didn't mean
anything by it.
I'm very sorry.
Quite all right.
We'll forget it this time.
Here, have a beer.
Thank you.
Schlager, you may inform
Captain-Lieutenant Straubel
that you have the blueprints
not later than
by your next trip.
I will, Herr Doctor.
That man Schneider
is still here.
He asked me to remind you.
Oh, yes, I'm coming.
Excuse me, gentlemen.
Where is he?
He's sitting over there,
Herr Schlager.
- You wanted to see me?
- Yes, I...
I wanted to know if Schuler
gave you any message for me.
Well, you have
your instructions already.
Yes, but I thought
he might have given you
a personal message for me.
An answer to the letter
I wrote him.
- You wrote him a letter?
- Yes, to his Scotland address.
Quiet.
What will it be, Herr Schlager?
- Two beers.
- Yes, sir.
Be more discreet mentioning
names in public places.
What was your letter about?
It was a scheme I worked out.
It could hold up
the mobilization schedules
and coast defense plans.
By kidnapping a certain
important army officer.
Kidnap?
Here you are.
Thank you.
Well, did you get to him?
No, I didn't even start.
I was waiting to hear from...
Well, you know, to get his okay
and how much they'd paid for it.
Always worrying about money.
Don't you see?
My wife is going to have a baby.
I've got to get some real money.
Then you better forget
these crazy schemes
about kidnapping
and concentrate
on our instructions.
For instance, we could use
some American passports.
- Passports?
- Yes. We need them
for our agents
going to South America.
You mean blank passports?
Any kind, old ones, expired ones
we'll fix 'em up, only, get some
we'll pay you $5 extra
for each one.
Now remember, I expect something
for that $50 a month.
- Sure.
- Bye, Schneider.
[telephone ringing]
Passport division,
Harrison speaking.
Yes.
Who?
Harold Mitchell,
undersecretary of state.
Yes, I'm here in New York.
It's a confidential trip.
Now there's something
quite important.
I need 35 blank passports
delivered to me immediately here
at the Hotel Atlanta
as quickly as possible.
Mr. Harold Mitchell, yes.
Hotel Atlanta.
But Mr. Mitchell, this is
rather an unusual request.
I'm afraid I'll have
to check back with you.
I have no time to waste.
This is state department
business!
Send those passports
over immediately!
I want those delivered
in half an hour at the latest!
Yes, Mr. Mitchell,
I'll... send them right over.
Hello?
Extension 615.
Passport division?
Uh, this is Mr. Mitchell again.
I've just decided,
if it's too much trouble
I'll get those passports
in Washington myself tomorrow.
Oh, it's perfectly all right,
Mr. Mitchell, no trouble at all.
I'll have those passports
delivered for you
in half an hour.
Yes, Hotel Atlanta.
No trouble at all.
Goodbye, sir.
Get me the police department.
The alien squad.
Yes.
Can I help you, sir?
Why, yes, I was just
wondering if, uh...
[telephone rings]
Excuse me.
Hotel Atlanta,
room clerk speaking.
Yes, sir, I understand exactly.
Just a second, I'll see.
No. No, I'm afraid
he hasn't arrived yet.
All right.
As you were saying?
Yes, I was just
wondering if, uh,
if you had a Pennsylvania
rail road time schedule.
You'll find one
at the porter's desk
the other end of the lobby.
- Thank you.
- All right.
Boy?
Operator?
Give me Western Union.
You want us to pick it up
at the Hotel Atlanta?
And where should
we send the package?
To our own office
at Grand Central Station.
Same name?
Thank you, Mr. Mitchell.
Have you a package
for Mr. Harold Mitchell?
- Yes.
- We're instructed to deliver it
to our Grand Central office.
Just a minute.
There's a Western Union
boy outside.
He's to deliver the package
to the Western Union office
at Grand Central Station.
- Let him have it.
- All right.
(Helen)
Kurt? Kurt, for heaven's sakes,
it's 1 o'clock.
You gonna stay up all night?
Go on to sleep
and leave me alone.
Hello?
Western Union Grand Central?
You have a package
for Mr. Mitchell?
Will you please send it
to your Varick Street office?
I'll pick it up tomorrow.
Well, yes, Mr. Mitchell.
Yes, thank you, sir.
- Where did he say?
- To our Varick Street office.
Thank you. Come on, Fred.
To the Queen's Tavern
on Walker Street.
Yes, Mr. Mitchell,
I'll have a boy there
with your package right away.
Yes, thank you.
Queen's Tavern on Walker Street.
[horn honking]
Eh, shine, buddy?
Here, get a shine!
Oh, would you like a shine?
[indistinct chatter]
Hey, Mister,
I'm gonna shine you.
Hey, would you like a shine?
[indistinct chatter]
(kid)
Please, it's a very good shine.
Ah, geez!
[car engine revving]
(kid)
Hey, buddy, let's have
the other one.
Hey, what's the matter with you?
I ain't done yet.
- Finished?
- Yep.
- You're all good now, bud.
- Say, uh,
there's a package for me
across the street in the tavern.
Run over there
and pick it up for me.
There might be a small charge.
Here's $2.
Tell them it's for Mr. Mitchell.
Oh.
Here's your package, mister.
- Okay.
- There's 40 cents change here.
- Keep it.
- Thanks.
Just a minute, Mr. Mitchell.
We wanna talk to you.
- What about?
- About this package.
But why? Why is he arrested?
He never does anything
but sit around the house
all day and think.
I knew something
like this would happen
- sooner or later.
- Nothing in there, Mac.
I told you there was nothing
there. Where is he? Tell me
- what you've arrested him for.
- Here's something, Fred.
What is it? What is it
you're searching for?
You got no right
coming around here
in the middle of the night
disturbing people.
Mrs. Schneider, has your husband
ever been connected
with buying or selling furs?
No, of course not.
What gave you that idea?
Never mind.
Sorry we disturbed you.
Goodnight, Mrs. Schneider.
This is the letter the British
Military Intelligence
took from Mary McLaughlin
and this is the one you found
in Schneider's apartment.
- Is that right?
- Yes, Mr. Renard, that's right.
All right. Thank you.
Uh, bring Schneider in.
[indistinct chatter]
Why am I dragged
from place to place
hotels, police departments,
state department?
I'm an American citizen.
I insist on my rights!
I've told you all I know.
I will not be third-degreed!
Sit down, Schneider.
Sit down.
All right, Phillips.
Smoke?
Don't worry.
There's no third degree
with the Federal Bureau
of Investigation.
It's too bad.
What's too bad?
I'm astonished at you, Schneider.
You keep sticking to that story.
A man asked you
to pick up that package
a man you never saw before.
It's true, that's all I know.
(Renard)
I expected more of you.
It's the sort of story
we hear every day
the usual, obvious alibi
of nitwits and common crooks.
From a man of your caliber
I would expect something ingenious
cleverly contrived.
Now look, Schneider.
I'm one of the oldest
operators of the FBI.
I've had to deal
with the most dangerous
criminals in America.
Hijackers, kidnappers, smugglers
the most cunning
international brains.
And now, I am privileged
to investigate the case
of one of the most
famous German spies in America.
A spy who's shown
tremendous daring
imagination, ingenuity
and yet who insists
on pretending to be
nothing but a stupid fool.
I don't understand it.
You, whose brain conceived
and planned
the kidnapping
of Colonel Austin--
- Wha--
- Sit down, Sword.
Sword?
Why do you call me that?
Oh, we've been reading
Mary McLaughlin's correspondence
between Germany
and America for months.
You, you read her mail?
That's how we got your letter
about hijacking
the mobilization plans
from Colonel Austin.
But how did you know
that the plans
would be there
just at that time?
Well, I figured it out.
It wasn't such
a bad idea, was it?
Oh, on the contrary,
an excellent one
if it hadn't been
for our interference.
Judging from your records
you've had a most
extraordinary career.
No, go on. Help yourself.
Shortly after you arrived
from Germany
you enlisted in the army.
One year and eight months later,
you deserted.
Arrested, you served
four months and five days
- in federal military prison.
- Correct.
After your release
you deserted again
this time embezzling
company funds.
Oh...
I couldn't stand
those brass hats
ordering me around.
(Renard)
So you decided
to take up the career
of a German espionage agent.
Correct.
But tell me,
how did you happen to know
that the Nazis
wanted spies over here?
Well, they've got
hundreds of spies here.
You know that, Mr. Renard.
Oh, yes, of course,
but how did you know?
Why, everybody
in the bunds knows that.
(male narrator)
For hours, Renard caters
to Schneider's inflated vanity
skillfully leading him on
to give an account
of his meetings
with Nazi spy contacts
of his success in obtaining
secret military information
of his brilliant plot
to kidnap Colonel Austin
of his wonderful plan
to obtain blank passports.
Many years' experience
in dealing
with every variety
of criminal mentality
enables Renard to be positive
that his present suspect
is a fairly common type
of egomaniac
one whose feeling of superiority
to the general run of mankind
is the direct cause
of criminal tendencies
one who can never be coerced
into making a confession
but who can be flattered
into it.
And so Renard continues praising
Schneider agreeing with him
pretending to consider him
a mastermind
until a full confession
of Schneider's activities
as a Nazi spy
has been extracted.
Oh, by the way we didn't
quite cover the point
of how you obtained the Z code.
Mr. Renard, I am terribly tired.
Come on. We know
you didn't get it by yourself.
Well, a friend of mine
a man I had working for me
but I don't want to
drag him into it.
Uh, was it the man
who lives with you?
Private Werner Renz?
Yes.
And the names of the man
and woman
who contacted you?
- Hilda Kleinhauer.
- And the man?
Mr. Renard, y-you are putting me
in an awkward spot--
Now, don't worry.
You have nothing to fear.
What's his name?
Schlager.
Franz Schlager.
Where can I find them?
I don't know, but every time
the boat docks, they show up.
What boat?
The Bismarck.
[instrumental music]
Private Renz?
- Yes, sir?
- Are you Werner Renz?
- Yes, sir.
- You're under arrest.
(male narrator)
New York Harbor,
Washington's birthday, 1938.
German steamship Bismarck
makes its routine
stop at quarantine
taking aboard
the usual government
customs,
and immigration officials.
But today, the customary staff
includes two men
who do not disclose
their identity
to the ship's officers.
Here are the crew lists, gentlemen.
Thank you. We'll check
their landing passes.
Thank you.
Get your landing passes ready!
- Hans Wiener.
- Yes, sir.
Ludwig Klausner.
- Ludwig Klausner!
- Yes, sir!
(male #2)
Heinrich Dempke.
(crew)
Here, sir.
(male #2)
Haslum Phelan.
Uh, Franz Schlager. Did he sail?
Franz Schlager. He didn't sail?
No, Mr. Chambers.
He isn't aboard.
Why not? Any particular reason?
No, no, nothing, sir,
just that he's on leave.
I see. Thank you.
(male #2)
Hilda Kleinhauer!
Is this your first trip?
No, sir.
All right.
Thank you, Miss Kleinhauer.
Arnold Eppendauer.
(crew)
Yes, sir.
Should we pick her up now?
No, we'll get her in port.
[foghorn blaring]
- Hilda Kleinhauer?
- Yes?
Would you come with us, please?
Why? Who are you?
United States
government officers
Federal Bureau of Investigation.
What do you want from me?
What is it?
I have never done anything
against the United States government.
That's just what we want
to determine, Miss Kleinhauer.
(Renard)
Why didn't Schlager
sail on this trip?
I will complain
to my German consul.
Let me go back
to my ship, please.
I tell you,
I don't know Schlager.
But he's a regular member
of the crew.
Maybe, but the Bismarck's
a big boat.
There are hundreds in the crew.
How about Kurt Schneider?
Kurt Schneider? No.
Please, I am telling you
you have me confused
with someone else.
You visited
Schneider's apartment
together with Schlager
on January 14th.
You were present
while they were discussing
their espionage plans.
You saw Schlager
receive an envelope
containing military information.
You put that envelope
in your purse.
You left about 7:30.
It's not true. It's all a lie.
I advise you to tell the truth,
Miss Kleinhauer.
I do not know
what you are talking about.
I'm talking about a man
you work with called Schlager
the man you both contacted
called Kurt Schneider.
I do not know
any Kurt Schneider.
You have invented him.
There is nobody like him!
Hello, Miss Kleinhauer.
Who is this woman, Schneider?
Hilda Kleinhauer.
She's Schlager's assistant.
On January 14,
did she visit your apartment
- together with Schlager?
- Correct.
(Renard)
You gave Schlager
military information
to take to Germany?
- Correct.
- Did you see her put
those papers in her handbag?
- Correct.
- Thank you. That's all.
Well, as you've seen,
Miss Kleinhauer
I haven't invented
any of this at all.
You still deny any knowledge
of espionage activities?
- I do.
- Then surely you won't object
to our examining your luggage
aboard the Bismarck
just as a matter of formality.
No, I do not object.
Go ahead, examine it.
Then will you be good enough
to write a letter
to the purser instructing him
to deliver your bags to us?
- No, I will not.
- All right.
Then I'll merely have a warrant
issued for their seizure.
- You can do that?
- Oh, naturally.
New York Harbor's
still very much
a part of the United States.
Well, uh, all right. I...
I will give you the note
but you will find nothing there.
I am very sorry, gentlemen,
how am I to know Miss Kleinhauer
really wrote this note?
Pardon me.
You could have found it somewhere.
No, we didn't find it.
Oh, excuse me, please.
I-I didn't know.
All right, Heiser,
show these gentlemen
to Miss Kleinhauer's quarters.
This way, please, gentlemen.
Thank you.
Hello? Give me
the Cafe Nuremberg, quick.
This your briefcase?
Yes.
You still don't know
any Karl Schlager
- or Kurt Schneider?
- No.
Both of them
perfect strangers to you?
Yes. I keep telling you
I don't know any Franz Schlager.
Oh, just a minute.
You said Franz Schlager.
How do you know
his name is Franz?
I, uh, you said it
yourself just now.
No, I said Karl Schlager,
not Franz.
And if I said
the wrong name, so?
No, you said the right name.
It is Franz Schlager.
Well, you've got me
all mixed up.
Well, that was my intention.
Uh, by the way, have you
a permit to take this money
- out of Germany?
- No.
I understand
it's a crime frequently
punishable by death
to smuggle money out of Germany.
I did not smuggle it out.
My government gave me
that money to deliver--
To deliver?
To whom?
I-I forgot.
Please, please,
why don't you let me go?
I have nothing more to say.
I tell you, I'm innocent.
Let me go back to my ship.
What about this?
Somebody put them there
in my bag.
Have you the key
to these code letters?
- No.
- But you can decode them,
- can't you?
- No, no, I can't.
I never saw them before.
Go through the lining.
Look in those perfume bottles.
Phillips, search every one
of those dressers.
You have no right. My German
consul will protect me!
Here's something, Mr. Renard,
I found it in the clock.
(Hilda)
It's not mine. I-I don't know
anything about it.
(Renard)
Perhaps not.
I demand to go back to my ship!
Miss Kleinhauer, I'm afraid
it's gonna be a long time
before you can return
to your ship.
You may not realize it
but you're in a very serious predicament.
The only way you can help
yourself is to help us.
Well...
what do you want me to do?
(Renard)
I want you to decode
these letters immediately.
[door buzzer buzzes]
Dr. Kassell, please.
I'm sorry. You can't see
the doctor now.
It's after office hours,
and he's very tired.
Oh, I believe Dr. Kassell
will see me.
What is your name, please?
Edward Renard.
Federal Bureau of Investigation.
What do you want
to see the doctor about?
Oh, just tell him I'm here.
He'll see me.
Just a second please.
There are two men
to see you, doctor.
They say they are from the
Federal Bureau of Investigation.
Here now?
Did you tell them I was in?
- Yes, doctor, I--
- Oh.
- When I leave, let them in.
- Yes, doctor.
Hello.
Cafe Nuremberg. Otto.
Get him for me at once.
It's very important.
Otto. Listen...
Yes.
Yes, I'll stop by sometime later
and have a look at it. Yes.
He should feel much better
after his medicine, yes.
All right. Goodbye.
Good evening, gentlemen.
- Good evening.
You wish to see me?
Yes. Your nurse told you?
Yes, gentlemen.
What can I do for you?
I just saw your
commission outside, doctor.
You're a reserve officer
in the United States Navy?
Yes, sir, I am.
And one of the most active officers
- of the German-American Bund.
- That's right.
That makes you keep constantly
in close touch with Germany,
doesn't it?
Well, naturally.
I'm very devoted
to my fatherland.
But I'm an American citizen first.
Uh, doctor, I wonder
if you'd give us the liberty
of examining your office?
Unless of course you wish
to insist upon a warrant?
No, no. Not at all.
I have nothing to conceal.
Thank you. All right, Phillips.
Oh, by the way, do you happen
to know Franz Schlager?
No, sir. I do not.
Hilda Kleinhauer?
No, sir.
Oh, uh, do you mind?
- No. Please, go ahead.
- Thank you.
Oh, very interesting.
- Biographies, eh?
- Mm-hm.
Some of the most important men
in America.
Yes, sir.
Finance, mining,
theater, doctors,
statesmen, lawyers
all classified
according to blood and race.
Yes, I see.
Do you find it
at all interesting?
Oh, I do. Especially your own
personal remarks on each case.
They aren't exactly flattering.
Well, naturally
they are not.
Traced back to the third
and fourth generation.
It's all done
to preserve Americanism.
It's a very thorough research,
don't you think?
Oh, yes. Your research
is thorough enough
but your facts
seem to be all wrong.
The story'd fit
Nazi prejudice.
Oh, uh, doctor
you wouldn't exactly
describe this type of research
as the essence
of Americanism, would you?
I would. Precisely.
In fact,
it is as a loyal American
that I am collecting
this information
since I am convinced
that certain subversive elements
must be removed
from our American life
before they totally corrupt
and destroy
our cherished democracy.
Your democracy?
Well, I don't know
how you personally feel
about these things,
Mr. Renard
but surely you
must be aware
of the insidious
international conspiracy
of desperate,
subhuman criminals
greedy for world power.
It is obvious that these
criminals need to be removed
from public life
before they are prepared
to throw
the entire world
into flames.
Careful, doctor,
you might have burned yourself.
Oh.
I'm so sorry.
An accident.
That's quite alright, doctor.
Mr. Renard, you are
wasting your time.
I know absolutely nothing
about any spy plan
nor about those code symbols
on the matchbook there.
My only contact with Schlager
was for delivery
of propaganda information.
To Dr. Paul Joseph Goebbels
head of the German ministry
of propaganda.
Yet this information
was proved to be delivered
to Captain-Lieutenant
Wilhelm Straubel
of the German naval intelligence.
But I'm not concerned
with the mechanics
of how my material
reached Dr. Goebbels.
And you deny
that you know Hilda Kleinhauer
Schlager's assistant.
I never saw her
in all my life.
But you admit
that you saw Schlager?
Under the circumstances
I just told you.
Not as a spy.
And this, uh,
Hilda Kleinhauer.
rather attractive girl.
Reddish hair,
dark eyes...
I'm certain I never saw
the girl you speak of.
I-I don't know
any such person.
(Renard)
Come in, Miss Kleinhauer.
Can you identify
this gentleman?
Yes. Dr. Kassell.
Is he the same man
who gave you
packages of spy information
for delivery to
Captain-Lieutenant
Wilhelm Straubel?
Yes. He is.
It's a lie.
It's not true.
It is true, Dr. Kassell.
I gave you nothing,
I never saw you before.
It is no use, doctor.
They have the codes,
the letters.
Everything about you, too.
Well, what do you say, doctor?
Uh...
Let me see, now.
Oh, yes, yes,
I-I remember her now.
She came to my office once
or twice with Schlager, but
but it was not military
information I gave him
it was merely
propaganda material.
Tell the truth!
It was only propaganda material
I gave Schlager.
No, doctor, I saw it.
You gave Schlager
military information.
You stupid cow.
- How do you dare--
- Sit down, Dr. Kassell.
Alright, Miss Kleinhauer,
thank you very much.
Now, uh, about
this military information
that you gave
Franz Schlager.
I am not a fool,
Mr. Renard.
Merely because
that stupid girl lied to you.
That information concerned
only the enemies of our party
and our fuhrer.
Your fuhrer?
I thought you said
you were a loyal American.
I am.
Sort of a contradiction
in terms, isn't it?
Loyalty to your fuhrer,
loyalty to America?
It may be to you.
You don't understand.
Well, frankly,
doctor, I don't.
[phone rings]
Hello. Yes.
Traced him
to the Hotel Olympic.
The register for the last year
was signed four times.
Twice in December.
No, not alone.
Uh, have photostatic prints
made immediately.
Yes, I'll be there.
Oh, until late tonight.
Uh, Dr. Kassell.
You were once president
of The Friends of New Germany
before it became
the German-American Bund
by order
of the Nazi Government.
Yes, I was.
But that's no violation
of the law.
Oh, certainly not.
I was just inquiring.
By the way, when did your wife
sail for Europe last year?
In December.
And while you were
a bachelor
you lived constantly
at your apartment?
Of course.
My office is adjoining.
You never went
to a hotel?
No.
Yet, on the register
of the Hotel Olympic
your name appears
on four different occasions
while your wife
was away in Europe.
How, how do you know that?
We make it our business
to know
everything there is to know
about a man
before we bring him
in for questioning.
What do you want from me?
I want you to tell me
all you know
about the German spy organization
in this country.
Alright.
I'll tell you what I know.
But remember,
I am no spy.
I only know these people
because they carried
propaganda material for me.
(Renard) In short, Dr. Kassell,
the German-American Bunds
are indirectly connected
through the ministry
of propaganda
with the ministry of war
and the military naval intelligence.
A network
of interchangeable propaganda
and espionage channels.
Well, now it's beginning
to make some sense.
And just how extensive
is this spy network, doctor?
They have spies stationed
in all of the navy yards
in Brooklyn, in Philadelphia,
in Newport News.
There are German agents
in the aeroplane
and munitions factories
at Bristol, Seattle,
Boston, Buffalo.
There's a spy base
in Montreal, Canada.
The chief United States inspector
in one of your factories
turning out
secret aeroplane parts
is a German spy.
I want specific names
and addresses
all the details.
Could I stop
for a few minutes, please?
I'm-I'm very tired.
Oh, certainly.
Perhaps some coffee?
Thank you.
Bring up some coffee
and sandwiches.
Go ahead, doctor.
- Here he is.
- Sit down.
Oh.
Good evening, gentlemen.
Good evening, doctor.
What happened, Karl?
Yes, what happened, doctor?
Nothing serious.
Nothing important.
They merely heard
I was active in the bund
so they asked me a lot
of silly questions.
What about Kleinhauer
and Schneider?
Did they connect you
with them?
How they tried.
But I denied I had
ever seen them before.
You told them
nothing else?
If I had,
would I be here, free?
I resent such insinuations, Hintze.
Karl, you are sure
there is no danger?
Oh, absurd.
There isn't
the slightest danger.
I assure you gentlemen,
none of us
has anything to fear,
none of us.
I hope so, for your sake.
Goodnight, doctor.
And keep in close touch
with us.
Come on, Hans.
I will.
Goodnight, gentlemen.
(Lisa)
Goodnight. And thank you.
Tell me, Karl.
What really happened?
Trying to frighten me
with their insinuations.
But, Karl, how did they happen
to let you go?
- Hintze and Wildebrandt?
- Yes.
- You two are under arrest.
- What does it mean? What for?
Violation of the United States
espionage laws.
- Kassell! He betrayed us.
- Get 'em in the car, come on.
[engine rumbling]
They think they can play
cat and mouse with me.
What if they should manage
to get out somehow?
Don't worry.
I am working very close
with United States government.
Now, they'll keep me informed
of all developments.
Don't worry, Lisa.
I know exactly what I'm doing.
(male narrator)
A federal dragnet
is thrown out immediately
working at top speed
in an effort
to round up
every possible suspect
connected
with the startling Nazi network
it has its agents operating
on a nationwide scale.
Walter Westphal?
- Yes.
- You're under arrest.
Come on.
(male narrator) Nazi agents,
operating as mechanics
machinists, engineers
and technicians
ferreting into vital secrets
of the United States defense.
- Helldorf?
- Yes.
We're from the Federal Bureau
of Investigation.
Come on.
[instrumental music]
Instruct all agents aboard
German ships en route America
extreme caution
until further notice.
Wire Schlager leaving Munich
to report here at once.
Have Gestapo
instruct New York agents
to protect all witnesses
and defendants.
Curious, how many arrests
they have been able to make
after Dr. Kassell
was questioned.
I suggest we have him
come over here immediately.
- What if he'll refuse?
- Let him refuse.
Have Gestapo bring Dr. Kassell
to Germany as soon as possible.
An urgent message
from the general staff, sir.
Thank you.
(male narrator)
March 13, 1938.
Helpless Austria, deprived
of her democratic strength
makes one last futile attempt
at freedom
through democratic plebiscite.
But Nazi Fuhrer Adolf Hitler
does not wait
for certain defeat
at the polls.
Defying a lethargic world,
Nazi troops invade the republic
on the pretext
of maintaining order
and annex Austria
to the German Reich.
(man on radio)
Vienna, Germany.
Authoritative reports
reveal a reign of terror
looting and suicide
in the old, gay city
of the beautiful Danube.
Major Emil Fey, former
vice chancellor, a suicide.
Friedrich Reilinger,
eminent Catholic leader
and daughter, both suicides.
Veteran Neustadter Sturmer,
Dr. Otto Russo
Egon Friedel
Dr. Otto Luhr,
1936 Nobel prize winner
suicide victims of Nazi terror.
Keep tuned to this station
for further news.
Karl, it's, oh,
it's unbelievable.
[indistinct]
So gay and lightheart--
Erika, let's not
worry about all that now.
What I ask you
is much more important to me.
But, Karl,
it will require so much money.
I have sufficient money
for a long time.
And don't forget,
I'm an able physician.
I can make a new home
and a good living anywhere.
No, Karl. You go alone.
[phone rings]
Hello. No.
Dr. Kassell
is not home yet.
Who's calling, please?
Oh, how do you do,
Mr. Renard?
They are released on bail?
Oh, how dreadful.
Very dangerous.
And will you
also tell him
that I advise moving
to a hotel at once?
Well, uh, preferably
to my own hotel
where I can be personally
responsible for his safety.
Yes, I'll tell him,
Mr. Renard.
Thank you very much.
I'll tell him.
Goodbye.
[door opens]
Good evening.
Any news, Lisa?
Karl, where have you
been all day?
- With Renard.
- With Renard? Were you?
Yes, just left him.
Had a long talk with him
a little while ago.
A little while ago?
Lisa, he tells me I'm in
a very serious predicament
and that I must leave town
at once
go away on a trip.
For... for how long?
Oh, indefinitely.
At least until
this investigation blows over.
In any case, I will let you know
wherever I stop
and after a few weeks
I send for you.
Karl, that's not true.
- Oh, Lisa.
- You're lying.
You want to go away
with that woman.
Don't be a fool. You don't
realize how serious this is.
It's that woman
you want to go with
you want to desert me,
you want to leave me alone.
Oh, stop it,
Lisa, please.
[phone rings]
Yes?
Who?
Yes, I'll tell the doctor.
- Yes.
- Who was that?
Karl, listen to me.
Take me along with you.
I know it's dangerous
for you here.
But you can't
leave me alone
- I am not young anymore.
- I am not leaving you.
I tell you, I'll send for you
in two or three weeks.
- Be sensible.
- I won't give you up, Karl.
I won't let that woman
ruin my life
after all these years together.
- Take me with you.
- No.
Don't be a fool.
I am leaving alone.
Who telephoned now?
It was Muller.
Fritz Muller?
His wife again?
Yes, she's very ill.
You must go over
at once.
Oh, it's you, doctor.
Come in.
I'm glad you got
here so quickly.
What happened
to your wife, Muller?
She seemed to be getting
so much better, yesterday.
Well, I don't know, doctor.
Tonight, after dinner,
she started complaining.
- I see.
- I really couldn't tell you
what's the matter with her.
Well, where is
your wife, Muller?
Where is she...
How did you get...
What are you doing here?
Our government was kind enough
to furnish bond for us.
You overlooked the fact,
Dr. Kassell
that American laws
are very generous to prisoners.
Well, I'm very glad
to see you free.
You are?
Well, of course, but...
Why this deception?
Why didn't you
come to my house instead?
We didn't want to disturb you,
Dr. Kassell
as we did once before.
Well,
what do you want from me?
Dr. Kassell, you are going back
to Germany tonight.
To Germany?
What is this?
A trap?
Let me out of here
at once!
What?
Listen.
You know I can't go back.
I-I'll pay you anything,
I have money.
Please.
Please, give me another chance.
I'll do anything you say.
I promise you, I-I'll do
anything you want me to do
I really didn't know
what I was doing.
Informer.
No, no, I will not
go back to Germany.
They'll put me
in a concentration camp.
They'll torture me!
They will, doctor.
Please, I'll give you
everything I have.
I am a rich man.
Take it all.
Please, let me go.
Please. Please.
- Please.
- Go ahead, Wildebrandt.
No! Don't! Don't!
Let's get him
to the boat.
[dramatic music]
He went alone to see this
patient in Greenwich Village?
No, I went with him.
What happened then?
On the way back,
he decided to stop off
and visit a friend
who's leaving on the Bismarck.
- What time was that?
- About one o'clock.
And yet you didn't
notify us until this morning.
I was not worried
until this morning.
Many times, he does not
come home until very late.
Have you any reason
for wanting your husband
to go back to Germany?
I love my husband.
I want him to be
where it is best for him.
Order a coast guard seaplane.
Radio up on
the captain of the Bismarck
to stand by
to surrender Kassell.
I'll be at the airport
in 30 minutes.
Yes?
Captain Richter speaking.
What?
Department of Justice?
Yes. I'll see.
Just a moment, please.
They're askin' for that man.
Tell them that you refuse
to stop the ship
on the high seas
as the weather is bad
and you will endanger the lives
of the passengers.
Hello. New York?
All ready, Mr. Renard.
Thank you.
Mr. Renard! Mr. Renard!
- What is it?
- Your office just called.
The captain of the Bismarck
refuses to surrender your man.
He says it's unsafe to stop
the ship on the high seas.
I see.
Phillips, call
the state department right away.
Have them cable the United
States Consul in Cherbourg
to pick up Kassell
when the Bismarck docks there.
- Right.
- Thank you.
(male narrator) Acting on
orders from the Gestapo
ship's officials refused
to surrender
Dr. Kassell at Cherbourg.
And when the Bismarck
docks in Germany
this time the delegation
to welcome Kassell
consists of
Captain-Lieutenant Straubel
a squad of black-shirted SS men
and a Dr. Krogman
one of the many legal advisers
attached
to the German foreign ministry.
Why am I treated like this?
I haven't done anything.
I-I...
I can explain.
I must be given a hearing.
There's nothing to be
alarmed about, Dr. Kassell.
We do not intend
to harm you.
You don't intend
to harm me?
On the contrary
we'll take
very good care of you.
All we ask
is that you publicly deny
any incriminating statements
you may have made.
Is... is that all?
One more thing.
Dr. Krogman
is leaving on this ship
for New York tomorrow.
'He will have an American
attorney come to Germany'
'to take down
a deposition from you.'
You will charge
the FBI agents
with using coercion
and intimidation
forcing you to sign
a false confession.
I see.
Yes, you are right.
That's what they did.
They tortured me.
Yes, of course.
And you will swear to it.
I swear to everything.
Will I be able to go now?
Not yet.
You will be held
on a technical charge
of entering Germany
without a passport.
Is that correct,
Dr. Krogman?
Yes.
For how long?
A week. Perhaps two.
When you are released, however
it does not mean that you are
free to leave the country.
I-I understand.
So you see, Dr. Kassell?
You have nothing
to worry about
for the present.
I see.
Go ahead, Dr. Kassell.
(Krogman) I demand that you
release this Kleinhauer woman
at once.
You've only recently
arrived from Germany
- haven't you, Dr. Krogman?
- Yes.
Well, just what
is your official status?
My credentials
are available.
I didn't come here
to discuss them.
I demand again
that this woman be released.
Well, you make this demand
in the name
of the German government?
Absolutely.
Your government assumes full
responsibility for this woman?
Yes, as it does
for any German citizen.
And furthermore,
unless she's promptly released
serious difficulties
affecting the relations
of our two countries
can be expected.
Dr. Krogman, I have no authority
to release this woman.
Also, I would like
to remind you
that this is
the United States of America.
We don't know what to do
with ultimatums here.
You'll see someone
in the state department.
Perhaps they will
be able to help you.
I want it to be a matter
of record that I warned you.
Yes, it's a matter
of record.
You may rest assured
that--
Show the gentleman out, please.
My government
will hear of this.
Goodbye,
Dr. Krogman.
Is he crazy?
Doesn't he realize
the German government
practically
admits complicity
by openly defending
Hilda Kleinhauer?
And furthermore,
I warned them
of serious international repercussions
unless she is
immediately released.
Yes.
Yes?
Oh, I beg your pardon.
Yes, Your Excellency.
You, you are absolutely right.
I only thought it...
Yes, your...
I-I mean, no, Your Excellency.
Yes, Your Excellency.
I understand perfectly.
The government does not wish
to be identified with this case.
I will find a lawyer
who has never been identified
with the German government
to defend Hilda Kleinhauer.
Yes, Your Excellency.
[door unlocks]
Thank you.
How do you do,
Miss Kleinhauer?
I'm Krogman.
Dr. Julius Krogman.
Will you please sit down?
I am to obtain an attorney
for you. Now, don't worry.
No jury will convict you
when you tell them
how you were terrorized
into signing a false confession.
- But I--
- No sleep for days, no food.
Promises of release
if you signed.
Every despicable trick of
the most barbarous third degree
was used on you until you had
no strengths left to resist.
- But that is not--
- I know you're afraid to speak.
You needn't be now.
Tell the truth.
That is your defense,
you understand?
And the truth is
that you were forced
into signing a false confession
dictated to you
by the FBI
You will make sure your attorney
understands this.
- Do you think it will work?
- Shh!
Be careful of
your choice of words!
You mean to say,
"Will the truth save you?"
- I say it will.
- Then when will I be released?
Immediately
after the trial.
Why must I stay here
until then?
My bail isn't much.
The German government--
Miss Kleinhauer
please bear this in mind.
The German government has
nothing whatsoever to do
with yours
or anyone else's activity.
Well, goodbye, Miss Kleinhauer.
Thank you very much.
[door closes]
Yes. I see.
What are you going to do?
Answer all questions
and tell the truth.
- Now go on home, dear.
- Oh, please, I want to wait.
You can't wait
in the witness room.
It'll only make me nervous
to have you waiting
around the corridors.
Please go on.
I'll come home
as soon as I can.
Alright.
Goodbye, dear.
Goodbye, Anna.
And don't worry.
[indistinct chatter]
[intense music]
Hello. Coast guard?
Uh, what time did the Donstadt
sail last night?
Oh, thank you.
Put in a call to Washington, the
state department, right away.
(male narrator) The state
department instructs
the United States Ambassador
to Great Britain to make every
effort to take Westphal off
the Donstadt when she
docks at Southampton.
You gentlemen are from
the United States embassy?
Yes. We've come to get
Mr. Westphal.
I'm sorry, but Mr. Westphal
is very ill.
You refuse to comply
with the request
of the United States government
concerning an American citizen?
Not at all,
Mr. Westphal has the right
to do what he wishes,
but he is very ill.
- Could we see him?
- Certainly. This way, please.
Please leave me alone.
I told you I can't go
with you.
I'm very, very sick.
Can't-can't you see?
But you realize the government
asked you to return
only to finish
your testimony.
I'm very, very sick,
don't you understand?
I can't leave the boat.
I'm very sick.
Yes, very sick.
Please go away.
[dramatic music]
Your Honor,
Mr. Foreman
ladies and gentlemen
of the jury
you have been selected to
determine the guilt or innocence
of 18 individuals
accused of violating
the espionage laws
of the United States of America.
four of these eighteen are
in custody
at the present time.
The defendants Kurt Schneider,
twice a deserter
from the United States Army,
Werner Renz
private in
the united states air corps
Hilda Kleinhauer,
former beauty operator
on the steamship Bismarck
and Max Helldorf,
technician employed by
the Zenith Munitions Corporation
of New Jersey.
In simple language,
the indictment means
that this group of defendants
conspired to secure
secret information
about our national defense
and to transmit this information
to the advantage
of a foreign government,
namely Germany.
[crowd clamoring]
Order! Order!
I wish to make it perfectly
clear that this conspiracy
was conceived in
and operated directly by
the present
German government.
[crowd clamoring]
Order!
I shall request the public
to refrain from
any demonstration
of emotion or partiality
in this court of justice.
Proceed.
It has been suggested
that the roles
of these four defendants
are inconsequential.
That is true.
But therein lies
their precise value.
They are persons
of unimportance.
They have been but little cogs
in the vast
and intricate machine
a worldwide spy network
whose organized efficiency
leaps all oceans
and boundaries
a vicious network
whose complex
fabric weaves inevitably
through the naval
intelligence offices
in Bremen and Hamburg
through many German-American
organizations here
through the war and propaganda
ministries in Berlin
through the inner sanctums
of present Germany's
highest officialdom.
(male narrator) Nuremburg,
Germany, September 12
addressing 180,000
Nazi party leaders
Fuhrer Adolf Hitler whips them
into maniacal frenzy
hurling war threats
and ultimatums
against all democracies
and their last Central European
Bulwark, Czechoslovakia.
Resorting to its favorite
device of stirring up
racial prejudices
and national hatreds
fomenting riots and disorder
the Nazi juggernaut sets
the stage for Hitler's invasion
again on the pretext
of restoring order.
The democratic republic
of Czechoslovakia
modeled on the constitution
of the United States
starts its tragic journey
toward oblivion
by falling into the hands
of the new master of Europe,
Adolf Hitler.
A man whose battle cry is
"We Germans
throughout the world."
And the democracies are given
still another illustration
of the supremacy
of organized propaganda
backed by force.
Our power increases
from day to day.
All of Europe is at our mercy
on its knees begging us
not to destroy it.
Austria is part
of greater Germany.
Czechoslovakia is screwed.
Italy is with us,
and safeguards Yugoslavia.
Japan is our ally.
Hungary is practically ours.
Our agents are succeeding
in Romania
Poland, and Lithuania.
France will soon be
isolated from all sides.
But now, since our glorious
victory at Munich
all our efforts
must be directed
at the strongest
remaining democracy
the United States.
Here we must repair
the few petty mistakes
that have recently
been made.
In order to dominate completely
the countries of South America
all excellent markets
for our manufactured goods
all superb sources
of raw materials
we must paralyze the influence
of the United States
by using every instrument
of propaganda at our command
by knowing every military
and naval secret it possesses.
(Kellogg) It has also been
suggested that the information
these defendants
have obtained for Germany
is of small moment.
But as we have endeavored
to bring out
during the course of this trial
we have only scratched
the surface
of the Nazi espionage network.
We cannot calculate
the extent of this spy ring
that has penetrated every nerve
and tissue of this nation.
Together with this propaganda
and religious hatred.
Here on this chart,
we can see the amazing system
of sinister forces at work
in this country.
And realize the dangers
to which our government
is subjected.
If you will examine
its structure
you would be convinced that
these dangers, if they continue
represent the most serious menace
to our national defense.
But there are some who will say
there's nothing to fear.
That we are immune.
That we are separated by
vast oceans from the bacteria
of aggressive dictatorships
and totalitarian states.
But we know and have seen
the mirror of history
in Europe this last year.
The invasions of
Poland, Norway
and Denmark by Nazi Germany,
Russia
and Finland's invasion
by Communist Russia
are still fresh in our mind.
These peaceful nations have
their entire national structure
eaten away by the boring
of the enemies within
who by treachery,
treason, and corruption
pave the way for the ruthless
march of the Nazi iron boot
into these countries.
[dramatic music]
Peace-loving Holland,
Belgium, and Luxembourg
became the next victims
of Nazi aggression.
Trojan horses
and fifth-column bundists
in these countries
threw off their masks
and stabbed these countries
in the back
while the wanton Nazi war
machine attacked in the front.
[music continues]
German parachute troops
dropping like a plague
of locust
from the skies over Holland
were met
by Nazi fifth columnists
in Rotterdam, The Hague,
and Amsterdam
and directed
to vital points of attack.
Important railway stations
and bridges
were blown up by members
of the fifth column
to prevent Holland and Belgium
from sending help
to their
beleaguered soldiers.
[music continues]
God alone only knows
what peace-loving nation
will be next.
Let us take a lesson
from the deadly parallel
of the Nazi fifth-column
activities
abroad and here.
Working insidiously through
its bundists training camps
where spies take cover
and where it diligently trains
its youth to seize power.
But ladies and gentlemen,
America is not simply
one of the remaining democracies.
America is democracy.
Democracy that has the God-given
inspiration of free men
determined to defend forever
the liberty which we have
inherited in our bill of rights
of the constitution
of the United States.
[cheering and applause]
[gavel pounding]
(judge)
'Order!'
And that these defendants had
been convicted of espionage
against the military
establishment's of Germany
I believe their fate would
be more fearful
than that
which here awaits them.
These natives
of a totalitarian state
are to enjoy the mercies
of a democracy
and they may deem themselves
indeed fortunate
that a court of a government
to which they were disloyal
is fully prepared to stand
between them
and the full vengeance
of the law.
In this country
we spread no sawdust
upon the surface
of our prison yards.
Extra, Nazi spies sentenced.
Extra, read all about it!
You doing fine, old Bill?
Okay, Jimmy.
Read all about the
big Nazi spy case.
- Paper, mister?
- Alright, son.
Thanks, mister.
Extra, read all
about the big Nazi spy case!
Extra!
Tired?
Very...
I'm glad it's all over.
Funny thing working on a case
like this for so long
something like spending
a great deal of time
going through a mad house.
You see these Nazis
operating here
and you think of
all those in Germany.
You can't help feeling
somehow that they're...
...well, absolutely insane.
As a matter of fact, you begin
to doubt your own sanity.
True. We see
what's happening in Europe.
We know what they're trying
to do here.
It all seems so unreal.
Fantastic, uh...
Well, like an absurd nightmare.
Absurd...
when you think of
its potential menace
it's terrifying.
I don't think, Renard,
that kind of people
are going to have much luck
in this country.
It's true, we're a careless,
easygoing, optimistic nation.
When our basic liberties
become threatened, we wake up.
- Have some more coffee, gents?
- Yes, please.
Just half a cup, please.
You fellas read in the paper,
they sentenced those Nazi spies?
Yes, we've heard all about it.
The nerve of those Nazis,
sending spies to this country.
Running those bundists camps.
Trying to stir up
the same kind of trouble here
they're making in Europe.
- Hello, Bill.
- How are you, Tom?
I see those Nazis finally got
what was coming to them.
Yeah, we were
just talking about it.
There's one thing they found out
here, though this ain't Europe.
(Tom) That's right, Bill,
and the sooner
we show 'em that,
the better.
Sure, we'll show 'em.
- The voice of the people.
- Thank God for such people.
Yes, thank God.
[instrumental music]