Company .. halt!
Good morning.
─ Good morning.
???? ????
Is someone ill?
For the Captain ma'am.
He can't leave the bridge.
Beautiful soup. Tomato soup.
Mrs Sorenson has no life-jacket.
─ Mrs Sorenson has no life-jacket?
Shhh. No life-jacket.
Did you hear that Mr Payton?
Mrs Sorenson has no life-jacket.
─ Who?
Mrs Sorenson.
My dear, haven't you forgotten
your life-jacket?
Hardly.
Mrs Sorenson, I think you've forgotten
your life-jacket.
Thank you Mr Skold,
but I prefer not to wear it.
Captain's orders Mrs Sorenson.
─ Really?
Mr Hansen.
─ Sir?
Put another lookout on the starboard bow.
─ Yes sir.
Ahoy there! Put another
lookout to starboard.
Jump to it.
I have to report sir, that Mrs Sorensen
refuses to put on her life-jacket.
Make her put it on.
─ I've tried sir, but she won't.
Mr Hansen.
─ Sir?
Ask Mrs Sorensen to see me in my cabin.
─ Yes, sir.
When I saw her come aboard I
knew we were in for trouble.
Did you sir?
Not that I don't like them that way.
Not in peacetime, sir.
And ashore.
Come in Mrs Sorenson.
You wanted to see me Captain?
What is your objection to wearing
a life-jacket?
Apparently the same as yours.
Mrs Sorenson, have you ever
been put in irons?
No.
You will find it much more uncomfortable
than wearing a life-jacket.
You can't put me in irons because
I refuse to wear a life-jacket.
You are mistaken Mrs Sorenson.
I am the captain of this ship and
you are a passenger.
My job is to give orders,
and yours is to obey them.
I am responsible for the safety of every
person in my ship and I am determined ..
Take my passengers safely to the port
for which they have bought their tickets.
Whether you like it or not!
Steward!
You're not really going to
put me in irons?
Sir?
Fetch Mrs Sorenson's life-jacket.
─ Aye aye, sir.
In 48 hours you will be
ashore at Copenhagen.
Where you can wear whatever you like.
But while you are on my ship,
you will obey my orders.
Sir!
You're wanted on the bridge, sir.
A British patrol boat.
We .. wish .. to .. speak .. with .. you.
We wish to speak with you.
As if we weren't late enough already.
They want to take us into a Control Port
and hold us there for days or weeks.
Better than meeting a U-Boat anyway sir.
Oh they say U-Boat Commanders
are very polite.
Yes .. afterwards.
She looks pretty fast, sir.
One round, blank .. load.
They are signaling again, sir.
Heave to immediately.
Let them come and get me.
Fire!
Helvig, ahoy!
Tommy, drop the ladder.
Ladder down.
Move out of the way for us.
Hello chief. Have a good trip?
Captain Andersen? I've got a telegram
for you from your owners.
I'm Lieutenant-Commander Ellis and
this is Lieutenant-Commander Ashton.
I can't say I'm glad to see you,
gentlemen.
We brought you some English
newspapers Captain.
Thank you. My passengers will
find them interesting.
We shall want to see your
ship's papers, Captain.
Alright.
Hello chief.
You refused to heave-to Captain.
Any particular reason?
For the reason that I didn't want to
lose time with your contraband control.
Radio-log sir, radio-cabin seal, sir.
─ Thank you.
What's your cargo Captain?
Iodine and medical supplies.
Crude medical supplies.
─ Yes, crude medical supplies.
My country has had no shipments
since the war.
I can see your point Captain.
─ I wonder if you can.
You see, the unfortunate thing about war
is that neutrals sometime have to suffer.
They may be carrying goods for our
enemies and we have to see that they don't.
It means inconvenience and delay, but it's
better than putting a torpedo into you.
I appreciate that.
Anyway, those are our orders,
and we had to stop you.
What would you have done
in our place, Captain?
Orders are orders.
What would you have done in my place,
Lieutenant-Commander?
Run away.
Cigar?
─ Do you mind if I stick to my pipe?
Not at all. I'll stick to mine.
Ship's manifest.
─ I'll update that.
Yes, here.
Consigned to the order of
the Danish Government.
???? 525 tons, packed in bales.
Yes.
Crude iodine .. 504 tons.
That's a big shipment Captain.
─ The biggest yet.
Uhuh, and very valuable to my country.
Yes, valuable to any country.
???? in bag, 1610 tons.
???? - 268 tons, 28 tons on deck.
Do you know what your
cargo's worth, Captain?
Certainly. 40 million kroner.
Yes, about 2 million pounds sterling.
[ door knocks ]
Yes?
Your turn next. He was simply charming.
─ Good.
You are English by birth Mrs Sorenson?
Yes, my husband is Danish and we lived
for some time in America.
Is your husband still in America?
No, he lives in Denmark.
I live in America.
You cross the Atlantic very frequently?
─ Yes, I do.
Perhaps you have some business that ..
My husband has the custody of our child.
And I am allowed to visit her at
frequent intervals.
I see.
Thank you Mrs Sorenson. Please ask
Miss Karoly to come in now.
Certainly.
You passed Puerto Blanco on the tenth.
Then ???? the twenty-fourth
and New York the sixth.
A roundabout route, Captain?
Owner's orders. Had to pick up Red-Cross
supplies in New York.
It's marked down Fred. Independent manifest.
32 tons, packed in special cases.
Consigned to Germany.
Under the International Red-Cross agreement.
─ Oh yes, quite.
Engineer's logbook, sir. Lieutenant says,
shall he proceed with the search, sir?
Yes please, Tell him "General Examination".
Oh one moment Church.
Captain, as a formality we shall need some
hatches opened. Will you give the orders?
Uhuh.
He's alright.
Thank you Mrs Abo, that is all.
─ Thank you.
Rather cute.
─ What?
Mrs Abo.
How do you think she came to marry
a professor with a Finnish name?
Oh, I can tell you that sir.
She was his only pupil.
Ha!
There's only one passenger left, sir.
─ Ah, Mr Pidgeon.
Surely, surely your name is English,
Mr Pidgeon?
Correct, I was born in the old country.
And your business takes you abroad?
─ Hmm. On and off.
You are a "talent scout" Mr Pidgeon?
When the mood takes me.
What kind of talent do you
scout Mr Pidgeon?
Acts ..
Variety acts.
Oh, then have these Hungarian artists
been engaged by you?
I'm only interested in the big time.
You travel a great deal to the United States?
I bring the acts over.
Not so easy these days.
Per Ardua Ad Astra.
Thank you Mr Pidgeon.
Okay.
Mr Skold, inform the passengers that while
in port they must black out all lights.
Yes sir. Allow me sir.
Commander, do you think we should
stay here long?
Can't say.
You see, I have a brother in London,
and I'm his favorite brother.
In that case, perhaps our search party
will be able to find some contraband.
Oh that would be splendid, sir.
Skipper. You're wanted in the saloon sir.
Do sit down Captain.
─ Thank you.
Well Captain, we've examined the ship's
papers, the passengers and your cargo.
The papers are in order and the officers
are satisfied with your passengers.
But the cargo is contraband.
But I have here an Admiralty list of ships
to be passed through quickly on arrival.
Your ship, Captain, is among them.
It only remains that you satisfy us that
your cargo is for your country alone.
How long will that take?
The Ministry Of Economic Warfare
will give that answer tonight.
So, there will be nothing to stop
you sailing in the morning.
That would be splendid .. steward!
My owners asked me to get in touch with
our agent here. Can you help us?
Going to stretch your legs tonight
Captain?
Go ashore?
Yes, I can manage.
How about dinner afterwards?
─ Very good of you.
There's no duty-boat free.
We'll arrange for a local man to take you.
You'll need a couple of Landing Passes.
Gentlemen.
─ Oh very good, very nice.
You understand Captain Andersen, until you
get your clearance papers in the morning ..
We shall hold you responsible for
the ship and everyone in her.
Perfectly. When will the boat be here?
─ About six.
Four bells.
[ door knocks ]
Come in.
Ready skipper?
Is the motor boat here?
─ Sure, it came half an hour ago.
Then let's go.
─ Oh don't forget the landing-passes.
I thought you had taken them.
─ Me? No ..
They were lying on the desk.
You sure you didn't put them in a drawer?
─ Of course I'm sure.
They can't have flown away.
I saw them lying there, but
I didn't touch them.
You didn't .. but somebody else did.
Anyway, how could we get ashore?
My goodness. I had a boat along
to do a paint-job.
Never mind the ship's boat. Go and see if
the motor-boat is still there.
The motor-boat? My goodness.
Gone!
I though so .. we'll start with
the passengers.
You take the port cabins,
I'll take the starboard.
Yes sir.
Come in.
Hello Captain.
─ I beg your pardon.
Mrs Sorenson?
Mr Pidgeon has flown.
Nowhere on the ship?
─ Nope.
Sure?
─ Yes.
Did you see Mrs Sorenson anywhere?
No.
Mrs Sorenson, and Mr Pidgeon.
Does it make sense to you?
No, during the whole voyage they
never once spoke to each other.
I wonder what she tore out of here?
It's the local paper.
If we had another copy we could tell.
Just a minute.
Enter.
May I borrow your newspaper?
Certainly Captain, but you can
read it here Captain.
Silly!
Now we shall see.
─ Page twelve.
I've got it.
"If you suffer from indigestion,
take Tono's Tonic Powder."
"By Mrs J Wright. I was worn out.
My husband gave me up, my doctor .."
What have you got there?
─ I don't know.
What is it, sir?
Revised timetable of trains to London.
London. I can see the departure for 7:15.
Arrives London Victoria 9:15.
7:15.
I'll stop them catching that train if
I have to swim ashore.
Mrs Sorenson .. and Mr Pidgeon.
Guard ship.
What will happen when we don't
turn up to dinner?
You will turn up, I'm going to
the railway station.
What shall I tell of our action
to the Commander?
Tell him whatever you like.
Mrs Sorenson .. and Mr Pidgeon.
Come on, Mata Hari, we've got exactly
a minute to catch that train.
I know but .. hello?
Hello. Can I speak to Mrs Clayton please?
This is the secretary speaking.
No, Mrs Clayton is not home at the moment.
She's in town, but she's out giving
a first-aid lecture. Who is that, please?
This is her niece Miss Clayton.
When will Mrs Clayton be back?
I think about half past ten Miss Clayton.
Will you tell her I will be in London at
that time. I will have a friend with me.
Very good.
I don't know you, do I?
No. I've only been with Mrs Clayton for
a month.
My name is Lang.
Come on. Yap, yap, yap.
Goodbye.
No. Stay there.
Would you mind shutting that door, sir.
There's a draught.
What's the next stop?
─ London, sir.
Hello Rickman. Back?
No, I'm paddling a canoe up Niagara Falls.
Funny, aren't you. How many ships
in the anchorage?
None. All boarders.
Do you want the Ocean Breeze or
Silver Fox for tomorrow morning?
What, those old tubs? No I want
Saucy Sally at six-thirty sharp.
Broken crankshaft.
─ Hell, that's the third time.
I can do My Girl for the six-thirty.
Well, you have got a bunch
of old crocks, haven't you.
Any more letters or telegrams?
─ Yes, but wait until I've finished.
Oh, it's seven o'clock now.
Why did Horace ever sell his farm
and go to sea?
Never mind, you'll be home by nine,
my good man.
You finished the boarding report
on the Zandam?
Two minutes.
How'd you expect me to read this?
How do you expect me to do
copper-plate with chilblains?
Lieutenant-Commander Ellis?
Straight along the passage, through
the swing-doors, turn right.
Well, find anything?
─ Yes, sir.
A lot of stuff that wasn't manifested.
Cases of machinery?
Yes, sir. Looks like parts of an aeroplane.
─ I thought so.
Ge me M.E.W. on the direct line.
Lieutenant-Commander Ellis, sir.
Hello Mr Skold.
─ May I present our agent.
Oh, we know about him.
─ Hello sonny-boy.
Where's the skipper?
He's staying on board, sir.
He's not doing very well.
Why, what's wrong with him?
He looked alright.
He's awfully ill now. He keeps on
having attacks. It's stomach ache.
And when he gets stomach aches,
he's no good for anything.
He should drink gin.
Waiter, four pink gins.
Can we send out a doctor?
─ No. He hates doctors.
So do I. Only two things worth a
twopenny-damn. Gin, and a good circulation.
Which side do we get out, mummy?
─ I don't know dear.
It's this side mummy.
Victoria. Victoria.
Alright governor.
─ Sorry.
The lady has the tickets.
How dare you go ashore! How dare
you steal the two landing passes!
How dare you go ashore without
landing passes!
Do you know what I could do to you?
For what?
You don't want to be mixed up with
the police do you?
No, do you?
─ No, I don't.
Where's Mr Pidgeon?
─ Mr Pidgeon?
I don't know anything about Mr Pidgeon.
I suppose he came to London to
engage Variety acts?
That's his business.
What a coincidence that you two stole
the same landing passes at the same time.
To use the same motorboat,
to travel on the same train.
You don't have to believe it.
I believe that if I stick with you,
we shall meet Mr Pidgeon again.
Do you?
─ Yes, I do.
Look. I promise I'll be back on the
ship before morning. My word of honor.
To play cards?
10:10. .. 12:05 .. 03:30
So we leave at ten past ten.
─ Or five past twelve.
And if we don't find Mr Pidgeon
by 3:30 we all go to jail.
And no doubt, we shall find him there.
Meanwhile, where you go, I go.
Well, it was worth trying.
Gas-mask cases! Torches! Gas-mask cases!
Don't forget the torches.
Don't forget your torches.
Don't forget your gas-mask cases.
Torches! Gas-mask cases. Here,
a nice torch for the blackout.
A ever-lasting battery and a beam
as strong as a searchlight.
If you buy one of these, you will
never lose your way.
I don't want a torch!
─ But it will guide your way home, sir.
It will guide the young lady
home as well, sir.
Only half-a-dollar, sir.
─ I'll buy a torch.
Thank you lady .. see that beam!
Thank you.
─ Thank you, lady.
What about a nice-looking gas-mask
case Miss?
Handy for putting sandwiches in.
I need another torch, for the gentleman.
─ I don't need a torch.
Everybody needs a torch in the blackout.
Thank you.
Thank you lady.
Shine your torch!
Oh, many times I've stood on my bridge
in the Atlantic on a night like this.
Oh, I beg your pardon!
─ Hey, look where you're going!
Obviously you're better in the middle of
the Atlantic. Now will you shine your torch?
This is Buckingham Palace Road.
─ You really know where we are?
Of course.
─ Amazing.
But I wouldn't be much use in the
middle of the Atlantic.
"Will that gentleman shine his
torch down please."
A police car.
─ Oh.
Coming?
Where are we going?
─ To the bus-stop.
Wait a minute. Are we going by bus?
─ I'm going by bus.
Hyde Park Corner, Ritz Hotel, Bond Street
and Oxford Circus.
Hold tight!
I beg your pardon.
Fares please .. fares please.
Any more fares please .. fares please.
Fare please!
A threepenny and a a penny one please.
Thank you. Any more fares please?
The penny one is for you.
You think you're very clever don't you.
How do expect to get about London
in the blackout without any money?
I can get all the money I need.
And I'll buy you such a dinner as you've
never had in your life.
Big words.
─ Big dinner.
Are you hungry?
As a matter of fact, I'm starving.
Well, let's take a taxi.
Alright. But I'm not paying for it.
Hyde Park Corner ..
Taxi .. yes .. taxi.
Stick to it.
Taxi!
Here's one .. taxi.
Go home crackers.
Taxi!
Here's one .. you see?
Can we give you a lift .. or something?
─ No!
You'd better take a taxi.
Taxi!
Cab! Cab!
It's a Hansome. Cabby ..
Where to?
─ The Three Kings.
The three what?
─ Three Kings.
The Three Vikings.
Oh, the Danish place? Albany Street?
Okay, come on me old boy.
Three Vikings ..
Good evening.
─ Good evening.
No gas-masks?
─ We have no gas-masks.
Two sir?
─ Yes, two.
Haven't you got a table by the wall?
─ I'm so sorry sir. They are all taken.
We should like to talk to the proprietor.
─ Yes, sir.
He's bound to know what is good in
his own restaurant. Isn't he?
Order! Order! I must have order in
my kitchen!
Mr Skold, f you please.
─ What is it?
A customer wishes to speak
to you Mr Skold.
OH what is wrong again?
What is wrong again?
Don't you know by now that I hate
to be disturbed. Tell him to go to hell.
But be polite. Polite!
Stir for two minutes, add cream,
don't stir, serve.
Uncle Erik, you're wanted on
the telephone. It's urgent.
Oh, are you also an idiot? I thought at
least my kitchen was clean of idiots.
Don't you see I have no time.
I must not be disturbed in my kitchen,
and now I am disturbed. Once is enough.
Tell the silly fool to ring tonight after
midnight. But be polite. Very polite.
But it is urgent Uncle Erik.
Oh ..
Uncle Erik .. please!
Good evening.
─ Good evening Mr Skold.
This is Mr Skold, proprietor of
the Three Vikings.
I am Captain Andersen of the Helvig.
This is Mrs Sorenson.
Mrs Sorenson is a passenger on my ship.
Good evening.
─ Good evening.
What a surprise Captain, and what
a pleasure, a very great pleasure.
I hope nothing has happened to the Helvig.
Oh no .. and your brother sends
you his love.
My brother? Now you must tell me
everything please.
What is it? Why don't you take the order?
You must have a drink with me.
Oh, would you like to come and
see my cold tables?
Certainly!
─ Come.
Now you must have some of this,
and some of that. That is wonderful.
By the way, Mr Skold, I came ashore in
such a hurry I have no money.
No money?
So .. you are Captain Andersen in the
ship where my brother is a cook?
Cook?
─ Or is he something else?
Of course he's something else.
─ Ah, but what?
Why, First Officer.
─ Ah, please, excuse.
But the Helvig must be since eight
days in Copenhagen?
But she's not.
─ Where is she, if she's not?
That's a secret, and it's also a secret
that I'm here in London.
Ah, so. It is a secret. Of course,
I don't mention it.
Is it also a secret why my brother did
not come to see me? My favorite brother?
Is it also a secret why he did not wire,
why he did not write?
How could he write, if we only
arrived this afternoon ..
No trouble.
─ Uncle Erik.
Go away! What are you doing in
the restaurant?
So, he could not wire, he could not write
and he could not come.
Why could he not come when a
passenger could come?
Because I am the Captain and I have
forbidden him to come.
And you expect favors of me when you
forbid my brother to come and see me?
Excuse me Mr Skold, I couldn't
help hearing.
I paid the gent's cab fare.
Three bob and a tanner.
Damn your bobs and tanners! There is more
important business here to be discussed.
Well, I couldn't help hearing.
Please Uncle Erik.
Now look here Mr Skold.
You seem to doubt my word.
I do now seem, and I do doubt!
And why should I believe you?
Mr Skold, the gentleman on the
telephone is a tall call.
If he speaks from America, let him.
I should care?
But it is your brother Mr Skold!
Your brother Axel, Mr Skold.
Axel? Why the?
I told you it was urgent Mr Skold.
Where is the phone?
Hello? Hello? Hello Axel?
It's me, Andersen.
Here in London. Yes, he's here.
Oh yes, I like it very much.
Listen, Axel, did you leave
the boat tied up?
Good .. yes I had to follow them.
No, Pidgeon is missing, but I've got her.
She's sitting in the restaurant and she ..
Speak to your brother.
─ Erik, Erik, Erik!
Oh Axel, I am so glad to hear
your voice my boy.
Your Captain? Yes, he is a beautiful man.
From the first moment, I liked him.
The lady asked if the gentleman is going.
What lady?
─ Please.
Thank you.
Bon!
Now. What will you have to follow?
─ We haven't ordered yet.
Not ordered. Not ordered?
???? and tomato sauce.
Which do you suggest?
This,and this and that, are all ready,
but that, that is wonderful.
But then I usually prepare that myself
and I would have to leave you.
Oh pity.
─ We should love to taste it.
Well don't worry, don't worry.
You shall see, in fifteen minutes.
???? ???? ?????
Follow me.
How is Axel the Mate?
He seemed to have dined well.
─ Not so well as us.
He has a clear conscience.
─ No he hasn't.
Why?
He has to cover my absence.
─ I've put you both on the spot.
I like being on the spot. Skol!
─ Skol!
What else do you like?
─ A small ship.
I suppose you've never tried a big ship?
The bigger the ship, the smaller
the adventure.
The smaller the ship, the bigger the
adventure, but you wouldn't understand.
Because you have childish ideas about life.
Because like so many women you live
only for little excitements, like uh ..
Like what?
Well, like going out every night,
somewhere new, somebody new. Right?
You didn't answer my question.
Did you ever try a big ship?
Of course I did.
And did you ever try being married?
That can be quite a big adventure.
─ Ah, why do women always say that?
Marriage ends adventure.
Why do men always say that?
Hmm! .. Skol!
Skol!
Well, in five minutes our first
train is leaving.
Show me.
Commandante Andersen.
─ Yes.
In the Danish Navy.
─ Uhuh. In the Danish Navy.
But you left it. Why?
The Danish Navy sails around the coast
of Denmark and then back again.
I wanted to sail everywhere
a ship can sail.
But you wouldn't understand that.
The "Bjorn Helm" was a big ship?
─ Hmm.
Six times as big as the Helvig.
That's the winder.
Press it again.
[ musical chimes ]
It's fascinating.
That's the song we officers used
to sing when we went ashore.
The last part especially.
Twice?
─ Twice.
????? ???? ?????
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah.
Let me try.
????? ???? ?????
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah.
Now I've got it.
????? ???? ?????
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah. Skol!
Skol!
[ train whistle ]
Close your eyes when you get outside
and count to ten.
The you will be able to see better
in the blackout.
Thank you Mr Skold, you think
of everything.
Oh it is nothing, nothing at all. And
whenever you come the restaurant is yours.
Goodbye.
─ Goodbye.
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah.
8 .. 9 .. 10.
Can you see any better?
─ Just as black as it was.
Blacker.
What are you going to do
until five past twelve?
I've got a lot to do.
─ We've have a lot to do.
We have lot to do.
─ What do we do first?
Have a drink?
─ Good.
And the drinks are on me.
Here's your taxi, sir.
And I'll pay for the taxi.
Where are we now?
─ Chester Square
Is it?
─ Look up.
I've never seen the stars so clear
in a big city.
Don't look so high. See that window?
I spent eight years of my life there.
Is anyone at home? Aunt Kate?
This is my aunt's house.
I think you'll like her.
Aunt Kate!
[ do barking ]
It's the boys. They must be in the kitchen.
Come on boy .. come on.
Come to me, then. It doesn't look as
if your aunt is at home.
She must be upstairs. Aunt Kate!
Aunt Kate!
At least the secretary ought to be here.
Aunt Kate.
Aunt Kate!
Are you sure you have an aunt,
and not an uncle?
Good evening.
Good evening Mrs Sorenson.
─ I'm Miss Clayton.
You've never heard the name Sorenson?
─ Never in my life.
This is my aunt's house. Who are you?
─ My name is Lang.
You're the secretary. Where is Mrs Clayton?
Sergeant Clayton. Somewhere in
England I believe.
Don't let us waste time Mrs Sorenson.
─ I tell you I am not Mrs Sorenson.
And you, I suppose, are not Mr Pidgeon?
Uh, I'm not Mr Pidgeon.
Sloan 2-7-4-1.
─ I want to speak to Mrs Sorenson.
What name please?
─ Tell her it's Mr Pidgeon. It's urgent.
She's in the bathroom sir.
Can she ring you back?
Ring me back? What the devil for?
She was supposed to be here long ago.
Tell her to hurry.
Where should she ring you sir if she asks?
─ She knows.
Where should she meet you, sir?
Hello? Hello, hello.
Have you finished?
─ Who is that?
This is the Army And Navy Club, madam.
So Mr Pidgeon is at the
Army And Navy Club.
The Army And Navy Club?
Then who are you?
My name is Andersen.
Hans Andersen.
And we are the Brothers Grimm.
Are they Police?
─ I wish they were.
No talking!
What are you looking at?
─ The stars.
Get out.
Suppose we don't get out?
Yes. As a matter of fact, we feel quite
comfortable where we are.
Yes! We are just beginning to
like it very much.
Get out and stop talking.
─ Who is going to stop me talking?
We are in a free country where you can
say what we like and do what we like.
We choose to sit here and talk as loud as
we like, and if we want to, we shall sing!
As a matter of fact we do want
to sing, don't we?
Yes, we do.
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah.
???? ???? ???? ????
"You, I suppose, are not Mr Pidgeon?"
"Not Mr Pidgeon. Not Mr Pidgeon.
Not Mr Pidgeon Not Mr Pidgeon!"
"Not Mr Pidgeon."
"Not .. Mr .. Pidgeon ..
Not .. Mr .. Pidgeon."
"Not .. Mr .. Pidgeon.
Not .. Mr .. Pidgeon.
No. He's certainly not Mr Pidgeon.
Conrad Andersen.
???? ????
Looks genuine.
Yes, Herr Van Dyne.
That's more than can be said for,
you isn't it, Mrs Sorenson?
Oh, I was forgetting.
Your name is not Sorenson.
─ And yours is not Van Dyne.
You are not Danish.
─ And you are not English.
We met once before. You remember?
Who can forget those hands,
that face, that voice?
That whole striking appearance.
─ And my powers of imagination.
Don't forget that.
─ I don't.
No-one knew better how to make
prisoners talk.
Then I don't have to warn you.
But I do have to warn you.
No, no, no. It's no good trying
to bluff me, Miss Clayton.
You said that once before in Düsseldorf.
Next day, I crossed the Dutch frontier.
Ah yes, but this time you haven't
got Mr Pidgeon to help you.
You said that before too.
Well, we shall see when we
bring him here.
From the Army And Navy Club.
Oh, I remember.
You said you wanted to know how
I should look ..
.. tied hand and foot, knowing that the
next day I would face a firing squad.
I should still be interested to know.
─ Oh, you think I'm a coward?
Well, would a coward take a dangerous
post like here, in the midst of the enemy?
Anyway, I'm not a fool.
That's why you're here.
While you and Mr Pidgeon were at
liberty I was in constant danger.
I waited a long time too. Five weeks
wasn't it Miss Lang?
Yes, Herr Van Dyne.
Patience is its own reward, as no doubt
you know from your own job.
By the way, what is your job now?
Oh, well. We'll talk later.
I am quite prepared to meet with this
fellow, the captain of the Danish ship.
We know all about the Helvig,
don't we Lieman?
The Helvig? Yes, Herr Van Dyne.
You were traveling on a neutral ship
to a neutral port.
You were reported this morning
to Contraband Control.
We know about it, don't we Lieman.
─ Yes, Herr Van Dyne, this morning.
You and Mr Pidgeon have been traveling
in neutral ships for the past six months.
This time, you sent your information
through the usual channels.
But you saw how you could save
the Admiralty five days.
Just what is that information,
Mrs Sorenson?
It doesn't occur to you that I've
merely come home?
I know you Mrs Sorenson. I know
people of your kind.
You're not a secret agent who works
for money. You like to do it.
It's in your nature to ask for trouble.
Adventure is in your blood.
Now, you have important information
for the Admiralty.
I know their agents never communicate
with their departments personally.
They do it by code.
Therefore such a coded message
must be in your possession.
Well, where is it?
Nothing is in your notebook. Your
lipstick contains nothing but lipstick.
Your cigarette case contains nothing but
cigarette papers and a made cigarette.
Curious to find a woman who makes
her own cigarettes.
I once met a woman who smoked
a clay pipe.
Really? How interesting.
May I ask you to take off your clothes.
Miss Lang will help you,
won't you Miss Lang?
Yes, Herr Van Dyne.
Well, Mrs Sorenson?
Can I have a cigarette?
─ Certainly.
At our last meeting it was a sign of
surrender when you asked for a cigarette.
May I have one of my own?
─ Of course.
You always did prefer your own
cigarettes, didn't you?
I remember at our last meeting ..
Of course! That's why I couldn't
find anything on you.
I should still like a cigarette.
So that's your job M47.
To find out under what neutral names
German vessels sail across the Atlantic.
Well, we know all about that,
don't we Lieman?
Yes Herr Van Dyne.
All marked with the same special
water-mark.
Well, if the Admiralty wants a message,
why shouldn't they have one. Lieman!
Can you find a neutral ship,
preferably American.
And bound for Europe.
─ Yes, Herr Van Dyne.
We have an excellent one here.
American freighter M.S. Mirabelle.
7000 tons.
Oil-burning cargo machinery
from St Elisabeth.
I think I have to go now Herr Van Dyne.
The cinema will be nearly over.
Go ahead.
─ Goodnight.
Goodnight.
Well, we can leave S.S. Lingham.
But we'll make the Admiralty believe she
sailed under the name of the Mirabelle.
What's the point?
─ Don't you understand?
I bet your Miss Lang understands.
You think there will be trouble if an English
warship arrests this American freighter?
But we are not Germans, who shoot first
and ask questions afterwards.
You will see Miss Clayton, the skipper
of the Mirabelle will get tough.
As the Admiralty have definite information
that the Mirabelle is really a German ship.
The English Command will get tough too.
As the Americans cannot bear anybody
to be tougher than themselves ..
Well .. that's how wars start.
[ national anthem ]
Your National Anthem Mrs Sorenson.
Why don't you stand up?
I see the Captain is already on his feet.
I seem to have missed a good deal.
I have no quarrel with any neutral Captain.
As long as he remains neutral.
Since you got mixed up in this affair,
I must treat you as an enemy.
I realize of course. that up until
now I have been treated as a neutral.
But, with your permission or without, I
intend to rejoin my ship before sunrise.
You're an optimist Captain.
─ And this lady is going with me.
We sail at dawn.
─ Tomorrow?
No .. today.
[ train whistle ]
I'm sorry I dragged you into all this.
You did your best to keep me out of it.
I hope Mr Pidgeon's clever,
otherwise we're sunk.
He doesn't look very clever.
Still, perhaps he is.
After all, you don't look very clever either.
Yet you are.
─ How do you mean?
You both escaped from him before,
didn't you?
Oh, you heard that.
─ Most of it.
And what do you think?
─ Hmm. Skol!
Skol!
Sorry I can't do anything about it.
─ Well, I can.
Yes, I know.
─ Know what?
You stiffened your muscles before
you were tied up.
Good! And what happens now when I relax?
You get a little play in the rope.
And if somebody gives a good hard pull
on the rope?
Who?
─ You.
How?
Haven't you got high heels and long legs?
─ Alright I'm doing it.
What are you waiting for?
─ Brother Grimm.
He must be given another chance
to look at us.
Don't worry about him, he won't come down
again. He can see us from where he is.
How?
─ Can you see the lift door?
No.
Well beside it is mirror which connects
to another one upstairs.
The Gestapo had the same thing in the
prison where I met Van Dyne.
You are clever. Do you think he's
looking at us now?
No, you can always see a flash of
light if anyone is looking at us.
I think I can bring him down.
What for?
─ Never mind.
First we move the chairs a little bit ..
─ Which way?
We want to be just opposite the
door and the mirror.
Pull it to the right .. stop!
He's looking.
─ Now he'll come down.
What did I tell you?
Hello Mr Grimm.
─ Don't call me Grimm!
You were introduced to us
as Grimm, Mr Grimm.
Is that all you came down for Mr Grimm?
You know why he came down?
You want me to say it? Why?
Because after we moved the chairs he
could only see you.
I get you.
Before we start.
We let him have one more look through
his periscope.
How did we get into this place?
Through a door. Iron. I think it was locked.
Along a passage, half bare-boards,
half carpet.
Then, into the lift and down here.
─ More detail?
Can't.
─ Why not?
It was pitch-dark. I had to go where
I was pushed.
Smell anything?
─ Cooking.
Hear anything?
─ Only the cinema.
Close at hand?
─ No, rather muffled.
When they played "God Save The King"
it came from over there.
[ music playing ]
Then what about that?
─ It's not the cinema.
It's a shuffle.
That banjo-player is good.
And the singer.
It must be a nightclub.
So, Van Dyne has his office under
a cinema and a nightclub.
He's having his look.
In two minutes we shall be
looking back at him.
Right, he's gone.
Now I relax ..
─ And I use my legs.
Come on!
─ It's not so easy.
Good girl.
I shouldn't hurt you.
─ Go ahead.
What can you see?
Courts.
─ Nothing else?
No .. just courts.
No sign of Brother Grimm.
Put your hands up .. like they were.
Now then.
Do you trust me?
─ Yes.
We shall catch that last train.
─ And warn Mr Pidgeon.
Yes .. and don't forget to talk
if Grimm is looking.
Look out! He's there again.
Talk!
To be or not to be, that is the
question. Whether it is nobler ..
He's gone!
If he suspects anything, we shall
hear the lift coming down.
No. It's alright.
What are you going to do?
Start at the bottom and work up?
No. Get to the top, and work down.
I've got my fingers crossed.
Bye bye.
Hands up!
Patriotic .. Plaster .. Products.
Very clever Mr Van Dyne.
What do you think you're lighting?
A bonfire?
Why can't you ruddy Wardens mind
your own business?
What do you expect me to light my
pipe with? An electric battery?
Why don't you do something to earn your
3 quid week and leave tax-payers alone?
Poking your long noses into
other people's pockets.
That's all the thanks you'll get.
Hey!
─ Good Lord!
Put out those lights!
─ They must be mad.
Go and see if we can get in that door.
Hoy! .. put out those lights!
Get a crowbar .. we'll have to break in.
Hoy!
Here's the crowbar .. now we're
getting somewhere. Give him room.
No, no, no.
Hoy .. just a minute now.
Put out those lights .. Hoy!
Put out those lights!
Hey, put out those lights!
Hoy!
Ooh!
Oh.
Too bad you didn't catch him Harry.
What's this? German?
Nah .. French.
Commander Andersen.
─ That'll catch him alright.
Taxi! Taxi .. Taxi!
Taxi?
─ Who's next?
Not me .. I'm just in for dinner.
I'll keep it hot for you.
─ What's the name of the street?
Hanover Square. The Three Vikings.
Danish Restaurant.
Foreigner ain't he? Blimey, he's in a state.
What's yours John.
[ door knocking ]
Where's Walter?
─ Gone home.
[ door knocking ]
Better see who the silly fool is,
but be polite. Very polite.
Captain Andersen!
Where's Mr Skold?
Mr Skold, get a map of London.
─ Get a what?
Get a map of London.
What are you waiting for? Get
the Captain a map of London.
I need your help. I need all your help.
You remember the lady who was dining
with me? She's in great danger.
Now listen .. there is going to be a fight.
A big fight! If you're all Danes,
you don't want a reason for fighting.
Who do we fight? Come on.
Here is the map.
And now where do we go?
That's what we have to find out.
I've never seen the place from the outside.
Now you all know London.
Where is their a cinema and a nightclub
in the same building?
The "Garden Of Eden".
The "White Negro".
The Mouse Trap.
There must be a least half
a dozen places ..
Quiet please! Quiet! Quiet!
Where is Chester Square?
Here!
Chester Square.
Now .. steering by the stars ..
We navigated North North-East at an
approximate speed of 8 knots.
We held that course for two and
a half minutes.
That would bring us about here.
Well we all know it isn't there.
At the same speed, we proceeded
due East for another two minutes.
We passed under a big arch.
Admiralty Arch!
Immediately afterwards we altered
course North North-West for 4 minutes.
At a reduced speed.
That would bring us here.
Soho!
Right. So. Now to check it,
we take a cross-bearing.
Give me a pencil.
Where's Hanover Square?
Hanover Square.
Somewhere where these two lines cross.
I say the "Garden Of Eden"
or "The Mouse Trap" or "The White Negro."
But how would you know the right one?
─ Because I know the band.
There is a banjo player and a man who
sings. We have to search until we find it.
Do we all go?
No, no, not all of you.
The five biggest will do.
Well line up, line up. But you can't go
to a nightclub looking like you do.
Yes, somebody has to give me a decent
suit. Somebody about my size. Now then.
You, you, you, you .. and you.
Your suit will do for me,
and don't forget - white ties.
Get me the Army And Navy Club.
─ The Army And Navy Club.
Mr Pidgeon?
─ Who wants him?
The lady is in the cab. Won't come in.
Call Mr Pidgeon!
It's about time she turned up.
He's been like a cat on hot bricks.
What it is to be young.
Where is the lady?
─ In the cab, sir.
Goodnight Bob.
─ Goodnight sir.
Army And Navy Club? He's just
this minute left sir.
Where to, sir?
─ Regency Hotel, Little Row.
What the devil happened to you?
I thought we arranged to meet .. Ahh!
You heard the address.
Mr Pidgeon!
Just a brandy please.
We're not staying long.
That's very nice of you, sir.
Your order, sir?
Tell me, you have no banjo-player?
─ No sir.
Are you sure of that?
─ Yes, sir.
We've never had a banjo-payer gentlemen.
No banjo-player.
Perhaps we can send out
for one for you sir?
Oh no, no.
Tell me .. have you a man singing here?
No sir.
─ No man singing here?
Waiter, haven't you a banjo-payer here?
No sir, I don't think so.
No banjo-player.
[ banjo music ]
I like the banjo-player.
Do you know the muffin-man?
Do you know his name?
Yes I know the muffin-man.
He lives down Drury Lane. Hey!
A marvelous banjo-player.
Do you know the muffin-man?
Do you know his name?
Yes, I know the muffin-man,
he lives down Drury Lane. Hey!!!
I can recommend our cellar.
Oh, but of course.
Everything our cellar contains will
be brought up to your table.
Can't be a very big cellar.
Champagne.
─ At once, sir.
What do you think?
Haven't you a man singing here?
─ No sir, only a girl.
Are you sure?
Very sure sir. We have never
had a man singer.
No man singing here.
You're going sir? You have ordered.
We are no longer interested
in your cellar.
The man!
Of course, it could have been a girl.
Well, why don't you bring the champagne?
At once sir. Waiter. Champagne.,
This is our place alright.
She said she smelled cooking.
From the courtyard into the kitchen,
and from the kitchen into here.
And let me in .. into the cloakroom.
Yes, of course, of course. I think we
should get our coats.
Are we going?
─ No, no.
This is one of the men, behind us.
Is he looking?
─ No.
Watch those two, and don't let
them follow me.
My coat.
That isn't my coat.
57 sir. That was your number.
I can't have that. It's not my coat.
─ It's the coat you gave me, sir.
Are you calling me a liar?
Let me see for myself.
I can't do that sir.
What on earth do you mean? Of course
I can look for my own coat.
What the devil do you think you're doing,
you young whippersnapper?
Let the gentleman look for his coat.
Call the manager!
What a carry on!
Don't let them pass Skold.
─ No Captain.
What's going on? I must get
through please.
Ahhhh!
Ahh!
Come on chaps! Come on.
The paper sir.
Give it to him, any time.
Go on!
Where is the lift? Behind this door?
Answer!
Skold!
─ Yes Captain.
Two men.
─ Yes, Captain.
Do you remember that code?
That door.
Hoorah, hoorah, hoorah!
Perhaps the ground floor?
No.
There must be a secret button for
the basement.
But this is the basement.
How does the lift work?
─ Find out!
What can you do, but press every
single button once.
Except you press every single button
twice! Of course, that's it!
You remember my watch, Skold?
Now, which button would you be sure
not to press twice?
I don't know.
─ The Start button!
Miss Lang? .. Miss Lang?
You always wanted to see me with
my back against the wall.
Drop that gun.
I'm not an amateur, Captain Andersen.
My gun points at Mrs Sorenson.
One single movement.
─ One single movement.
Can we bargain?
─ What will you offer?
Freedom.
─ In return?
What guarantee?
─ My word.
Insufficient.
─ I am not like you Van Dyne.
I use my own name.
I don't kill people for the crime
of recognizing me.
What I do is done by every secret agent.
You have spies in your
own country, Captain.
These two .. they use their own names?
Can we bargain?
I'll put away my gun if you'll do the same.
Mrs Sorenson, would you bring in
my coat and hat, please.
The Police are here. I've got your coat.
Well, what are you waiting for? Go on.
I give you my word .. that as
soon as we step out of the lift ..
You are free to go where you like.
I hope we shall never meet again.
I hope so for your sake Captain.
I've no intention of visiting Germany.
You timed that very nicely Captain.
The Police are here.
Meet me at Victoria at 3:30.
Yes Captain. I locked them in.
Are you alright?
We haven't got much time.
─ And I've got to go to the Admiralty.
I know. We'll meet you at Victoria.
The window. Over there.
Careful. One step at a time.
Aren't you running with them?
─ No. I'll show you the way first.
Stop!
The lift is coming. Stay where you are.
Don't move.
Who's there?
─ Hello Van Dyne.
You didn't escape?
─ You innocent!
Well, your Police didn't get me anyway.
No wonder you hoped we'd
never meet again.
Van Dyne?
He always said he was tough.
Well .. thank you for everything Erik.
And goodbye.
Goodbye.
Thank you all.
Luke .. Henry .. Bjorn .. Vorsbald .. Arnold.
Thank you Arnold .. and goodbye.
Goodbye.
Now she's missed the train.
Pidgeon. You don't know that girl at all.
Done it?
Yes.
Here are your papers Captain,
and here's your clearance paper.
You can heave up anchor
whenever you like.
Skold! Heave up!
You should hoist this code signal to
avoid being stopped again.
Well, Captain, next time I hope you make
up for the dinner you missed.
Thank you Lieutenant-Commander Ashton
and goodbye.
Oh, and uh .. here's a little something
for your stomach-ache.
Mrs Sorenson .. the Captain wants
to see you in his cabin.
Thank you.
That girl certainly likes trouble.
Come in Mrs Sorenson.
You wanted to see me Captain?
Sit down Mrs Sorenson.
Mrs Sorenson, because of you ..
The whole Control Port thinks I'm an
old woman suffering from indigestion.
It's lucky that nobody knew what
nonsense I was up to.
You think our Police and Intelligence
departments are pretty dumb, don't you?
Open your stomach-powder.
And nobody knew.
[ watch chimes ]
I have had enough trouble because of you.
And I feel I shall have more.
Drop that life-jacket ..
Hoorah .. hoorah .. hoorah.
Subs for KG
by "Targa".