Today's review will be the final
operation of training period two.
Instructions for period three
will be issued tomorrow.
Study them. Make your plans.
Stand by for flight quarters.
- First Division ready for flight.
- Second Division ready for flight.
You boys are getting so efficient
you scare me. Come on, they're waiting.
- What course did you get to steer on?
- Course 273 for 15 minutes.
- That's about what I got.
- From this point, we can circle...
Hey. Sit down. I can't see the board.
Bombing pilots, attention.
Rendezvous over the carrier
at 2000 feet.
Gold braid's on the field ashore.
Fly past in mass formation.
Then make a dive-bombing attack.
And don't forget to take your shore legs.
Honolulu. Here we come!
All right. All right. Relax and stand by.
You bunch of ground lovers.
- Taking care of my gear. Tom?
- We'll move it ashore.
- Thanks. - Not at all. I'll
be glad to get rid of you.
- Oh. Have you got a cigarette?
- Yeah.
- Say. What is this? Gold?
- Sure. We've got a friend at Fort Knox.
- You guys didn't buy these on Navy pay.
- We found them under a rock.
You ought to wear specs to go
with them. Or carry a cane.
These certainly make an impression.
Only thing I own that'd make
me welcome in a pawnshop.
They sent them
because Joe rumbled...
- ...with a governor's wife in Cleveland.
- That probably had a lot to do with it.
With the boys running National Air Races.
Thought we'd do better stunts.
Things will be awful tough on Joe
if black cats sprout wings.
National Air Races, five times a day
scraping noses on the ground.
It was worth 18 karats.
Oh. Yeah. But I got the
best deal out of Cleveland.
- 5 feet 2, blue eyes.
- There he goes again.
- Wait till he's washed a million didies.
- And walked with junior's gas pains.
He'll wish he'd taken a cigarette case.
Swede. How'd you get glamor dust in
your eyes? Pilot's a fool to take a wife.
Hazel's broad-minded. She's letting
me off once a week after marriage.
Well. That's better than
being in a penitentiary.
I wish you transferred to San Diego with
us instead of here. After the honeymoon.
Yeah. It's a crime to break
up the three top hats.
Did a lot of loops together
here and there.
Boy. You're gonna miss those times.
So are we.
I'll have a bride to take care of.
You guys will be playing tag with cadets.
I'll play tag-
Pilots. Man your planes.
Stand by to start engines.
Stand clear of Propellers.
She's sweet as sugar, commander.
Doctor. There's something
sort of morbid about our jobs.
Here we sit, day after day.
Like buzzards on a rail fence.
Yeah. I guess you're right. Lucky.
We sort of symbolize the uncertainty
of life for those pilots.
- No wonder they don't love us.
- Oh. I don't mind them. Sir. It's my wife.
She says I have to stop
smelling of iodoform.
Did you ever have complaints on it?
Did I? Only about eight years.
Harvard. Hopkins. Cambridge.
The girls all used to call me
“The Iodoform Kid.“
- Generally. They called me. "Stinky.“"
- How did you manage to get rid of it?
I didn't. They just got used to it.
Killed a lot of romances for me. Lucky.
I should have been smart like you.
Lieutenant, stayed single.
Especially if I'd known
I was coming to Honolulu.
Why. That's fine talk
when you're a new bridegroom.
Three weeks and I got marriage
up to here.
Yeah?
Three more and you'll have it
up to here.
Those planes do something to you.
Don't they?
Almost as good as the Army.
Look at that formation.
Bombing six. Stand by to peel off.
- It's Swede.
- Blackout again.
- You got a cigarette?
- Sure.
I can't move. I can't feel anything.
How did I get"?
Here.
That's good.
What happened, chum?
Did you misjudge your altitude?
It was a dive.
I couldn't pull up.
Blacked out.
Why don't you doctors
do something about that.
Yeah. Why don't we. Here.
Here's the pressure
on the spine right here.
That can only be relieved
by an immediate operation.
Well. He's pretty weak
from shock and loss of blood.
There's a chance if we wait for him
to regain strength.
Wait? Of course. It's your responsibility.
But did a case ever improve by waiting?
He'll never regain consciousness unless
we go in now. I wish I wasn't so certain.
- Who's caring for Larson?
- Commander Martin. Lieutenant Lee.
- You saw him. He's still alive?
- He was. Yes. Sir.
I'm Larson's squadron commander.
How is he?
A concussion. Possibly skull fracture.
Also. The x-rays showed a dislocated
vertebra pressing on the spinal cord here.
It's a problem of whether
to operate now or wait.
I don't wanna be insistent.
But we're wasting valuable time.
- What'll you do for him?
- Does he have family in Honolulu?
- No.
- We're his friends.
We haven't time to worry about that.
Allison's just published a complete
record of over 300 cases of cord injury.
Each single case that recovered
was operated at once.
Every minute the pressure was unrelieved
lessened the chances of recovery.
- What more can I say?
- Perhaps you're right. Come along.
Sponge. Sponge.
Scalpel.
Retractor.
Breathing has stopped.
Pulse is getting very weak.
- Sticky. Isn't it?
- Yeah.
That much injury.
There never was a chance.
No. None whatever.
I'm sorry. But your friend
just died on the table.
Accident cases are always uncertain.
You can never be quite sure of
the extent of shock or internal injuries.
Well. I'm sorry.
You were certain enough a while ago.
Maybe it would have been better to wait.
As the commander said.
No. It wouldn't have made
any difference.
His spinal cord was
almost completely severed.
He said he lost consciousness
pulling out of the dive.
We think he lost it in there.
Everything was done
that could have been done.
I appreciate your feelings. But not your
criticism. It has no sound medical basis.
Are you an example
of sound medical basis?
I sent Hazel a cable and a letter.
She'll be going through
the ringer for a while.
Do you think we ought to see her?
No. It would just get her
all stirred up again.
- Linda!
- Doug.
Pal! What are you doing here
in Honolulu?
Of all the nice people.
How nice to see you.
- It's good to see you too.
- Gosh. You look wonderful.
- Thanks.
- Listen...
Come over here.
I want to talk to you.
How many times have I told you
to stop following me?
Who said I was following you around?
I'm with friends and got bored
and went for a walk.
Of course. I was hoping I might run...
Okay. I'm following you around.
But in a very refined way.
Darling. Why do you waste your time
on me? You're much too nice for me.
- Am I?
- Sure. You are.
I've told you, as far as I'm concerned.
A woman is like an elephant.
I like to look at them.
But I don't want to own one. Come on.
- Hey. Peter. A table for two.
- Over there.
Now. Two of those tall green horrors
of yours.
That will kill us or cure us.
You're a double-dyed. No-good.
Cold-hearted wretch. Douglas.
Somehow. I find you very entertaining.
What? Oh. Thanks.
Well. How is good old Jack
back there in Washington?
His name is Charlie.
And he lives in Baltimore.
Yeah. Old Charlie. That's what I said.
Well. How is he? Swell guy.
I always used to get so jealous of him.
Shall I phone and tell him I've caught the
mumps or something and stay a while?
Yeah. Sure. Do that.
Did you hear what I said?
I'm offering to stay another week.
What? Oh. Another week.
Why. Darling. That will be wonderful.
I hope you can make it.
Look. Will you excuse me just a moment?
I must talk to these fellas.
Why do I keep tossing myself at you?
Why am I such a chump?
Darling. You're not a chump.
I'll be right back.
Say. Could I buy you fellas a drink?
No. Thanks.
I just... Oh, thanks, I'll have it here.
I just wanted to tell you I'm sorry
for sounding off that way this morning.
I guess we're all wound up
a bit too tight.
Yeah.
You know. This blackout in dive-bombing
is a very interesting medical subject.
I just read a report on it.
Seems those German Stuka pilots
have been hit hard.
You find a way to make
pullouts easier?
Sure. Cut down your diving speed with
flaps and just hang up there in the air.
Then you're a pushover
for antiaircraft fire.
Yeah. It's tough. All right.
But I still think with proper research.
We'll lick those problems.
It's a cinch. The new German bombers
are coming in at about 38,000 feet.
All RAF fighters have to do is top
that by a few thousand feet to attack.
Trouble is. When you're that high.
You're unconscious.
Say. That brings up
another interesting problem.
Dr. Collins has new work on high-altitude
sickness. What's it doing to your outfit?
Three men in the sickbay.
And one funeral.
We don't know whether that last one
was high-altitude sickness...
blackout or just too much
smart surgery.
It must be pretty uncomfortable
up at 30.000 feet. Isn't it?
Not at all. Doc. It's great sport.
Freeze. Get nutty from no oxygen.
Crash. Break your neck.
You ought to try it some time.
Thanks. Well, just thought we might
learn something from each other.
I've learned one thing from you.
If you pill rollers flew more.
You might find how to help.
- I agree with you.
- How many hops you made this week?
Me? None. I'm not a flight surgeon.
Just a routine doctor.
Then keep your amateur flying talk
to yourself. Doc...
till you get your feet off the ground.
Pilots like Swede die because
so-called experts can't keep them alive.
- You don't even fly. And still you got...
- Wait a minute. Listen. I'm on your side.
I agree. Medical science is far too much
in the dark about these things.
Then give the flight surgeons a hand.
Maybe all they need is a genius like you.
Wouldn't it be funny
if that's what they did need?
It'd be more than funny.
It'd be a first-class, full-grown miracle.
Give me a check.
Remember me?
Linda. The girl you met out there.
I'm sorry for staying away so long.
I didn't mean to.
We got on some important subjects.
So I surmised. I also surmise I'm not
one of them. As far as you're concerned.
- Don't be mad.
- Oh. I'm not mad.
I don't mind anything sweet.
That's my chief attraction.
- I know.
- We'll have a date if you can remember.
- Fine.
- And I decided not to stay for a while.
Good night.
Too much sugar in the bloodstream.
Torpedo Squadron 6 from tower.
Wind northwest. Take off when ready.
Thirty years ago. The Navy had
one airplane and two pilots.
Only 20 years ago. A Naval aviator
was the first man to fly the Atlantic.
In those few years. The men who learned
to fly here really built Naval aviation.
And now you're here
to learn to fly and to fight...
become a part of that heritage.
Soon you'll be looking back
and realizing...
that each of you has shared
in making history as it is made today.
All right. March to ground school.
Attention. Left face.
Forward. March.
I know you're trying. Everybody's trying.
In fact. The Navy is famous for trying.
But if small planes make you dizzy.
You'd better go back to Philadelphia.
We won't order another transfer
to teach you to fly.
- Now. You think it over.
- Yes. Sir.
- He's in a bad mood this morning.
- He's in a very good mood for him.
- That's all.
- Yes. Sir.
Any of you guys can't find a room.
I'll share my doghouse with you.
- You're next. Sir.
- Thanks.
- You better stand away from that door.
- Why. Sir?
I don't want you to get hurt
when I get thrown through it.
- Morning. Sir.
- Morning.
Lieutenant Lee, reporting
for flight-surgeon instruction.
- Welcome to San Diego. Doctor.
- Thank you. Sir.
- Bachelor, eh?
- Oh, yes, sir.
Good. Married officers always want
to go home for lunch.
- You did Naval Air Station. Pearl Harbor.
- Right. Sir. Pretty much a wasted year.
But now I've got some ideas for research
on blackout and high-altitude sickness.
Ideas for research are good
to have around.
We've even got a couple here
ourselves. Lieutenant.
Oh. Well. That's very gratifying. Sir.
- Analysis of student rejections.
- Thanks. I'll read it later.
Oh. Lieutenant Commander Rogers.
In charge of research...
Lieutenant Lee.
Student flight surgeon.
- How do you do, sir?
- Hello.
Lee tells me he's got ideas for research
along your line.
- Look after him. Will you?
- Right. Sir.
Come along.
What's your school?
The diploma mill of Hoosier State?
No. Harvard. Hopkins. Cambridge.
- I can read and write.
- Very impressive.
How'd you offer the Navy so much
for so little in return?
- I'm just naturally generous.
- Not to mention your devastating wit.
Now I'd appreciate it
if you'd answer my question.
I joined the Navy because it offered
an active medical life.
Then I got interested
in aviation medicine.
I applied for the flight surgeon's course.
And here I am.
- I trust that meets your approval. Sir?
- Temporarily. It does.
Go to bachelor quarters
and report at 8 a.m. tomorrow.
- When do I start flying?
- Just leave that to us.
- We'll see you get lots of nice
little rides. - Well. Thanks.
And don't think I don't appreciate
the one I've just been having.
Put her down and keep her down.
Hey. What do you think you're flying.
A kangaroo?
That's tough luck. You missed them.
Now. Put her down.
- What kind of a landing do you call that?
- I'm sorry. Sir. I got confused.
Every time I take you doctors upstairs.
You pat me in the face with a spade.
What have you got against me?
Nothing. The ground's closer
than I thought, that's all.
Slim. You'd never make a flier
in a thousand years.
Doctors are Dodo's by nature.
All of them.
- One thing I want to thank you for.
- What. Sir?
You're the last grasshopper
in this plague of surgeons.
It's an even break to live longer.
- That's all.
- Yes. Sir.
-Hello.
Sorry. But here's another grasshopper.
Well. Well. What have I done
to deserve this honor?
You took the words
right out of my mouth.
Tired of Honolulu?
Run out of women?
No. No. Things just got a little dull
after you left.
Well. When do I start flying?
I can't imagine a nicer job than teaching
you myself. But I'm too busy.
That's a tough break for me.
We'll try to find an instructor
worthy of your talents.
Hey. Tim.
- How are you. Lieutenant?
- I was all right until now.
Tim. The doctor here wants a pair
of wings so he can visit his ex-patients.
See if you can jam his head
into a cockpit.
Well. I'd be delighted.
Get your flight equipment on
and report to plane 17.
- Don't forget your parachute.
- Thank you. Gentlemen.
I know I can expect the very best
of instruction at your hands.
This is a profanity strainer.
I talk. But you can't talk back.
Very clever.
No home should be without one.
All right. Come on. Get aboard.
You're all set?
All right. You take it.
Fly straight ahead.
Keep your nose on the horizon.
Wings level.
All right. Don't pay any attention to me.
I'm just talking through this thing
for practice.
I said. Handle the controls gently.
Dr. Lee.
A Harvard man should know
how to be gentle.
I've checked a lot of students
in my time. But you're about the worst.
If we weren't officers and gentlemen.
I'd say you stink.
Now. To make a quick recovery.
Put that stick forward. Now. Try it again.
Anytime.
Hey. What's the idea?
Flip her over.
Let go of the stick!
Are you trying to fly
or combine suicide with murder?
Maybe that wouldn't be
such a bad idea.
You told me to put the stick forward.
So I did.
Sure. Right through the instrument board.
Don't use your surgical touch on me.
I wanna collect my pension.
Don't worry. You'll be a burden
on the taxpayers for many years.
You're no better at flying than you are
with a knife.
I'll give you one more chance.
Monday morning.
You flunk that one.
And you're washed-out.
Hey. What's the rush?
You got something lined up in town?
No. It's either get off the station
or get a general court-martial.
General court? What for?
For punching that Joe Blake on the nose.
So long. See you later.
Why don't you learn how to drive!
Why do you drive in your sleep?
You came around with your
eyes shut.
Yeah. Well. You saw me coming.
Why didn't you stop?
You got insurance on that fire truck?
No. They don't write it against
drivers like you.
It'll cost you about 50 bucks
to fix my car.
Fifty bucks? You crazy? You can buy
two of those crates for that.
Well. Then maybe you'd rather
I take it out of your hide.
Yeah. Why don't you try that.
Go get him. Boy.
Sorry. I meant that last one for
somebody else. How are you doing?
All right.
- Say. You throw a mean punch there.
- You too. Where'd you learn that right?
At Yale. I was captain of
the boxing team last year.
Yale? Well. That explains everything.
I'm from Harvard. Put her there.
All right. Take her out alone.
Okay.
Sorry if I made good
and disappointed you.
It's a blow. All right.
Commander, there's just one more
thing I'd like to ask you.
- Yeah?
- Why do you dislike me so much?
Because you're a grandstand player.
And a phony on top of it.
If Swede Larson's death makes you
say that. You're being childish.
His number was up before we got him
to the hospital.
I'm not responsible for his death
and you know it.
- Maybe so.
- Then why don't you quit riding me.
Our jobs are tough enough as it is.
I'll stay out of your way.
And you stay out of mine.
Now, get going.
Hit your left rudder.
Not your right, your left.
You're losing altitude fast.
You're gonna crash.
All right. Come on out.
You died a beautiful death.
This. Gentlemen. Perfectly sums up
today's discussion of blind flying.
This pilot crashed because
he trusted his senses.
His semicircular ear canals
lead him to believe. In the darkness...
he was turning left when he was
turning right.
Never trust your senses.
Trust your instrument board.
Did my demonstration bore you.
Lieutenant Lee?
Oh. Not at all. Sir.
It brought up pleasant memories.
I studied the semicircular canals
in second-year medicine.
Did you. Now?
You also learned all about blind flying
at Harvard. Hopkins and Cambridge.
Oh. Yes. I did quite a bit there. Sir.
In a hopped-up jalopy. Of course.
You must've been the pride and joy
of your professors.
You have no idea how they adored me.
Keep that if you like it.
Dr. Lee and all of you gentlemen.
A flight surgeon has been described...
as a combination of Dutch uncle
and father confessor.
Because he's more
than the pilot's physician...
he's a judge of their fitness to go on
with the work they've chosen.
For this task.
He must be conscientious...
and above all. Humble.
Or he has no business being here.
Tomorrow. We'll take up the effect of
anoxia on the electrocardiogram.
Class dismissed.
Boy. You sure got guts talking back
to him like that.
Surly character, isn't he?
I bet a blood sample would show gall.
Bile. With a good dash of sulfuric acid.
Here's the one I'm working on now.
- See that strong bulkhead?
- Yeah.
What are the forces that pull
on a diving pilot when he blacks out?
Between 5 and 10 G.
Between five and 10 times
as strong as the pull of gravity.
- Will it be more with faster ships?
- Not much.
If we lick blackout in our present planes.
The answer will be good along time.
I've gone over these chamber
equipment lists. They seem okay to me.
Good evening. Commander.
Who threw that knife?
I did. Came back pretty fast.
Though. Didn't it?
If he spent less energy being bitter
and more on flying. We might get action.
Maybe he has a right to be bitter.
He wrecked his heart using himself
as a guinea pig on high-altitude flights.
Now he can't fly anymore and he's stuck
at a laboratory desk day and night.
Rogers? Used himself as a guinea pig?
- That's right.
He's also the man who doped out
vitamin A for night blindness...
optically correct goggles...
and shoulder safety belts
to stop crash injuries.
As a flight surgeon, he's tops.
Wow. I had no idea.
No. I didn't think you had.
Yes. Come in.
Good evening.
I saw your lights.
So I thought I'd stop by.
What can I do for you. Lieutenant?
Work seems to be piling up on you here.
I was wondering if I can help you with it.
- You might make those blood counts.
- Sure.
These are mixed.
You know. It's...
strange how wrong you can be
about things and people.
I suppose that's because everything's
so confused in the world these days.
You need a jolt to bring you
to your senses.
When you stop to contemplate
some of...
the things you've said and done.
It makes you feel like an idiot.
But I guess it all comes out
in the wash.
It certainly feels good
to be back in a lab.
Cigarette. Doctor?
Thanks. Doctor.
- I was just thinking of another odd thing.
- What's odd?
Of all the tests used for flying aptitude.
No one thought of trying the Rorschach.
What do you know about it?
Well. Just enough to suspect
it might be valuable.
- Don't you agree?
- I agree that we ought to try it.
- We?
- You and I.
You do all the hard work, and I'll take
all the glory. If any. That suit you?
Sure. Any way you want it.
Doctor. I'm disappointed
in my judgment.
I'm beginning to like you.
Doctor. I'm just suffering
a similar disillusionment.
I'm beginning to suspect you're almost
human yourself.
Douglas Lee.
William Lester Keel.
Good luck to all of you.
The commandant's aide will give you
your orders.
Gregory? Here you are. Slim.
Company commanders. Take charge.
Dismissed.
What did you draw?
Aircraft carrier Saratoga. Pearl Harbor.
I go to Norfolk for assignment.
Well. Soft shoulders and happy landings.
- You too. Norfolk?
- Yeah.
Say. I know a cute redhead there
if you get lonesome.
Well. I'm lonesome now.
Is she big or small?
Well. She's sort of... She's...
Oh. What's the difference?
She's cute anyway.
You'll have to give me her address.
What was your luck?
- Honolulu. The Saratoga.
- Not bad.
Not bad at all. But it's along way
from my real interest, research.
That's life. Soon as a man gets
warmed up for research...
he's yanked off for duty.
Never seen it fail.
Yeah. I guess so. Discouraging. Though.
Guess it's one of those things.
- How'd you like to stay as my assistant?
- I'd like to stand on my head.
I asked for you and Washington
okayed it. This just came.
I'm gonna work you half to death.
Research will be in addition to your other
duties: examining cadets and pilots.
You'll wish you'd gone to Waikiki.
- Never mind that. What's step A?
- Our old friend blackout.
- Doctor. I don't know how to thank you.
- I can't hear a word you're saying.
Well. I'll be right with you.
- Here you are.
- Thank you.
- Would you like something to eat?
- No. Thanks.
Would you like a drink?
Pardon me.
Sorry.
- There you are. Mrs. Fisher.
- Thank you. You're so sweet to me.
Don't mention it.
So you're from Baltimore?
- Where's Mr. Fisher? Is he in Baltimore?
- I just lost him.
- I'm sorry.
- I just lost him in Reno.
- I suffered no pain.
- That's different, isn't it?
- It is indeed. Quite different.
- You here all alone?
All alone. Commander.
Until I leave for Honolulu.
- You have friends there?
- Yes. Some very nice friends.
Tell me. Don't you ever get lonesome
traveling alone like this?
Often.
What are you doing for dinner?
Maybe you'd like to have dinner with me.
- That might be arranged.
- Fine. Where would you like to eat?
Why. I don't know. My hotel is as good
as any place. It's quite convenient.
- Swell, Mrs. Fisher.
- I think you can call me Linda.
- Thanks. I'm Joe.
- Hello. Joe.
Hi. Linda.
- How about another drink?
- I'd love it.
I'll be back in a minute. Linda.
- Pardon me.
- Oh. Sorry.
- Hello. Bill.
- Hello. Doug.
- Hello. Dr. Lee.
- Hello. Mrs. Silvers.
- Nice of you to drop in.
- Thank you.
- May I introduce you around?
- No. I think I know almost everyone.
- Circulate. Have fun.
- Thanks. I'll put my hat over here.
- Hello. Tim.
- Why. Doug. How are you?
- Hello. You beast.
- Sugar! No kicking. Now.
Not yet. You know. It's strange.
When I woke up this morning...
Hurry knew something nice would
happen today.
- Well. So did l. And this must be it.
- Shake.
- Aren't you going to kiss me?
- Oh. Yes. Darling. How are you?
- What are you doing here?
- I'm stationed here. How about you?
You didn't answer my letters.
I was going to Honolulu to see you.
Darling. I'm divorced.
Charlie now belongs to the ages.
Isn't that pleasant?
- Oh. That's wonderful.
- Come on. Let's sit down.
- Oh, Dr. Lee, this is Commander...
- Blake.
- We know each other.
Sure. We're old friends.
Then give my precious a drink.
The commander and I were going...
to dine together tonight.
And you must come with us.
Doug and I are old friends too.
But very old friends.
I helped to cheer him up in Honolulu.
- You certainly did.
- You're such a beast. But so sweet.
And here I go throwing myself
at you again.
Come on. Let's get out of here.
Come on. Commander...
Blake. No. You two run along.
I remembered I have watch tonight.
How unpleasant.
Well. I'll go powder my nose...
tell our hostess a customary lie and be
right back. Meet you in the hall, Doug.
Why am I such a chump
where you're concerned?
If you had an engagement with the lady.
Don't let me stand in your way.
Too bad there are no women on
the selection board.
You'd be an admiral inside of a year.
All right. Come on with the box.
She's got recording instruments
and a movie camera...
to photograph your faces while you're
unconscious. Just turn the switch.
What? No bathtub? No hostess?
No. You'll have to furnish
your own hostess.
From what I hear.
You're the guy who can do it.
Oh. You have. Eh?
Well. Every knock's a boost, you know.
I understand I'm flying
for you gentlemen.
Nice way to spend my time.
I haven't had much to do.
Just training the cadets, flying at night
and... ls Casanova in on this?
- Dr. Lee will act as medical observer.
- You gonna be the pilot?
You can't feel worse about it than I do.
If that's so. Why not give the job
to someone else?
My group was ordered
to send a pilot for a test.
In a good outfit, the skipper does it.
What are the orders?
Service dives to terminal velocity.
Nine-G pullouts.
On the first one.
Tense your muscles from head to toe...
pull your bellies in hard,
yell as loud as you can.
We want to see if that slows
or stops blackouts.
- All right. You ready?
- Yeah.
All right. Men. Pull her out.
Now we're at 15.000 feet
and leveling off.
Here's the dive.
Twelve thousand.
Nine thousand.
Five thousand.
Now we're pulling out.
Still yelling.
Here's the blackout.
Well. There you are.
The yelling didn't help at all.
- Your blackout was slower.
- Well. What does that prove?
I think we're on the right track.
But we overlooked something.
Yeah. A way to stop blackouts.
Might as well run a Mickey Mouse
as that stuff.
Look. I want to tell you something
about that dive.
When we were pulling out of it.
I was bending over.
My camera was stuck
and I was trying to fix it.
- I didn't black out. Just went hazy.
- Bending over? What could that do?
I don't know. Maybe it's equalizing
the pull, something like that.
- Meeting gravity halfway.
Possible. But not probable.
Bending over puts the heart
level with the brain.
It might hold the blood above
heart level.
Next time. Try bending
over low as you can.
First it's yells, then it's bends.
Maybe we should try ski jumping next.
Wait a minute. It may be a guess.
But it's worth trying.
Sit down. I'll show you
the physiological principle involved.
Well. Come out of the test tube. Men.
- Fifty cadets are waiting for examination.
- Right.
Well. Back to earth again.
Now you know how Einstein feels when
he has to add up the household bills.
Take your places for inspection.
All right. Come on.
Take them over here.
- How many are there?
- About 30. sir.
General physical.
Heart. Lungs. Height. Weight. Index.
- Take the ear examination.
- All right. Shirts off!
All right. Gentlemen. Give way. Please.
- More civilians?
- Yes. Sir.
Remember me, sir?
Lucky. Pearl Harbor. I've just been
detailed to be your assistant.
Remember you?
You're a window in the house of my life.
Good to see you.
Glad you got transferred.
So am l. Sir. I'm a new man
since I got away from my wife.
I feel 10 years younger.
I'm putting on weight.
Lucky. Come over here.
It's sure nice to be back with you again.
Thanks. Lucky. Right back at you.
There's a babe in the pay office
looking for you.
- A babe?
- Yeah. A blond with a Brooklyn accent.
She's getting an allotment blank
for your pay.
My wife! That can't be!
She couldn't have swum from Honolulu.
I wouldn't put it past her.
Sir. I gotta hide right away.
This can happen to the best of men.
- Go right ahead.
- Thank you. Sir.
Head her off. Stop her!
Give me a break. Will you?
Where are you going to hide?
How about the Isolation Ward?
Lieutenant. You got genius.
Come on!
Yeah. But. Lucky. Can't you...?
Where is he? Where's my husband?
- Mrs. James?
- In person.
He's in there. But you can't go in.
He's a very sick man.
He'll be a lot sicker
when I get through with him.
I hate to tell you this.
But they're afraid he's got:
If that ever gets in the arm. The whole:
The neck starts:
Comes down the... on the racetrack.
And any time you go into... the... and:
It's very serious.
Whatever that is.
It's too good for him.
Don't get too close.
It's very contagious.
You see. Ma'am.
How it comes and goes?
- And so will l.
Head up.
All right. Down again.
Feel dizzy?
- Yes. Sir.
- It's all right, Abbott.
- It's a perfectly normal reaction.
- Oh. Thank you. Sir.
- Feel all right?
- Yes, sir.
I can see you are.
Report to the training office.
- Thank you. Sir.
- Who's next? You"?
Well. It's a small world. Isn't it?
Yes. Sir.
- Getting plenty of exercise lately?
- Yes. Sir. Too much, sir.
That's good.
If one eye sees higher.
Which would you land with?
The good one, sir.
Better keep your left up.
Or you won't have a good one.
I won't forget that. Sir.
- What's your middle name?
- Thomas. John Thomas Anthony Ill. Sir.
Born Hempstead. New York.
June the 12th, anno Domini 1919.
This is 1941. San Diego. California.
9:30 a.m., sir.
Very good.
Make a note. Mentally alert...
fresh as a new-laid egg.
Well. An egg anyway.
Favorite sports: automobile racing
and boxing. Ready?
- Yes. Sir.
- Here you go.
Head down! Hold them. Yale!
He says he's practically got the stick
between his teeth now.
All right. Cut the motor.
Why don't you be practical.
You can't use your bending-over routine
without changing the cockpit.
How can a pilot aim with his head
bent down?
Well. He might try a periscope
or a Ouija board.
Can you design a bomber so the pilot
can lie down and aim the bomb...
- ...through the nose of the ship?
- Who's it for? Buck Rogers?
Seriously. Can it be done?
- I suppose a pilot could lie down...
and use auxiliary controls during
the dive. But it sounds silly to me.
Things are tough when a pilot
has to fly on his stomach.
I'll ask the design section.
But I'm sure they'll send...
an order transferring me
to a nut house.
When you two figure out
your next move. Let me know.
I'll be down in Squadron 2.
Gentlemen. I have a solution
to your problem.
Provide each dive-bombing pilot
with an old-fashioned stiff collar.
That will choke him and keep the blood
from rushing from his brain. So long.
Very funny.
“High. Tight. Old-fashioned stiff collar.“
What that guy needs is a high. Tight.
Old-fashioned whack over the head.
Stiff collar.
- Hey.
- What?
What that half-wit just said
about a collar...
except it's not a collar.
It's a belt. Understand?
- Frankly. No.
- Look. Lance...
you make a belt that fits around here.
It's rubber. Pneumatic.
Just before the dive. You inflate it.
That will push the stomach up
under the ribs. Like this:
Compress the whole upper part
of the abdomen.
That will keep the blood
above heart level.
Come on. Lucky. Hurry up.
What happens if this glorified corset
ain't right, sir?
You heard the story about the guy
whose parachute didn't open. Right?
- Do you know how to get into it?
- Sure. It's simple.
At least it was when I designed it.
Here. Place me under the bag. Will you?
- That's it.
- This makes me feel right at home. Sir.
How does it work?
This hooks up to the pressure flask in
the cockpit. When you start a dive...
you release the valve. It inflates it.
Does that. We hope.
It works the way it has on the ground.
It ought to be a cinch.
Did you tell Blake I was waiting?
He said he'd be here when he finishes
lining up the National Defense Program.
Oh. He did. Eh?
That's very clever of him.
Pressure belts. Pressure chambers.
Flying's getting to be as tough as my
wife. Pressure on you all the time.
Yeah.
Aren't you going to wait
for the commander, sir?
You're breaking regulations, doctor.
The commander will be awful sore.
Tell him I'll write him a letter
and explain everything.
Joe. Isn't that your test tube
taking off?
Yeah. What's the idea?
Looks like you're being stood up. Pal.
That lamebrain. He can't fly that ship.
There won't be enough left to identify.
Don't blame me if anything happens.
He shouldn't have done it.
I told him that.
I mean. I was gonna tell him that.
But he got away so fast, I couldn't.
He ain't had enough experience
to fly that ship.
- He's heading for the last roundup.
- Pipe down. What's the matter with you?
Nothing. Sir. I'm just neurotic.
Thought you'd meet me with
a crash truck and fire engine?
No. Sir. A whiskbroom and a dustpan.
- Get the instruments. Will you?
- Aye. Aye. Sir.
Works like a charm. I hoisted her
back to 10 G and didn't even get hazy.
I'm afraid to say it.
But we may have something.
I'm not afraid to say it.
- Aren't you a bit green to dive alone?
- Yeah.
Ground's hard when you
bounce a plane off of it.
But you see. With this belt. You won't.
Some real pilot better check it
before we get excited.
Of course we're gonna check on it.
Test it. Send it to Washington.
Ask them to equip other groups...
- ...so they can check it.
- Fine. I hope it works out.
I envied you up there. Doug.
Being glued to the ground.
I feel as if I'm doing only half the job.
What are you talking about?
You do more than any two of us.
It's funny how a guy's mind works
when he's up there flying.
Just before I put her into that dive.
I kept thinking to myself:
"There's two kinds of blackout
this belt may whip."
Our kind and the sort they're having
over London right now.“
Up.
Down. Up.
- Down. Up.
- Can we have a little music with this?
Down. Sure. What do you want?
Some boogie-woogie? Up.
Down. That's enough.
Sit down. Relax.
- Let me see the chart. Will you?
- Here.
All right. Your Schneider index
seems too good to be true these days.
The result of clean living
and high thinking.
Commander?
Dr. Rogers. How long do I have to keep
on taking these Schneiders anyway?
I know it's a nuisance.
But we have to track changes...
in pulse and blood pressure.
It's one way of determining
if you should continue flying.
I think it's a lot of bunk.
Come on. Hill.
Is that all?
Look. Washington's approved the belt
for further tests.
- It has? Swell.
Congratulations, doctor.
Washington doesn't care
what it approves of these days.
When do we go?
When do we start testing?
A couple carriers are due next month
for a bombing problem.
Couldn't be better. That'll give us
a chance to try it in group action.
- Better take a look at that chart.
- Come on. Tim.
Go on and take those charts
out of my hair.
Tim. I'd like to see you for a minute.
What's the matter?
Haven't I bounced enough?
You better be in on this too. Joe.
Well. Sounds like a tea party.
Hey. Lucky. She's back again.
Why don't somebody tell me
when it's payday?
- Here we go again. Boys!
- Hey. Look. You better be careful.
He's asleep. Mrs. James.
He had a bad night.
He's got worse ones coming
when he gets better.
We're doing all we can
to get him back on his feet.
Just get him strong enough to sit up. I'll
have more fun beating him on the head.
No. You see. The doctor says he's got:
You see... for the patient's...
and they get themselves laying in bed:
- Look. You see where it says “ward“?
- Yeah.
Well. You take the D out
and the... what have you got?
Piston rods.
So you see. It'll never help you.
It will satisfy my soul.
That dame's crazy.
You're not going to recommend me
for a waiver. Are you?
- That's right.
- The service can't lose a pilot like Tim.
Can't you wait.
Give him another Schneider?
- I don't believe that would do any good.
- What do you know?
I can count. Read a watch
and a blood-pressure dial.
- What's wrong with me?
- Pilot fatigue.
As far as flying's concerned,
you're worn-out.
Like the works of an old watch.
What are you talking about?
I can fly as well as I ever could.
Doug's right. There's no argument.
This tells the story.
Here's a composite graph of Schneider
indices in the cases of pilot fatigue.
This is the turning point.
Tense irritability. Nervousness.
You weren't in good shape when you
reported. I ran extra Schneiders on you.
When Dr. Lee took over your group.
I told him to continue with the tests.
Your Schneiders have been following
this curve.
Last week. You were here.
Now you're here.
In my book. That means
you're washed-up with flying.
- For how long?
- Maybe months. Maybe forever.
I can't get by without my flight pay.
I have a wife and kids to support.
- You can't do that on peanuts.
- These things are never easy on anyone.
I won't take any grounding from you.
If the Navy doesn't want experienced
pilots. I know who does.
If you're smart.
Stay out of airplanes.
Stick around a couple months.
See what happens.
Why stick around
and get turned down again?
That's nice going.
I don't know how we ever got along
around here without you.
Don't resign. Tim.
I can fit you into a good ground job.
You know there's no such thing
as a good ground job.
I'd go crazy every time
a plane flew past.
What's this other thing?
Same thing you'd do
if you were kicked out.
- Smoke?
- I got one.
Why didn't you make him
stop flying sooner? Take a rest?
Because flying is like adrenaline
to tense pilots.
Take it away. And they fold up.
So you keep them flying.
Try to coax them back on their feet.
But when the fatigue becomes chronic.
They're usually through.
I know you hated it.
This is a hard business.
A flight surgeon has to face the truth.
And often. It isn't very pleasant.
It certainly isn't.
Well. I guess I should have followed
my mother's fondest wish.
She wanted me to be a violinist.
They all pulled out clean.
Twelve minutes and 15 seconds.
That's really bombing.
A little less doubtful
about the belt now. Commander?
Real pilots used the belt.
Found it's all right.
The belt flew the planes
and aimed the bombs for them.
It'll probably make coffee for them
when they get out.
I think we can forget about blackouts
from now on.
Get stretchers
and take them to sickbay.
It must be high-altitude sickness.
If it is. It's worse than blackout.
The unsolved problem.
Better not stay unsolved for long.
If it does. My mother will get more than
her wish. We'll both wind up violinists.
Royal Air Force fighter, landing on field.
It's the RAF.
He's way off his beat.
Hey. That's a nice job.
I'd hate to have that on my tail
in a dogfight.
- Say. Isn't that Tim Griffin?
- Yeah.
Commander Blake.
- Hi. Fella.
- Hi. Boy.
Commander Blake. Tim's back.
He just brought in that RAF fighter.
- Hi. Tim!
- How are you, Tim?
Hi. Sailor! How are you?
- Well. How are you, sailor?
- Tim. What brought you down here?
I picked it up in L.A..
Ferried it to Canada.
Took a detour to see how
you were doing without me.
We're doing all right.
Look at that uniform.
How do you like that?
They call me the Beau Brummell
of Montreal.
- How about some gas?
- Got a credit card?
- I just sign the bill “Winston C.“
- Okay. Now. Fill her up.
- Don't touch the motor. It's perfect.
- Nothing else, Tim?
- I'll take anything that isn't
nailed down. - How's a spot of tea?
- And a hamburger?
- Right.
Well. Look here.
How are you?
Aren't you pretty.
I'm looking for a beauty contest to enter.
Next month. I go on
transatlantic bomber ferry.
Each pilot flies his own ship over.
One plane brings them back.
It's real dough. A hundred pounds‘ bonus
a hop. And four and five hops a month.
A thousand bucks a month?
Yeah. If any of you guys want a job.
Just let me know.
Hey. What's the lowdown
on the RAF fighter squadrons?
Nobody chases ships anymore.
They're too fast.
You pick out an enemy. Dive on them
and hose them with eight machine guns.
If you don't drop him down. Keep going.
Look for another pushover.
Altitude's the answer.
Forty to 45,000 feet.
The guy on top wins all the marbles.
I've got to roll, Joe. Check.
Oh. No. This one's on Uncle Sam.
You mean. Uncle Joe. Okay.
Oh. Hello. Doctor. You remember me?
Worn-out, rundown “like the works
of an old watch“?
- Sure. How are you?
- Still flying. No thanks to you.
But I thank you
for kicking me into a better job.
I hope all of my mistakes
turn out that well.
They might if your patients get away
from you early enough. I was lucky.
I hope your luck holds. Chum.
In fact. I wish you all the luck
in the world.
Well. Thanks for those few kind words.
Come on. Joe. So long. Sailors.
- Ninety gallons.
Ninety gallons.
And charge it to Winston C.
Thanks.
I'll smoke one of my own.
- Sort of miss the old gang. Don't you?
- Yep.
The days you and Swede and I flew
together were the happiest in my life.
We can't live them over.
But they're sure swell to look back on.
This is all right.
Great bunch of people up there
and on the other side...
but I'd rather be a pilot
in the Navy...
with you as my skipper
than anything on earth.
Thanks. Tim. Right back at you.
- Say. How have you been feeling. Really?
- Oh. Fine. Fine. Joe.
Of course. I get woozy now and then
after too many hours in the air.
That's why I break these ferry trips up
into short jumps.
Where do you land?
San Francisco or Medford?
I'll go on to Seattle.
That's an easy hop.
- So long. Joe. It's been swell.
- Take care of yourself. Sailor.
Thanks.
RAF fighter. Griffin, pilot.
San Diego for Seattle.
Please notify San Francisco,
Medford and destination.
Expected time of Arrival, 5:10.
That is all.
Let me know when he passes
San Francisco and Medford...
- ...and when he arrives in Seattle.
- Aye. Aye.
Mr. Griffin passed Medford.
Both Seattle and Vancouver are calling
him now. He doesn't answer.
- Thank you. Take over.
- Aye. Aye.
- Larson. Smith.
- Here. Sir.
San Francisco calling Griffin
in RAF lighter.
Medford calling RAF fighter.
Griffin, pilot. Griffin, answer Medford.
Seattle calling Griffin.
This is Vancouver. Griffin, RAF lighter,
answer Vancouver.
San Francisco to Medford.
Have you checked all emergency fields
north of your station?
Medford to San Francisco. It‘s gone out
by Teletype. We‘re on the phone now.
Medford to all stations.
RAF fighter. Griffin, pilot. Attempted
to land at emergency field 26.
He made a normal approach,
but misjudged his altitude...
and hooked a wing against a hangar.
The ship is a washout.
The pilot was instantly killed.
That is all.
San Francisco to all stations.
Resume regular routine.
Think we should've denitrogenated Elmer
before taking him up to 25,000 feet?
He'd look cute riding
a stationary bicycle...
trying to work the nitrogen
out of his system.
I think that whole decompression theory
is much overdone.
I'm inclined to agree with you.
I've heard you want
human guinea pigs...
- ...for your low-pressure research.
- We do.
I'd like to volunteer for the job.
Also as pilot for your high-altitude work.
When you get to it.
That's great. But I thought you felt
our work was a waste of time.
I guess I've been wrong
about a couple of things.
The pressure belt and Tim Griffin.
- Can you use me?
- I'll say we can. We'll let you know.
Thanks.
Start reducing pressure.
A thousand feet.
Five thousand.
Ten thousand.
Twenty-five thousand.
- That's it.
- Elmer can take it.
Take him up to 40.000.
If he's all right, we'll try it on humans.
Okay.
- Good morning.
- Good morning. Sir.
This is human guinea-pig experiment 32.
Its purpose is to study
how the lack of oxygen...
affects your ability
to coordinate rapid movements.
I appreciate your volunteering for this
experiment. And good luck. All right.
Just sit down anywhere. Gentlemen.
And adjust your oximeters on your ear.
That will show the amount of oxygen
in your bloodstream.
Now. I think you understand
about this chamber.
It's for reproducing the conditions
of flying at high altitude.
We do this by pumping out the air inside
and gradually reducing the pressure.
The higher the altitude.
The more trouble you'll have...
coordinating your movements
so that you can fly properly.
We're ready.
Mac's in chair number one.
Abbott's in two.
Anthony's in three.
Blake in four.
- All right. Start reducing pressure.
- Aye. Sir.
Now. Follow the movement of the lights
with your controls.
By lining the green light
with the red...
you indicate your ability
to coordinate.
Five thousand feet.
Five thousand.
Six thousand.
Seven thousand.
Eight thousand.
Nine thousand.
Ten thousand.
Eleven thousand.
The pressure now corresponds
to 12.000 feet.
Put on oxygen masks.
Thirteen thousand.
I don't need any oxygen yet.
Tough guy Anthony says
he doesn't need oxygen.
All right. But watch him.
Sixteen thousand.
Ls Joe's equipment properly set?
- Nineteen thousand.
- Yes. It is.
Twenty thousand feet.
Twenty thousand feet. Going up.
Twenty-one thousand.
Twenty-two thousand.
Twenty-four thousand.
Twenty-live thousand.
Take a deep breath.
Once more.
Twenty-seven thousand.
Twenty-eight thousand.
How do you feel. Tough guy?
- Twenty-nine thousand.
- Never felt better.
Thirty thousand feet.
Thirty-one thousand.
Thirty-two thousand.
Better check Joe again.
Thirty-live thousand.
- Thirty-six thousand.
- That better?
- You said it.
- Thirty-seven thousand.
Lance. That setting wasn't adequate
for a man of his size. I increased it.
We're just under 40.000 feet.
Let me hear heartbeats.
Let me hear Blake's.
All right. Give me another one. Someone
who‘s had a full supply of oxygen.
Cut the motor.
Forty thousand.
Now. Let's see how long
you can stand this pressure.
Start to increase pressure.
We're coming down. Watch your ears.
What a hop.
Start rubbing it hard.
Aeroembolism.
Feels like a duffel bag full of jelly.
All right. Try it now.
- Is that better?
- Yeah.
Report to the lab
for x-ray pictures.
Thank you very much, gentlemen.
For being such cooperative rabbits.
I wish we could reward you.
But we're fresh out of lettuce.
Look straight.
All right.
There's a suggestion of gas bubbles
in this knee joint too.
Every case we've tested has shown
strong evidence of bubble formation.
The higher the altitude.
The stronger the evidence becomes.
See? No mistaking that.
Maybe flying should just be restricted
to 35.000 feet, and let it go at that.
We can't. In flying. The sky's the limit.
A fighter has to be able
to get above the other fella.
If you restrict altitude.
You're not making progress.
That's right. We've got to find
the cause of high-altitude sickness.
Whether it's partly bubbles
or entirely lack of oxygen.
All we've been able to find out is that
pilots need oxygen above 12,000 feet.
We don't know what high-altitude
sickness is, but we know how to stop it.
Keep the pilots at sea-level pressure.
No matter how high they go.
- When is that pressure-cabin job ready?
- Four. Five days.
Your pressure cabin might be fine
for big ships. Weight doesn't matter.
For the small fighter, the extra weight
will knock 5000 feet off your ceiling.
- We'll find out. Let's see blood counts.
- You need a close-fitting pressure suit.
You can't put a pilot in armor.
He'd be too stiff to move.
- He could move if it had flexible joints.
- Ventilation would be a problem.
The pilot would snuff out like that.
- I don't believe you can do it.
- Why does it have to be armor?
Wait a minute.
I think Blake's got something there.
Look. If we design it like this.
On the principle of a diving suit...
with flexible joints here.
Yet capable of holding oxygen inside...
Hurry think we'll have something. Look.
I'd like to work on it with you
if you're willing.
- It's okay with me.
- While you're knitting your union suit...
I'll go right ahead
with the pressure-cabin job.
You're wanted in the office
right away.
Fifty new cadets are
assigned to your squadron.
- Who assigned them?
- I don't know. Sir. I didn't.
Fifty? Why do they keep
shoving them at me?
What do they think I do? Wave a magic
wand and make fliers out of them?
Joe's pretty irritable lately.
You may have noticed it. Joe's
Schneider chart's been missing.
Yeah. I did.
I didn't want it known that he's been
on the pilot fatigue curve lately.
Dropped to two this morning.
He's almost reached the chronic line.
That means we've got to get another
man for our high-altitude work.
That might be the worst possible move.
He still has a fair chance for recovery.
It will be tough on him
after all the work he's done.
Is he worried about something else?
No. But I think Griffin's death
hit him pretty hard.
Besides. He's tense, nervous as a cat.
Works all the time.
- Doesn't know how to play.
- You could help him with that.
Me? I doubt that.
Wait a minute.
I've got a clue.
- Maybe I can, at that.
- Good.
Hey. Lucky.
- I've got a job for you.
- Aye. Aye. Sir.
Hey. Lucky. Lower your boom.
Tugboat Annie's back again
with a full head of steam.
Ain't a guy got no privacy
in this man's Navy?
You can't see him, Mrs. James.
He's gotten lower.
He couldn't get any lower than he was.
Where is the snake?
- In an oxygen tent with four nurses.
- That sounds like him.
I bet they're all blonds.
Are they? Are they all blonds?
No. Male nurses. We're trying
to pull him through the crisis.
Better get him pulled by next payday.
Or I'm going to the admiral.
Mrs. James?
Hurry...
I was just wondering if I couldn't
sort of help you with the admiral?
You know him?
Truthfully. No. But he and a friend
of mine are very good pals.
I thought we could discuss it
somewhere sometime.
Perhaps tonight for dinner? About 7?
- Well. I don't know.
- 7:30?
I suppose it'll be all right.
Seeing how I'm practically a widow.
Your husband's in a bad way. And we
could discuss the various arrangements.
Well. I live at the
Blue Horizon Apartments.
I'll meet you in the lobby.
Make it 7. And please don't be late.
I'm always on time.
You see. Hurry... for the Navy.
I can... traditions. You know.
People talking about the state.
I walk through... Boy Scouts. But:
That's nice. So am l.
I'll see you later.
Okay. Lucky. All clear.
Hey. What's wrong with you, bud?
Measles.
What's yours?
- Why is this door open?
- Well. I was going...
What are you doing in there?
I was checking things to see if
everything's shipshape for inspection.
There's measles in that ward.
You'll have to stay in Isolation.
My sister's in town.
And if I could see her tonight...
then I'd come back
and have my measles in peace.
You can see her in 21 days.
Take care of him.
- Aye. Aye. Sir.
- What am I gonna do for 21 days?
I wouldn't pay any attention
to the captain. Lucky.
What if you are... and people
bring you...?
You can have:
What can you lose?
It's healthy:
I'll even bring you my socks.
You can darn them.
You understand that Navy property
is valuable. Don't you?
You took the risk of cracking up
your plane by landing on field seven.
- Your orders were clear. Am I right?
- Yes. Sir. But Hurry...
You haven't answered my question.
You made the landing in emergency field
number seven against orders. Why?
I wanted to try landing
in a small field. Sir.
You tried it and cracked up your plane.
You weren't ready for it.
I wasn't ready for the wheelbarrow
left on the runway.
Otherwise. I made a perfect
three-point landing.
You can try one on the washout board
at 4:00. You're through.
That's all.
Too bad about that kid.
He had the makings of a great pilot.
Yeah. For a circus.
The Navy has no place for stuntmen.
That's funny. I always thought you did
quite a bit of stunting yourself once.
Along time ago.
For publicity purposes.
The Navy has changed since then.
Well. It just seemed too bad, after all
that time you spent on him. To lose it.
I'll bet a month's pay that you got your
ears pinned back for the same thing.
- Who told you that?
- Nobody. That's the kind of guy you are.
Why don't you give him another chance.
He thinks you're great.
All you have to do is talk to him
to straighten him out. How about that?
You're the nosiest guy I ever met.
And it's always in my business.
- I'll give him one more chance.
- Swell.
Thanks. And while you're in the same
mood. I'd like to ask one more favor.
- What is it?
- Remember my pal Linda Fisher?
She's getting into town with a friend.
Help me out?
No soap. I got a lot of work to do.
What's her friend look like?
I've never known Navy fliers.
But I know lots of Army fliers.
They're loads of fun.
That's very interesting.
- Did you miss me dreadfully?
- Miss you? Oh. I could hardly stand it.
Isn't that pleasant?
How long have I been gone?
How long? Must have been weeks.
Wasn't it?
Weeks? I've been gone for months.
You foul creature.
You haven't heard a word I've said.
- Are all Navy men so absent-minded?
- Yeah. No. no.
Hey. Lee. It just hit me.
I know how we can control
the pressure and oxygen in that suit.
Globe valves with fine threads
on the spindles.
- Wouldn't work, I don't think.
- Yes. It would work. I'll show you.
- Are they all like that?
- He seems to infect them.
Unfair to organized womanhood.
Maybe if we extended this flange
down a little farther.
It won't do it, Joe. The movements
to the valve aren't fine enough.
You'll either get a slight trickle of
oxygen or a whole slug of it all at once.
You've got to have a smooth.
Fine. Hairline control.
How about a shampoo
and finger wave?
You know. I fly too.
But I'm not such a bore about it.
I can talk about other things
now and then.
We'll have to find somebody
to invent a new valve.
I'll try if you've got
another screwdriver.
Excuse me.
That shade won't be becoming to you.
Joe? Look.
A slide valve with a fine screw
on the stem.
Each turn opens it just a hair.
This is it.
Sure. That's got it. Look.
If we design something like this.
Have the outlet...
Will you gentlemen excuse us. Please?
Helen. Not so loud.
You might wake them up.
- And I said they'd be exciting.
- I'm disappointed in the Navy.
It's getting so a girl
can't compete with nuts and bolts.
Well. There's always the Marine Corps.
May I help you?
Yes.
This valve engages this gadget.
We're off to the races.
- Have we overlooked anything?
- No.
- Dr. Lee?
- Yeah.
Mrs. Fisher asked me
to give you this with a message.
Thanks.
"Hume Mechanics Magazine.“"
- What was the message?
- Sailors, you're an awful bore
Valves to you We've gone ashore
We don‘t like quarrels
We don‘t like scenes
The Navy's tau busy
We'll try the Marines
These pressure-cabin jobs are tricky.
Sure you understand all the controls?
- Pressure. Oxygen. Humidity. Temperature?
- Certainly.
Don't look toward the sun when you get up.
Its rays will blind you in that thin air.
Thanks. So long.
Why do we need oxygen masks
in a pressure cabin?
- We don't.
- What did we bring them along for?
Force of habit, I guess.
Just over 35.000 feet.
- How do you feel?
- I'm getting a little woozy.
Why can't we keep the pressure up?
Can't and still ventilate.
Supercharger is full on.
It's no good at this height.
What's our next move?
I don't know.
Maybe we better get out and walk.
Thirty-six thousand.
Picking up ice.
She's sweating.
Thirty-eight thousand.
I can't balance the temperature
and humidity.
She's sluggish on the controls.
Too much ice.
The de-icer's frozen.
Give me oxygen.
I guess I left you for a few minutes.
- Are you all right?
- Yeah. I'll take it.
Swing low. Sweet chariot.
I heard the horn that time.
- What horn?
- Gabriel's.
This is about the most attractive
piece of ground I ever stood on.
Yeah. We almost bought
6 feet of it apiece.
Cigarette?
Yeah. Thanks.
It's gonna be tough on Art.
Well. It wasn't exactly a picnic for us.
Thanks.
- How'd it go?
- Make a nice ice wagon. Art.
- That's about all.
- Took two of us to handle the controls.
We were busier than one-armed
paperhangers and twice as cold.
Cabin's too damp. It sweats
and gathers ice by the ton.
- Outside of that. It's perfect.
- For everything but flying.
Well. I guess that's that.
Here's where we're
starting all over again.
Send me a full report.
I'm glad you got it down all right.
Thanks. So are we.
Can I interest you in our pressure suit?
You're going to have less luck with that
than you had with my pressure cabin.
This puts the whole problem
right in your laps. Boys.
Fine. It's right where we want it.
- Is this where the oxygen line goes in? -
It fits here. There's a slide valve for it.
- Where does your microphone plug in?
- Here.
There's a communication system
built in the helmet.
- You can see it.
- Oh. I see.
Lieutenant, this is gonna look
just like a diver's helmet.
Well. We don't care if it looks like
a birdcage. Just so that it works.
Here's your oxygen line right here.
44.500.
44.700.
45.000. There it is.
That's enough.
It's time to come down.
Cut the motor.
Open the pressure valves wide.
- Get the valves in the back.
- Aye. Sir.
You'd be in horrible shape if a mosquito
got in there with you. Wouldn't you?
- How was it? - Great. Except
I feel like a fish in a bowl.
Fine. Lift it off easy.
- How did the valves work?
- Like a charm.
It was worth losing two dames over.
I'll fly this suit to 50.000 if
I have to climb hand over hand.
I better check on your ticker anyway.
- Breathe normally.
- I'm all right.
Considering its weight.
It's pretty comfortable.
I like to hear that.
Wouldn't like to play tennis
in it. Would you?
Let me butt in here.
Listen. Boys. I think you really
got something here.
I guess that's all. Come. I want
to take a Schneider on you.
- Why?
- Just to keep the practice.
Lance. You can't do it that way.
You can't hand a man a piece of paper
with that kind of news in it.
It's too cold-blooded.
If you got a better idea. I'm willing
to listen. You can't send it to him.
I suppose not. That would be worse.
Everything's all set.
The ship's raring to go.
Cigarette?
- No. Thanks.
- Lance?
You boys gonna be out there
with a band to see me off?
Well. What's eating you guys?
One of your rabbits got the pip?
No.
I was just discussing it with Lance...
and it would be better
if you didn't make this hop.
No. This KING'S my baby.
What's the difference
who makes the test?
- You know the suit will work.
- You mean. We think it will work.
Come on. Level with me.
I smell some kind of a runaround.
No. There's no runaround. It's...
I wish I could think of some other way.
But I can't.
Your Schneider hit the chronic-fatigue
line this morning.
We checked it every way. Twenty times.
Backwards and forwards. No mistake.
You mean. I'm washed-up.
No. No. I wouldn't put it that way.
A man of your experience is always
gonna be valuable in the service.
So what if you have
to give up flying a while?
- You can keep running your squadron.
- Yeah.
I'll be a great example for those boys.
Parked in the office with my knitting.
I guess it had to happen
sooner or later.
It's tough to get yanked out of the ring
when the main event is about to start.
- After you've trained all your life.
- You've trained plenty of other guys.
If and when the main event does start.
They'll be in there pitching.
Sure. Sure they will.
Well...
it was a good show while it lasted.
I would like to have finished
this pressure-suit job...
before the rocking chair got me.
- Is that my diploma?
- Yeah.
I better take it just to make it official.
Say. Do you know...
some other man who can
do this test job for us?
Yeah. Yeah. I'll have
a good pilot for you.
Thanks.
Joe.
I wish there was something
I could say...
but there never is. Is there?
Commander Blake.
Yes?
I just wanted to thank you for
giving me another chance.
- Forget it.
- It's meant a lot to train under you. Sir.
Thanks. Just remember
one rule. Anthony:
As a pilot. Fight to be on top
and stay there.
- You can't lick them from below.
- I won't forget that. Sir.
- Is she ready?
- Yes, sir.
- Pull her out.
- All right, boys. Pull her out.
Just a minute. Sir.
There seems to be something wrong.
There. That's got it.
How'd he take it?
Not as hard as I thought he would.
That doesn't sound like Joe Blake.
No. Rotten job. Though.
- Who's in that plane that just took off?
Lieutenant Commander Blake, sir.
I want to contact Lieutenant
Commander Blake. He's in 6FOX4.
Very well.
San Diego. Calling Lieutenant
Commander Blake in 6FOX4.
This is Blake in 6FOX4. Go ahead.
Joe. This is Doug. What the devil
do you think you're doing?
I'd say I'm doing about 250
at 26.000 and going up.
Are you“? Don't try to take
that ship to its ceiling.
Why not? That was the whole idea.
I want to prove this.
Then you can turn me out to pasture.
Listen. You're in no shape to fly.
You've been grounded.
I can't hear you, pal.
The neighbors are playing the radio.
Joe. This is Lance. Don't be a fool.
Come on down.
Twenty-eight thousand.
This suit works like a charm.
We should open a tailor shop for angels.
Joe. That's high enough.
You've done the job.
Now head up for the stable.
I can't do a thing.
She's got the bit in her teeth.
Look...
the skipper's come in the room.
He's here with us.
He's ordering you to land.
Tell him he shouldn't be hanging around
the radio tower. It's undignified.
Thirty thousand.
Life begins at 40.
Listen to reason, you crazy idiot.
You guys are wasting my breath.
I'll see you later.
Joe.
Switched off.
Might as well argue with a wall.
That ship's out of control.
Sound the crash alarm.
“Heat oxygen line to prevent ice.
Suit perfect then.“
The sole purpose in forming
for this ceremony...
is to honor the men who. During the
year. Have done the most for the service.
So it's my privilege to make an award
of this trophy...
for the year's outstanding
achievement in aviation.
And so we honor two flight surgeons...
Lieutenant Commander Rogers
and Lieutenant Lee...
whose professional skill
has made possible...
the effective work
of our finest pilots and best planes.
These men have been instrumental in
solving some of the greatest problems...
in aviation medicine.
They've been more than faithful
to the flight surgeon's creed:
"Keep them in the air.“"
We also honor the memory of
Lieutenant Commander Joseph Blake...
who heroically sacrificed his life
in first testing the pressure suit.
His supreme sacrifice
was not made in vain.
It insured that the planes
and pilots of this nation...
can more safely fly. Fight and defend
their country in the stratosphere.
Lieutenant Lee.
I accept this. Sir. On behalf
of my friend and coworker...
Lieutenant Commander Blake.
A very gallant gentleman.
And salute.
Pilots. Man your planes.
Lieutenant?
I've been ordered to stay on duty
as an instructor.
Any time you need a guinea pig
for future research...
I'd like to carry on Blake's work.
That will be fine.
We'll let you know.
And. Sir. The pilots would like to have
you make this hop with us. If you wish.
Thanks. Thanks. I would like to.
.