Subtitles by Nostromo
Heil Hitler!
-In your opinion Herr Dr
-He's been talking too much
He has to speak in Munich on Thursday
Impossible,no public appearances
for at least 10 days
I'd  thought you'd say that
He won't listen to us
Has the heat turned up,
the rooms like an oven
-Just what I was going to say
-Exactly what I did say
-Well,Heil Hitler!
-Heil Hitler-Heil Hitler
Herr Roeder
There you are,Rabenau
I suppose you're going to tell
me he can't speak on Thursday
If he does,I won't answer
for the consequences
I knew it,now Goering and
Goebbels will both want to deputize
Why not a duet?
I'm afraid there might be
a little lacking in harmony
Good bye
BTW I haven't seen you since
your wedding,my congratulations
Thank you
Ought to be some restrictions
on you Austrians
carrying off all the beauty of Berlin
More restrictions
What can a poor Prussian policeman
hope to do against your fatal charm?
Why not use your powers of arrest?
-Remember me to Irena,won't you?
-Yes I will
Open
Yes,that's a little inflamed
Say A
A
-Again
-Ninety nine
I'd have you know my other patients
treat with me with some respect
They are not married to you,
darling,at least I hope they are not
Seriously you can't afford to take
chances now you're in rehearsal
I've just been telling that
to another celebrity
Who?
Sc ch,we are indisposed
Oh dear,I hope it's nothing serious?
He has what it's called
laryngismus stridulus
My goodness what it's first name?
If you had it,it would be a sore throat
Oh,darling you are silly
-Otto!
-Irena
Darling!
I thought you were not
arriving until tomorrow
Hello Otto,what sort of
time did you have in Italy?
Marvelous,thanks
What do you got there? A prix de Rome?
No,I just missed it
Well,lets have a look at them anyway
Oh,that's delightful
Isn't that cow rather anemic?
Speaking as a throat specialist or a vet?
Rebuffed again,I'd just had
one from Mrs Roeder
Done you good,darling
Thank you very much
Now then,now then,time you're off
Hello Mr Otto,glad to see you back
Now don't you forget
you've got two calls to make
before you go to your club
there's your coat and there's your flower
Thank you
That club,why has it be tonight
It's only once a year,my sweet
I'll be back to see
the new year in with you
You stay,won't you Otto?
I'd love to
I want to make the final
diagnosis of that cow
Karl
Your flower
One day I'll come and spy on you
You'd be bored to death
we just sit round talking rather pompously
trying to pretend we
are still at Heidelberg
That's what you tell your wives
Tell me about your work
Oh,what are you looking at?
I had to watch that sort of
thing the whole time out in Italy
Well,do watching now darling
You can do it
Suppose I shall
I shall be rather silly
Probably make you very fit
Get rid a little of this
I must say they do look rather good
One,two,three,four,five,six,
seven only eight tonight,Sebastian
Yes,Sir
Large Muencher, please
Hello Franz,hello Josef
Wonderful platform for workmen
No unemployment, all you see it's
what's in front of your face
Hello Karl
-Hello Heini
-Hello Karl
No,no, you need know the rules
no politics,isn't it so,Karl?
Absolutely,you should do as
I do leave politics to politicians
There you are,what did I tell you
-Your,beer,Sir
-Thanks
-Telephone,Sir
-Thank you
Well,I leave him to you
It's all very well he's joking
Why is it that bad comedians
are gloomy on the stage
and good comedians,like
you my dear Emil, are gloomier
Karl,I'm just telling Franz
how I got this,you remember?
I remember yours most attractive
Karl,gruss
-Hello,Karl
-Hello Rudolf
When did you get back?
What was America like?
I don't know I went to New York
No need to ask if married life suits you
Heavens,this is as obvious as all that
Nothing could have pleased me better
Hello,Father
-Beer?
-Well,just a large one
Sebastian
Gustav
Ah Rudolf,excuse me one moment
Well,how are you after
your American triumphs?
Hello,Father
Isn't it extraordinary always
bottom of the class
Now look at him lightning a 3 mark cigar
Yes,you remember he never
could do a simple equation
and now he can make a million
vanish right under your eyes
Can you never know what's happen to it
High finance and mathematics,
Father,have nothing in common
Judging by your record it certainly haven't
What is it Heini,has she
canceled that supper date?
Oh,no as a matter of fact it was the
Gestapo
The want me there now
It is something I
Probably a driving offense
or something like that
Expect I'll be back in 20 minutes
In case I'm not in time,Happy New Year
One,two,three only four tonight,Sebastian
I'm afraid so,Sir
Large Munchener
Father
-Emil
-Hello Karl
Rudolf
I must say these reunions give me a
slight sense of decreasing exhilaration
I never realized that this
room was so large
Let's get rid of some of those chairs
-Any news of Heini?
-No
No news
Your beer,Sir
Cheer up Sebastian take a drink with it
Oh thank you very much,Sir
We are here anyway
Emil are your audiences still
hanging on every word you sing?
I'm afraid not there's are words I sing
more likely to hang me
Don't sing
Some actors I know might
be improved by hanging
Really,Father,remember you
thought that most unchristian sentiment
Gentlemen
Sebastian
Gentlemen I didn't mean tell you
until the end of the evening
But I'm afraid that this is our last night
We have orders to close the whole club
Student meeting are forbidden now Dr
But I
I would like to say how much
I've enjoyed serving you,gentlemen
After that I don't think
we can pretend anymore
No,what good are meeting places for friends
When one can't be sure any longer
who is your friend,I'm going home
-Good night,Father
-Good night,Emil
-Coming,Rudolph
-Yes-Good night,Karl
Bye Emil
Oh,I must be getting along to a church
You're coming to watch service,aren't you?
Yes I hope to bring my wife with me
If I can get her away from theater in time
-Let's see she is playing in
-Iphigenia
Oh yes of course
Iphigenia
I should be glad if you'd come
There's nothing wrong,Father?
No,no,nothing only
I should just be glad if you could come
-How much have you seen?
-Last act
-You are wonderful
-Oh wasn't very very bad
The moment I saw the Fuhrer I collapsed
She's just coming
-Hello,Otto
-Hello
You're rather quickly
I had I'm just staying on duty
-Very pretty
-What do you think of my sets?
I liked them
Me?
You're all right
You beast
Actually I thought you were
frightfully good
Didn't you Hanna?
I've seen her worse
Take a week's notice
The Fuhrer thought you were marvelous
How do you know?
I was watching him the whole time
You must found the play very exciting
I can always see it again
You know that uniform is very becoming
Glad you like it
I do indeed,have you've been
doing any painting lately?
I haven't much time for
that sort of things nowadays
No I suppose not
-Good night,Irena
-Good night,darling
-Good night Karl
-Good night Otto
When the crowd comes in
you won't let them keep you
for too long,will you?
-No,of course not
-Give me one of those
Thank you
-Do and get yourself a drink
-Yes
Hanna,see who that is will you?
Rabenau
Ask him to come in
Willie,I'm glad to see you
More wonderful than ever
I was enchanted
Good evening Roeder
I hope I'm not in the way
No one could be more welcome
Let me give you a drink
On this occasion I think I must
Actually this is an official visit
but we must just drink a toast
The new director of popular patron
Our most distinguished actress
and producer,Frau Irena Roeder
You
You mean me?
But
I can't believe it
Karl,did you hear what he said?
Aren't you drinking the toast?
To you my darling
Taken my breath away
Der fuhrer wants to
congratulate you himself
I'm here to take you to
the chancellery at once
Of course I'll be as quick as I can
There's a whole crowd of them
outside,you have to see them
Oh dear,I'm afraid I must
Give me a minute
I'll be waiting for you in the car,Irena
We'll have to celebrate our
new year tomorrow
Oh,darling I am sorry
-What could I do
-Never mind
You'll be able to meet Father
Landbach some other time
You're going anyway?
Otherwise he'll be brokenhearted
-I'll be thinking of you at midnight
-Oh,darling
Hanna,you let them in
Oh,good evening,Dr Roeder
My dear you were divine my husband
stayed away from staff to see you
My dear brethren
Before I begin my address this evening
I want to tell you of something
something which I'm afraid will
distress you as it has distressed me
our good friend Father Brandt
who is well known to
and loved by many of us
has been removed from his parish
It is said that he was an
enemy of the Reich
A phrase we've lately heard
used of many of our brethren
but one which we who knew him best
will I think find it difficult to believe
I intend to ask you
prayers for Father Brandt
But before I do so
I feel it my duty to
give any who may wish
the opportunity of leaving now
I am glad so many of you will
give him a benefit of your prayers
He is in need of them
In asking our Mighty God to protect him
Shut up and come on down
I would ask you to intercede also
for those others who have preceded him
Stop him,come down
Friz Felderberg Johann Schmalz
Clear the church
Heinrich Meindorf
Emil Sonbach
Hans Feldman
Oscar Brandt
Fritz Schulz
Friedrich Mann
Herman Geldt
for those I have named I have asked
for blessing of our heavenly Father
Come along hurry up clear the church
Come on you get out
All right Hanna,good night,
see you in the morning
It wasn't nearly so alarming as I expected
He was most enthusiastic
about the performance
He couldn't have been more kind
Everyone was there,Goring and his
wife and nearly all party leaders
I can have my own offices
and all the staff I want
Are you listening?
Yes,of course
My first thing is Stuttgart
just think what a city
Any producer would give his soul
for let lose on a job like that
Apparently there is to be no restrictions
as regards expenses or labor
I've been thinking that it'll be
Darling,you're not listening
What's the matter?
I'm sorry,my sweet,I saw something
this evening which upsets me rather
Of what?
Oh,just a boy I used to
know behaving horribly
Who?
Let's not talk about it,on with
what you were saying
I hardly know what I am saying
I can't believe it
I can quite believe it myself
You are pleased though,aren't you?
You want me to be?
Oh,of course I do
The only thing that matters
Then you go ahead
A few more people like you at the
head of things,we might be a lot better off
Oh dear
Sounds very solemn
Being married to a high government
official is a very solemn business
Karl
This job won't make any
difference between us
Of course not
And subversive remarks from the pulpit
so inflamed the congregation
the priest was injured
Fatally
Fortunately stormtroopers
were able to restore order
But it is evident that scrupulous agitators
can no longer depend on their
cloth to protect them
from the indignation of the people
And here is the actual report,Sir
They went too far and
accidentally killed him
A little overenthusiastic
It is evident that unscrupulous agitators
can no longer depend on
their cloth to protect them
from the indignation of the people
Landbach's epitaph
He'll get no more
And we are responsible
We?
People like us criticizing,
grumbling and doing nothing
We are stifled my friend
What can we do?
Still people with a sense of decency
like you and Fenner
there must be others if
we could only reach them
Who's that?
I don't know
What are you doing?
Sorry,Sir didn't think I'd disturb you
You could hear us in the
next room,couldn't you?
No,Sir
Why are you here there's
nothing wrong with the radio?
Just an ordinary routine inspection,Sir
It's all in order
I see
Quite an interesting job yours
And well paid
I don't know so much about that,Sir
I do manage to pick up
a little bit on the side
Doing what?
Help a friend of mine
build sets in the evening
A budding Marconi
Wish I was,Sir
I think he was about the greatest
man who ever lived
You know,I shouldn't let the
Gestapo hear you say that
I didn't mean anything
You won't say anything,Sir,will you
You see I've been trying to
get license to build sets on my own
well it's hard enough unless you got a pull
Starting up yourself?
I want to,Sir,yes
You're a married man?
Going to be,next month,Sir
I might be able to put in a
word for you for that license
Thank you,Sir
-Whats your name?
-Hans Glaser,Sir
Al right,you drop me a
line tell me all about it
Yes,Sir
-Thank you,Sir,good morning
-Good bye
There's one they haven't spoiled
-Yes
But it's a nice thing we decided
that an ordinary workman could not
scare us out of our lives
-Hello Fritz
-Good morning,Hans
Give me half a dozen,will you
Hey
-Hans,someone might see us
-Who cares
-Elly,I've got some wonderful news
-What?
No,I don't think you ought to know
Oh,please,please tell me
All right,listen
Elly,here you are children
A nice hot lunch
Sausages,potatoes and sauerkraut
You shouldn't have bothered
Something colder could have
been quite good enough
Rubbish,you won't feeding up
Well I can't stay,Elly
I've got lot's to,and I don't
like leaving the flat too long
with that wretched Frau Lehman
nosing about like she does
Do you know I think that woman is actually
capable of raiding our larder
-Nonsense granny
-Oh yes she is
I've got some very special for you tonight
-Don't you be late either of you
-We won't-Good bye
Good bye,granny
Come on you must tell me
-Guess whom I've been just talking to?
-No,who?
-Have you London Times please?
-I'm sorry,Sir,it's been confiscated today
What again?
Now tell me who was it?
Doctor Karl Roeder
The great specialist
-No
-Yes
What's more he's going to
get me a radio sales license
Hans,that's wonderful
I should think it is
We can get get married
Right away
I'll make the finest sets on the market
You'll have a real diamond ring
Yes I had a long talk with Roeder
He asked my opinion of all sort of things
Not really?
Yes he was most impressed
You know when a chap is
seen with people like Roeder
It's nothing we can't do
We might even control the world's radio
Hans,I think you're wonderful
Watch one now for Hans
flight,see you tonight
Good bye
-Good afternoon,Frau Schmidt
-Good afternoon,Frau Lehman
I suppose you haven't got
a bit lard in that bag,Frau Schmidt
-No I have not
-Oh,Frau Schmidt
-Just a tiny,please
-No
You had all of mine last week
That's it,is it?
Living on the fat of the land
and you can't grant me
a little piece of lard
See your neighbour starve would
you never raise a finger to help her?
Now look here
You know very well I've no lard to give you
after all you've got as much as to
spend on food as I have as you didn't
-Well,out with it
-Well,spend it differently
So,now I can't have a drop
or two to keep my strength up
You let me starve in the gutter,I suppose
Because Judgment you're asking for
The Judgment
What a type that hag
My lard
"Mightiest nation in the world"
"Our great fuhrer as given
us new hope and a new faith"
"and Germany's destiny
will be the world's destiny"
"On est entendre Fleur
du mal tango de Brazil"
"et maintenant,chere auditeur
vous ecoutez a passe de muse quickstep"
You see what did I tell you
-All listening to foreign stations
-Shut up
"vous ecoutez maintenant une
autre information Washington.."
But I haven't heard
anything it was just the music
You seem to follow foreign broadcast
-Take her away
-Oh no
No please just a moment
I can explain,don't you understand
I was only listening to the music
I wasn’t do anything,oh Elly
Granny they're taking you
Who are you?
She's my granny what's been happening
What's the matter,where are they taking her
Quite calm,listen,there's nothing to
worry about,just a matter of routine
We'll take her to the police station,
where she'll answer a few questions
She'll be back in an hour
Now if you want to help your grandma
This is would you could do it,
tell me a little about her
Hello darling I thought you
were going out to Grunewald
I got Ludwig to go for me
So I could spend a little time with you
Thank you,darling
There's a wagon load of
fan mail for you over there
I look at it presently for just
two minutes I want to look at you
-What sort of morning?
-Wonderful
Now I'm married to the Reichsdirector
of Popular Pageantry
I could have charged double fees
You remember this
Sorry I can't dine with you tonight
-Oh hello
-I'm just going on duty
You're always going on duty
What is it this time?
-Just cleaning up
-Cleaning up?
-Like the other evening
-What do you mean?
Ask Otto
I do my duty and obey orders
Even when duties mean smashing up churches
and beating various people to death
He was an enemy of the state
even if he was friend of yours
But his death was an accident
Was it?
Does it occur to you that
he was doing his duty too
Duty? His duty was to his state
Not to his conscience?
If it wasn't for your position he would
be put away for saying less than that?
-You are just...
-Otto I'd better think you go
What was all that about?
The time they'll finished with him
he'll have no more soul than a sheep
You've seen what's happening to him
it's happening to thousands like him
Blind obedience for a rule
of force and terrorism
Frightening
What has Otto done?
He's the boy I told you
about the other evening
He was in the raid on Landbach's church
He was only obeying his orders
Oh,no he wasn't
I was there I saw the look on his face
He was enjoying himself
But if,it was the congregation
that attacked Landbach
Do you really believe that?
Hello
Who?
Oh yes I remember
What's the address?
Right,I'll come along
Sorry,Irena,I have to go
Something rather serious
Irena
I'd like you to do something
I'd like you to come with me
You might be able to help
It's a young girl
Well,of course I will
If I'm being of any use
It's the most monstrous
thing I've ever heard of
I do know how you must feel
That man won't go unpunished
that I promise you
I'm going to Herr Rabenau's office now
I'm staying here for a little
And I'm going straight to the Gestapo
What good that'll do?
Why should that fuffy devil
smash our lives and get away with it
-He shan’t do it..
-Steady
Get hold over yourself
What good will that do?
You'd only be shot or put
into a concentration camp
You wouldn't be much good to Elly there
You got to help her now
-Get on with your work
-My work
Building radios then to
shot their lies through
Sir,there is not a word of
truth in what she says
I'm not lying,he's the one that's
lying and you're all trying to hush it up
It's always the same
they can do anything if they are in uniform
and nothing ever happens to them
Nothing to do with the case be quiet
I won't be quiet I'm not the
only one and you know it
It isn't the first time you
try to hush things up
What abut the girl who
worked with Schwartzes?
And the Jewish tailor in the Oldergatz
And the priest,they
murdered Father Landbach
You're just a gang of murderers
and bullies,you dirty swine
You think nobody can ever touch you
but I'll tell everyone,
I'll shriek it everywhere
-Is it over?
-Yes,and the man will be made an example of
Poor child,come along
This is Dr Weiner
How do you do
I've just just been telling
Fraulein Schmidt
she's helped us tremendously
and we are very much obliged to you Irena
for bringing this to our notice
-Can I take her away now?
-I shouldn't advice
I've just given her a sedative
You'll see it's been a great
ordeal for her,poor child
We proposing to send her to a rest home
at Zell am see,at the state's
expense of course
That is good of you
The least we can do
When will she be going?
At once
Her fiance is outside could
she say goodbye to him?
By all means,Dr perhaps you go with her
What's happened?
She's got a little overwrought
The doctor's given her
something to quiet her
Can she come with me now?
Well,not just it
she's going to a rest home
for a little while,isn't she Dr?
Yes,we'll take great care of her
When she comes back she'll
be so well you won't know her
Doctor
-Good bye,Elly
-Good bye,Hans
Good bye
Hans
Oh Ellie,get well soon
You must admit that they
behaved very handsomely
Yes
They've been kind and generous
and done everything in their
power to make amends
I don't deny it
No,but you got reservations
why don't you admit
that you've been entirely wrong
and your attitude is most unfair
Oh but I do in this instance
I was completely wrong
All you said is perfectly true
But you see,my darling
unfortunately one case put right
doesn't mean that there aren't great
many which has not been put right
-But you can't ignore it
-Neither can you
Generalize about the case of
one girl lucky enough to have influence
There are thousands of others,my sweet
some of them humble fighting little
people with no one to speak for them
Who is generalizing now
who are these people?
What are their names?
All right,Heini,Fritz Mahler,
Trenker's eldest boy
Father Landbach,you know them all
and there are plenty more beside
Landbach,you'll always harking back to that
You known particularly well
that he defied the authorities
and preached sedition I..
I simply don't understand
your attitude at all
Of course you don't you
simply won't let yourself think
And you think far too much
you do nothing but criticizes
you won't admit that the
fuhrer has done anything
What's the good of arguing
They've got you,you're party official now
And I'm proud of it
Proud?
I believe that the party is
destroying this country
like a cancer destroys one of my patients
That's sheer treason
I won't listen to it
I'm going to Stuttgart tonight
I'd think it will be better
if you don't come down there
That's sheer treason
Come on you get out
Today our thousands across the frontiers
calls for the Fatherland for help
They shall not appeal in vain
Their cry is heard
They shall be free
Doctor
Could you build a radio transmitter?
Could you?
Yes but you can't get parts without
You mean you can give me the license?
Could you build one without a license?
You mean
On the quiet?
Yes
How old are you Glaser?
24,Sir
And you're not a member of the party
-Why?
-It's all right
I'm against them too
You?
You're not trying to trick me,Sir
No,Glaser,I'm not trying to trick you
I don't like living in a country
where you can't speak the truth
to fear your best friends gives you away
Yes all the shouting and bullying
and trying to train young kids think
going into war is grand
Well I think it's all wrong that's all
What's the use of talking
There might be some use in talking
-To a microphone
-Microphone?
That's the only way we will
ever get them to listen
loudspeakers blare at them all day
we've got to use their methods
but give them the truth
You mean,sort of pirate station
Yes,freedom stat,,,
That's it we'll call it the freedom station
You get me the materials
And I'll build a transmitter that
will reach the whole country
Good
-A piece of paper
-Yes
You realize what it means if we are caught
Yes
Fine
Let's make a list of what we want
Heil Hitler,I want a top
Heil Hitler
Take a choice which color would you like?
I'll have this one
That's 20 pfennig
Thank you
Give my love to your mother
Heil Hitler
That depends on the volume
I'll teach you how to use a selector
so you can work without
either of us being there
I think I've got the hang of the things
Well,so we can do without crystals
Is this it?
No I'm afraid not
Still a little more ammunition
-Here,Kurt, the sixteen limit
-Right
Is it nearly finished?
Yes except for the crystals
Without them we are sunk
They've should have been here hours ago
Something must have gone wrong
Perhaps just a minute
Good afternoon what can I do for you
I dropped this to be repaired
As arranged
Thank goodness I thought
you were never coming
Did you have any diff
Don't turn round now
Behave quite naturally
It's wonderful how the evenings
are drawing out,isn't it?
Of course with all this flu about
one still has to be careful
You keep quite well yourself
Cover up
No,that's not it
Perhaps
Yes,I think the boy likes that
Well,I'm afraid the squeaker
of that one is broken
But well what do you think
of that if it's for a boy?
Oh,no he sees too much of that at home
Well,what about that?
It was a policeman but he only
wanted the dog for his little boy
What about this?
Tonight at 10 30 we'll speak to them
-I've earthed it to the lightning conductor
-Good
Here you are
We are ready doctor
Two minutes to go
Attention everybody
This is the first broadcast of the German
freedom station calling on shortwave 26.9
freedom station calling on short wave 26.9
Every night at this hour
you will hear same uncensored news
as the rest of the world
Every night the lies shouted at
you by the ministry of propaganda
will be answered by the truth
Do you never ask yourself why
under the Nazis freedom of thought
and action is forbidden
Do you never ask yourselves why
you are no longer free to chose
and practice your own religion
For six years you have sacrificed
your rights as human beings
and for what?
"those to satisfy the
greed of a handful criminal"
Detection room
Shortwave received number 1 reporting
new station operating on 26.9 meters
Call themselves freedom station
Get me Capt. Muller
New station working 26.9 metres
-Capt Muller
-Yes
26.9
Right
An unauthorized broadcast is
in progress on shortwave 26.9
You are forbidden to listen
by order of the Gestapo
Bloody fool now you advertised
this to the whole nation
Get me Herr Rabenau,private number
Get me Kummer and tell
Grabner that I want him
Hello
Is that you Dressler?
Transmitting on short wave 26.9 metres
Very well Capt.I'll tell him
You know Will
I can't believe this sort of things
amuses you anymore than it does me
No but I think it's good for us
How?
It will be reminded now and then how close
we are to beasts in the field
-"The intellectual blackout is complete"
-Mitzi,Mitzi
Shut up
"All over the country children
are being taught not to think
"and not to use our intelligence"
"but repeat like parrots phrases
from a gutter full of hate"
"and yet what has hate ever
accomplished on earth"
"except evil,what can
hate beget except hate"
Dressler
This is the end of the
first freedom broadcast
"The gestapo will try to trap us
but God willing we shall
speak to you nightly
"at 1030 on shortwave 26.9"
"we shall not fail you,we are your
voice and you must be silent"
If only it worked
If only they all heard you
We shall know when we get home
Let's get us off here
That's not the point other
places haven't you got it
don't give me excuses I don't
care how you do it but do it
There you are
Fine mess you made of this,get Muller
Hello
-Is that the report on freedom radio?
-No,Sir-Get it
Tell him to wait
Where the devil have you been?
Listening to the freedom station
We know where they were roughly
Roughly?Why the blazes
why didn't you jam them out?
If we jam them,Sir,
the detectors can't find them
Well they are not rounded
up in a couple of days
your job won't allow 2 pfennigs
Our detectors can locate them in 22 seconds
We'll get them tomorrow night as
soon as they start their broadcasting
You'd better
Herr Spiedler talking
Yes,tell the Herr doctor,I rang up to
wish him many happy returns of the day
Well,would you wish Dr Roeder many
happy returns of the day from Maria
Will you wish Dr Roeder
many happy returns of the day
from his friend in East Prussia
I'll tell him Sir,but I'm sure
there is some mistake
-Oh,doctor,
-Help yourself to a drink,boys
Doctor,the telephone hasn't
stop ringing since half past ten
What do they want?
I think someone is telling a joke
They'll be calling up from
all over the country
wishing you many happy returns
I told them that it wasn't your birthday
Well,boys,all over the country
We've done it
-Doctor
-Well
-They're due to start in about a minute,Sir
As soon as they do we'll find
their position on this map
-Nagel
-Sir?
Just explain to Herr Rabenau,will you
We pick up the waves from Freedom radio
on detectors placed about 200 miles apart
For example Berlin and Breslau
By taking the maximum
intensity of these waves
each of these stations
can get the direction of the pirate station
in relations to their own position
and where these two direction intersect
is the rough position
of the pirate transmitter
How exactly do you do that?
Do you see that instrument over there,Sir
Let me explain
That's what we call a directive aerial
This man finds the direction
of maximum intensity
from the freedom station
Meanwhile we receive a reading from Breslau
by plotting both these readings on the map
as you saw obtain the point of intersection
This is the freedom station
calling on short wave 26.9
"There we are going to take up
some problems that affects us all"
-There's your blib
-Breslau bearing 95 degree east
Breslau 95 degrees West
It's someone in Ostertal district,Sir
Squad car attention stop
all traffic entering city from North
Search for radio transmitter
-About a mile northeast of Ostertahl
Ostertahl,it's about 12 miles from here
Just coming into Ostertahl
-That's the peak South 21 West 14
-South 21 West 14
North 2 West 28
We are doing everything we can Sir
I got all my best men working day and night
Karl
It's almost time
Ready to go
Right
-Ready?
-Just about
There you are Professor
This is  freedom station message
Right
This is a freedom station
calling on wavelength 26.9
I'll tell you we must find them
I had another call from
Berchtesgarden this morning
How can I find them if Goebbels
keeps jamming them out
Now we have absolute proof
that your criminal leaders are investing
millions of marks in foreign securities
Here are the figures everyone
of them has been verified
Rabenau who presumes to tell you
to turn your butter into guns
has the depositions in
the following sums abroad
Buenos Aires 7,5 million marks
in Luxemburg 2 million
That wasn't jammed was it?
Muller,you occupy a position
of responsibility
So far you've been lucky
enough to keep that position
The third Reich does not tolerate failures
I think you understand me
Well,that's the list
Something to think about isn't it?
How long are we going to put up with
this whole scale thieving of
public funds by our ministers of state
Hanna it's Karl,he's come back
What swollen dreams do
you suppose these men hold
while you at the same time
hold death and misery for you,the people
How funny
-I thought for a minute that was
-Karl
Yes
That was the freedom radio
Ridiculous
Must be some resemblance in the voice
Quite a strong resemblance I'd thought
Don't be stupid Otto
Hanna
All right duckie, I'm just getting them
Well I must be off
Aren't you going to wait for me?
I'm afraid I can't do it,
there's a job I must do
I'll be home later
All right good night
She seemed to note it at once
she actually called out his name
when she opened the door
You don't like Dr Roeder very much,do you?
It's not that,Sir,I thought it
was my duty to tell you
It was indeed
You've done very well my boy
I'm just wondering if we can't make
more use of your special advantages
What about taking him
into your detection unit,Muller
I'll be very glad to have him,Sir
Thank you,Sir
Report to Capt Muller's
office in the morning
-Heil Hitler
Well,that's a very pretty surprise
You're going to arrest Roeder?
No, we need more evidence
than to arrest the Fuhrer's doctor
besides we want the others too
I'm going to give a
little party at my house
Dr Roeder should be the guest of honor
-He'd smell a rat
-That's the idea
Suppose we ask him for 1015
just before the broadcast
-I'll ask her too
-I thought they weren't living together
They are not
Her reaction should be very entertaining
Irena it's your turn now
-Won't you please do something?
-No -Oh,please do
You really must let me off tonight
I've been at the stadium all day
What little surprise have
you got in stall for us this time
One that I think ought to be rather good
when the Fuhrer comes in a 140
foot banners were unfurl in the wind
Which reminds me really I
don't think I ordered the wind
I'll talk to Goebbels
We don't want a hurricane
you know when our good
doctors exaggerate things
There was a message from
Karl,he's been delayed at the clinic
He'll be along later
BTW the so called freedom
station is on the air just now
might be amusing to hear
what they have to say
Yes
I don't think we shall
have any more opportunities
"And tonight the minister of propaganda
has once more been telling you
that our envious neighbor
are preparing to invade Germany
and destroy her people that too is a lie"
Invented to excuse preparations "
I won't listen to that stuff
Oh quite,but there is
something about that voice
Oh yes,do let's hear
some more,it's so thrilling
Please
I'm sorry Karl missed that
As he might have found it amusing
Sorry I'm late,Willie
Oh hello Karl
Listen tomorrow
night at 10 30 as usual
Tell your friends to tune in
on wave length 26.9 meters
And in the mean time,good night
Let me help you
Thank you
Good night,Irena
Won't you see me home?
Of course
Well,there's one thing
we can take Roeder off the list
and start looking elsewhere
On the contrary we can
now concentrate on Roeder
Very easy to put a voice
on a gramophone record
but very hard to conceal the scratch
-You've been busy at the stadium?
-What? Oh,yes
-Must be very interesting
-Very
-Will you be there?
-No,I'm afraid not
I shall be busy at the clinic
Been a long time hasn't it?
Yes
Have you missed me?
What do you think?
Oh,Karl
Why do we go on like this
isn't it rather silly?
I'm not enjoying it,Irena
Can't we try again?
We've both been made miserable
for no good reason
I'd give a lot to be convinced of that
Oh,Karl,
Nothing is big enough to
make us suffer like this
it doesn't make sense
Will you go back on your belief?
The fuhrer and all he stands for?
How can I? How we agree
to differ about politics
Politics? It is something deeper than that
I feel it so strongly
Oh let's talk about something else
Oh,Karl
What ever you feel need it
stop us loving each other
As far as I am concerned it never will
That what makes it so hard
Even to talk to you
You see
I don't feel like I've the
right go back on what I've said
Even if I wanted to
Not even if I ask you
Sorry
Not even if you ask me
I see
Taxi
Pariser Platz
-Good night
Attention everyone,attention everyone
On Monday our fuhrer will speak
to us from the Tempelhof's stadium
On the peace of Europe
Every German will listen
Work will cease at six o'clock
in all factories and offices
Children will assembly in schools
Peace of Europe,80 million people
forced to listen to lies like that
You can shouting the truth
at them for seven months
and I don't suppose we'll reach 20 %
Sorry in my opinion you never will
And why not?
Because there are too many
people like you moaning
and nothing can be done
Can't see what can be done?
They like giving orders or taking
orders I know the German mentality
Damned Rudolph our fellows are German
Hans and Kurt are Germans
they are not unique
They are not many of then
Hello
I just want to tell you the
appointment this one next Friday
Thank you
What is it?
That was Wolfgang
They invade Poland on Friday
Friday
Five days
I told you,you are up
against something too big
Nothing too big
Landbach thought it was worthwhile
-Didn't stop him
-No but they broke his neck
Now listen Karl
you're doing great work as a doctor
don't throw it away
You can still lead a useful and happy life
With all this unhappiness,no Rudolph
The invasion on Friday
Peace speech on Tuesday
The whole of Germany forced to listen
The whole of Germany
I wonder
-Hello Karl
-Hello Emil,Fritz-Good evening,Sir
Got anything to drink?
I always thought stars
dressing room was full of it
-Full of what?
-Drink
Oh,Fritz get the doctor some beer,will you?
It only be your number
in a minute and quarter,Sir
I'll look after Mr Fenner,Fritz
You're always saying
what a good driver you are
Now you have an opportunity of proving it
What?
You're to be at Taeppische car park
at stadium tomorrow 5 o'clock
You mean you're actually going to try?
Why not?
That shocking stuff you're
putting on your skin
Takes ten years off my age
You know,Karl
You deserve to succeed
You put ten years on your age
if you plug up your skin with that
Coat
The moment the fuhrer starts his speech
You get your engine going
I've got your pass
Here it is
Emil,I can count on you?
Your call Mr Fenner
Right
Umbrella
Bye Karl
Heil
Heil Hitler
-What do you want?
-Last minute inspection of cables
If anything goes wrong
tonight I should lose my job
You might lose more than that
Open that bag
What's that?
A bomb what do you think?
-Heil Hitler
What's this?
Auxiliary line
Show me that box
Help
Thanks
Better tie him up
-The fuhrer
-Right
Such a magnificent arena,
I congratulate you
I must say it's looks rather good
-Where have you been?
-Sorry,Sir,I was checking up the front gates
German men and German women
"The soldier who sometimes
wear civilian clothes"
-Good luck,Karl
-Thank you,Maria
"On the ruins of the infamous
treaty of Versailles"
"A new proud Germany has arisen"
And the challenge of our
youth we'll no longer deny"
"That is the watchword of my policy"
"Peace is might"
"Peace for Germany and for...."
"That is a lie"
"This is the freedom station
calling on Short wave 26.9"
"You face the greatest
moment in your history"
"Tonight at 10 30 we shall
make a vital announcement"
"All I have time to tell you now"
"is that the fuhrer far
from working for peace"
" is about to commit you to war"
"We believe one more time.."
"War can only end with the
annihilation of Germany"
No one is allowed through here
Now get back
-Where are you going?
-Special job,Sir
No one is allowed to leave,
show me your papers
Double bend ahead,when
we get round,you jump out
No
Do as I tell you
Hello
Not yet I'm not a thought reader
You didn't see who it was
No,Sir,I had the mechanic down
and my back to the door
Whoever it was
must have been in the corridor,
you must have seen him before you went in
There was no one there,Sir
Herr Dressler will tell you,Sir
I thought you went for the main gates
Yes,Sir but I came back that way
I want you again later
Yes,Sir
Hello,hello
Muller where the devil
What?
Where about?
A street where Roeder has his clinic
Yes,we're throwing a cordon
on the entire block
Right away
Halt
Schulz,take a room in there and search it
Kalder,in there
Lt
You know Dr Roeder's private rooms?
Go around behind them and a thorough search
-take these men with you
-Come on
You'll come with me
What do you want?
I wish to see Dr Roeder at once
You can't he's with his patients
-In there
-You can't I tell you
What the devil do you mean
by bursting in here like this?
I've orders to search this building
for a wireless transmitter
This is a clinic,not a broadcasting station
Is it?
What's that?
Who are you,what do you want?
Hans
Elly
What's the matter?
What's happened?
I've been ill
I couldn't do the work
Work?
Food was so bad
I couldn't eat it
I got away
But your letters?
We only wrote what we were told
Look here,what sort of rest home was this?
It wasn't a rest home
It was a concentration camp
Concentration camp
I can't go back there,Hans
I can't go back there
Concentration camp
I'm sorry you can't go through
But I'm Frau Roeder
I can't help that but you can't go in
It's quite all right,of course,
Frau Roeder can go in
Thank you
Shall I open,Sir?
Yes go ahead
Carry on
Not at all
In difficulties?
Allow me
I had orders to search
Quite I just want to help
Here,you might call this my private museum
For instance here we have an
important part of a famous financier
Here is the nose of the
Chief Justice of Freiburg
Regrettably non Aryan
I made him a new one
Well,how do you like to
look of some of the others
I mustn't disturb you
-Everything satisfactory,Capt?
-For the present,yes
Heil Hitler
It's true
Seemed so fantastic I couldn't believe it
This afternoon the same voice
saying those vile,horrible things
Every tone,every word, told me it was you
Say something
What do you want me to say?
Why did you do it?
I did it because I had to do it
Because I saw people I
love rushing to destruction
I saw that many who felt as I
did were powerless as individuals
but if we could only find a way
to putting them in touch with each other
uniting their strength
the disaster may be averted
The freedom station the way we found
What do you want to do? Start a revolution?
Yes,revolution
You believe that Hitler is working
for peace,but you are wrong
In three days our army
will march into Poland
Then I decided to tell the nation
something of vital importance
Just as it was
I don't believe it
But it's true
Then why didn't you tell them today?
I was cut off before I could
Tonight I shall tell them
If it's the last thing I do
And it will be
You think you are brave but nothing
but a fool or worse you're a traitor
They'll kill you and you'll deserve it
You haven't a chance after this afternoon
-I saw the Gestapo outside here
-They found nothing
But what about me?
I suppose you think I'm going to
shield you because I'm your wife
No Irena I don't expect you to
Oh God
This is a nightmare
I want to wake up
Karl,what have they done to us?
Got us
everyone
I must go
Karl
Where are you going?
Please tell me I must know
Remember?
Karl,I got to talk to you
Irena there's no time now
Karl
What am I to do?
You must do what's your
conscience tells you
If you feel it's your duty
to report me I shall understand
And you know where to tell them to find me
Otto what are you doing here?
I might ask what you're doing
With the freedom radio
Don't know what you are talking about
Don't you?
I'm going straight to Gestapo headquarters
Perhaps you'll understand that
Of course,I'm going with you
You'd better not
I warn you I shall tell them the truth
I shall tell them the truth
That'll be the end of freedom radio
Don't try and fool me
Fool you?
Never once I was fooling if I
never acted well before I did then
You weren't acting
You've been crying
My dear child how many
years have I been on stage?
And you know that one of
the first thing that you learn
is to cry convincingly
As a matter of fact also one of the easiest
No one would have told me
whether we were going if
I hadn't turn on the tears
You can say what you
like you still love him
You wouldn't lift a finger against him
Love him
I hate him
He's a traitor
Played right into my hands I
know where the freedom station is
Are you coming?
Did he give yous any hint
as to where he's going?
He said he was going to Oberstad
He didn't say that
Where did he say?
He didn't mention any place
Otto couldn't have heard
we were just outside the door
that's were they've gone well that
simplifies matters a good deal
We should be able to get them all now
Well,Irena,I can't thank you enough
Dressler,stay where you are,I want you
We know of course what they
intended to say at the meeting
Of what?
Our troops about to march into Poland
They know by giving the
public a piece of news like that
they're creating immense difficulties
But it's not to,of course,we
are not attacking Poland,are we?
Yes it's true enough,it was forced on us
Naturally you'll keep all this to yourself
Of course
Thank you again,you helped us enormously
I'm very glad that I helped you,
I hope you catch them
That won't take long now
Good bye
She was lying wasn't she?
-Well I
-I see you agree with me
She is very much in love with him
I do have the well meaning
she will not get into any
That's all right I'll see that
she's kept out of it
Tell me exactly what you heard
-You say he didn't mention a name?
-No,Sir
What did he say then?
She asked him where they were going
He didn't say anything at first
Then he said something about
"Remember?"
He's knocking on something
Like that
-Like that?
-Yes,Sir
Where were you?
Right behind that door,Sir
-That one?
-Yes,Sir
Where do you think he was?
Somewhat about here
Of course I can't be sure
No,of course not
Probably the desk
Or something on it
Or perhaps
You know where this is?
Yes,Sir
That's Herr Spiedler's cottage,
we've been there often
Dear Hans make sure your transmitter
is in order in case mine breaks down
-It's all right I've just overhauled it
-Good
-Look after her
-I will
-Do you feel any better?
-I'll be all right
You know Carl I don't like this arrangement
What's wrong with it?
There's no necessity for you
to do this broadcast alone
The boys can take the boat,
I'll come with you
Oh no that won't do
you got to stay with the second
transmitter ready for tomorrow
Have you told me everything
what happened this afternoon?
Yes I think so
Why?
No one called at the clinic?
Just getting interested where you'd
been or anything like that?
My dear fellow what are you worrying about?
It never slipped up yet no
earthly reason why we should now
All you got to do is to take that
boat as far away from here as possible
It's a common sense precaution
I'll see you tomorrow as arranged
That'll be all thank you
Karl
Irena
Otto overheard us in the library
I had to go to Rabenau
pretended to give you away
I said you've gone to Oberstadt,
that was all I could think what to do
But I don't think Otto believed me
and he's been here often
Rabenau said there's going to be a war
You've been right all the time
And I've been blind
Oh,Karl
Darling,you can't stay here
I've got to make the broadcast
I'm not going away again
I'm with you now
No,it's impossible
You must take the car and I'll
meet you somewhere afterward
I can't do that
I hired one
in case they should be look out for mine
I've send it away,you see
Can't get rid of me
I am not going
No,you're not going
I wonder where's that going
It might be the Vienna express
Vienna
Budapest
Istanbul
How often have we seen
that on the side of the train
We've never got further than Vienna
We never wanted to
We didn't did we?
It's time come and help
me put up the aerial
I'm in the cottage now
No
But as soon as they start transmitting
we'll pick then up with the detectors
They can't have gone far
Report to me the moment you get them
The Chancellery is on
to me every five minutes
They will be any moment now
we'd better stay here and get
our bearings from headquarters
-Yes,Sir
-Wait for me in the car
-Finished?
-Yes
I'm glad you're here
Good luck
This is a German freedom station
calling on shortwave 26.9
" A few hours ago we told you we had news
of vital importance to each one of you"
"You may find it hard to believe"
Just coming in
There’s fatigue 97
Breslau bearing 205
"Over and over again you've been
told that democracies will not fight"
"We have certain proofs that they
will but only if you forced them to"
"All these things rest with you"
"You cannot escape responsibility
by blaming on your leaders"
"if you allow this thing to happen
"the blame is yours and you will
earn the loathing of posterity"
"You gave this man his power"
-Switch on the speakers
"Your future is at stake,
your lives are at stake"
"It is through actions united
and courageous actions"
" that from our hearts we
appeal you tonight"
Open these doors
Get down
"Do not deceive yourselves
that nothing could be done"
"and let you act now"
I give you five seconds to
stop this broadcasting,come out
"Unless you act now your
chances are gone forever"
"No man or woman who loves
the fatherland or fights his liberty"
"can afford to stand aside,rise
up and make our stand for freedom"
"make ourselves hard before"
Karl
"Did you hear that was
the death of a brave man"
"he died for freedom and for Germany"
Come and have it again
No,no
"You have heard the last broadcast
of the so called freedom station"
"Those responsible for the
outrage have been silenced"
Give me the Chancellery on the telephone
"This is the Freedom station
calling on wavelength 26.9 meters"
"we shall be broadcasting tomorrow
night at our usual time 10 30"
"That is all for tonight"
Subtitles by Nostromo