I WANTED WINGS
Based on a Story by
ELEOANORE GRIFFIN and FRANK WEAD
From the Book
I WANTED WINGS by
LIEUT. BEIRNE LAY. JR.
This production was actally filmed
at Randolph Kelly and March Fields.
The splendid colaboration of
the Unied States Army Air Corps
is gratefully acknowledged.
BIRTHPLACE OF MANS WINGS, AMERICA
TODAY WATHES HER SKY WITH GRAVE CONCERN.
FOR IN THESE SKIES OF PEACE NATION IS
BUILDING THE UPPER BATTLEMENTS OF ITS DEFENSE.
TO THE OFFICERS AND MAN
OF THE UNITED STATES ARMY AIR CORPS
WHO CLIMB ON STRONG WINGS
TO MAN THESE HIGH RAMPARTS.
AND TO THE YOUNG MEN OF AMERICA
WHO WILL TAKE THEIR PLACES BESIDE THEM,
THIS MOTION
PICTURE IS DEDICATED.
This is Ranger Station 58.
18 bombers.
Altitude estimated 15.000.
Course southwest.
Now directly overhead.
This is Mojave.
Yeah, Mojave.
A big bunch of planes
are flying over here.
They're going like San Hill
and headed for Los Angeles. Yeah.
Okay.
Anti aircraft companies.
Battery B. 52nd Monterrey.
Duarte at command.
27 heavy bombers passing over here.
And estimated altitude 12.000.
Changing course from south to east.
Warning net command to
Battery B. 52nd Monterrey.
Message received. Okay.
Wanting net command
23rd Pursuit Squadron. Go ahead.
Warning net command to
Battery A. Morrow Bay.
Repeat message, please.
38th reconnaissance
to warning net command.
Large enemy formation
just sighted over Palm Springs.
Southbound attackers estimated
over Santa Barbara in 12 minutes, sir.
Headed directly for Los Angeles.
- That's my ground speed. 2-6-0.
Transmit enemy positions in course to
all pursuit squadrons and antiaircraft units.
Order 38. The reconnaissance
squadron maintain contact
with enemy formation over Palm Springs.
Blackout immediately.
- Yes, sir.
Turn your boys loose with
their sirens, Chief. - Yes, sir.
On the roof of the municipal building,
we're bringing you  an eye-witness account
of the first simulated
air raid upon Los Angeles.
Below us are the glittering
lights of a great city.
At play and at peace.
Men and women are...
There go the blackout sirens now.
Turn out your lights.  Pull down your blinds.
Automobiles, please
switch off your headlights.
Stand by your radios
for further instructions.
Los Angeles is now rapidly blacking out.
You there.
In the drugstore.
Turn off that neon sign.
Turn off your headlights, Mac.
35th Pursuit Squadron reporting.
Successful interception
effective westbound formation.
We estimate all enemy units will
converge on Los Angeles in eight minutes.
Order all remaining pursuit
squadrons up to intercept. - Yes, sir.
The attacking bombers are reported
approaching the city from many directions.
Parachute troops are
being dropped on the outskirts.
Here come the bombers now.
You can probably hear them.
There go the pursuit planes.
Here comes the attack now.
And believe you me, we can be
thankful the explosions are up there.
And that they're not real bombs.
The raid is over.
The lights blink on again.
Once more of the city
takes up the tempo of normal life.
No homes have been shattered.
No fires sweep the gutted
streets of a murdered city.
No terror or sorrow fills the
upturned lives of helpless civilians.
For the United States is at peace.
But these realistic maneuvers
are a convincing guarantee.
That American soldiers and
citizens alike intend to be prepared.
We return you now to our main studio.
One moment please. We have a bulletin here.
An Army Flying Fortress bomber
en route back from maneuvers
is reported to have crashed
in the desert. North of Marsh Field.
And here is another bulletin.
The fate of the crew is not yet known.
And officials refuse to
comment on the unconfirmed report
that a woman was found
dead in the wrecked plane.
Charge one.
Violation of the 84th Article of War.
Specification.
In that Jefferson Young,
second lieutenant, Air Corps.
Having received a lawful
command from Capt. Everett Mercer,
Air Corps,
his superior officer,
not to attempt to take off from
the scene of an emergency landing
in a Flying Fortress airplane,
did near Spring Canyon, California,
willfully disobey the same.
With the result that injuries
were sustained by the crew.
A passenger was killed.
And the airplane destroyed.
Charge two.
Violation of the 96th Article of War.
Specification. In that Jefferson
Young, second lieutenant, Air Corps,
did at Marsh Field, California,
admit an unauthorized passenger,
one Sally Vaughn, on
board a Flying Fortress airplane.
In violation of existing regulations.
And to the prejudice of
good order and military discipline.
How does the accused plead
to Specification Charge One?
Guilty, sir.
What is the plea to
Specification Charge Two?
Guilty, sir.
- That's not true, sir.
Any further interruption
will necessitate your removal
from the courtroom. Sit down.
You have no further statement?
- No, sir. - Court will be closed.
Let me see the
record of the accused.
You must be crazy.
- Aw, skip it, Al.
You're fixing yourself up for good.
- Let me take care of that.
Guess I must be seeing things.
I thought I saw Carolyn. - Listen, Jeff.
I'm not going to let you
toss out your job for my sake.
I'm gonna go in and
tell 'em the whole story.
One chirp out of you and I'll
break your neck. - Well, gentlemen.
Here's the record.
Jefferson Young the 3rd.
Lawrenceville Preparatory School.
Yale University.
Applied for Air Corps training
and was admitted to Randolph Field
two years ago this spring.
RANDOLPH
FIELD
CADETS WILL NOT USE
EAST END OF PARKING LOT
Give me your attention.
Down here at Randolph,
they don't care who you
are, or where you come from.
The Army is only
interested in two things.
Can you fly?
Will you make an officer?
And they'll find out.
And we upperclassmen
will try to help you learn,
what we've learned
in the last four months.
Before you report to the flight
surgeon for a physical recheck,
take a look at the man
on either side of you.
Go ahead. Take a good look.
In four months, one
of you won't be here.
Report to your
squad leaders. Dismissed.
One out of three washed out.
You two ought to toss a coin to
see which one he's talking about.
Oh, he's talking about me.
Regulations say you can't be over 6'2".
That's just what
I was when I enlisted.
But I grew a half-inch
waiting to be admitted.
Good morning.
The boys will be
out flying pretty soon.
You scared of flying?
No, sir.
Scared of not flying.
I know just how you
feel. I'm Colonel Riley.
First man to go
up in a free balloon.
1879. Went up on
half an hour's notice.
All they told me
was to drop sandbags.
And I dropped them.
Floated 800 miles in five days.
When I gave my report
to President Ulysses S. Grant.
I said the air.
The air is the thing.
It's here to stay.
- I hope I stay with it.
Well, son. If you run
into a stall, just call on me.
I've been giving the Army
expert advice on training
young pilots for the last 40 years.
Hello, Sandbag.
- Hello.
Aren't you a new
cadet, mister? - Yes, sir.
You're supposed to be the hospital
taking a physical recheck. Aren't you?
Yes, sir.
- Weill, take off.
I'm going to dress down
that young upstart for not saluting me.
That's all, young man.
- Yes, sir.
Song you got the makings
of an officer and a gentleman.
Thank you, sir.
Hey, you better quit stalling.
And get over the flight surgeon's
office for that recheck. - I'm going.
You f- Why not?
Nothing the matter with us.
- You sure are lucky.
I don't smoke. I don't drink.
I don't break training for four years.
And what happens? I'm overgrown.
You know, I had the same trouble.
Till I find out if you stand
at attention for a while.
And jump up and down, you can
maybe jog a half inch off. - Yeah?
Sure. Jockeys do it all the time.
Do you mean like this?
- Yeah, only higher.  Oh.
Well, fancy that.
Say, uh, uh.
Ludlow. Al Ludlow.
- Cassidy.
He's a polo player.
- So what?
J. Y.? Oh, yeah.
Jeff Young the 3rd.  Eight goals.
He's filthy rich, Ludlow.
- 8 goals and 8 mission bucks.
Is that the way they rate him?
- Say, tell me, Young.
What is a tough guy like
you want down here anyway.
Here's a good place to find
out fast just how tough you are.
Oh, well, I don't have to find out.
That this is what they gave me for
being the toughest guy in the Big Ten.
Too bad they don't have
cheerleaders down here. - Yeah.
Yeah.
And here's the shoe
that kicked the winning field
goal against Notre Dame last year.
When you get back
from the flight surgeon's,
I want to show you my baby
pictures. Aw, swell. - If you get back.
Yeah.
Well, come on, baby.
Bounce. Bounce. - Oh.
Oh yeah. I wish I'd
known about this before.
I could have been doing
it in the train coming down.
I see where it's going to be awful
noisy sleeping in the Hall of Fame.
Say, Ludlow.
What did you do
before you came here?
I was a mechanic.
Worked in garages.
Airplane factories.
Sold.
I tried just about everything.
Well, uh, where'd you get
your two years college equivalent?
Trade school? - Never
stayed long enough one place.
I got a satchel full of diplomas
from correspondence schools.
What brought you
down here? - I want to fly.
As it would be.
Say, uh. They really wouldn't wash a
man out for a half an inch, would they?
Sonny, down here, they
wash you out for a bad haircut.
Turn around.
Straighten up.
- Oh, yes, sir.
Ohh.
What are plans after
you graduate, Cassidy?
Oh, applying for a commission.
Get a job with an airline,
maybe. - I suppose that...
You mean I pass?
You mean I'm only 6'2"?
You're six-two and a half.
But since you added
the extra half-inch after you enlisted,
I guess it's on the Army.
But don't grow anymore.
Our airplanes don't
stretch. - Aw, I won't, sir.
I mean I won't, sir.
Ha, I passed. I passed!
My clothes.
I forgot my clothes, sir.
What's the matter? Don't you like your
mechanic's outfit,  Mr. Jeff Young the 3rd?
Hey, I'm in!
Hey, fellas. I'm in!
I made it!
Hey, 82, out, 82, 54, hike!
That's the play
that made me famous.
Taking out two
guys at the same time.
As you were.
What? Where do you misters
think you are? At a freshman rally?
This is the Army. We expect
you to act  in a military manner.
Size?
13. - 13? That'll have
to be special issue.
Left face.
Right face.
About face.
- Right face.
Right face.
- Left face.
Forward, march.
- To the rear, march.
Left - - March.
Left... March.
Right, march.
Good day.
You're turning too fast. Don't forget
air speed until you stall into a spin.
Now recover from
your spin and try it again.
Be seated.
Take off at will.
What's the matter,
mister. You sick?
No, uh. No, sir.
I made a terrible mistake.
What's that, mister? - I thought
they taught you to fly down here, sir.
They do. You'll meet your
flying instructor tomorrow.
Oh, swell.
Cadet Young, sir.
Cadet Ludlow, sir.
- Cadet Cassidy, sir.
Cadet Masters, sir.
- Cadet Wilcox, sir.
Now we'll drop all that.
I want you to relax.
This is an airplane. I'm going
to teach you to fly one, I hope.
This is the ship will start out on.
So let's climb aboard
and look her over.
I'll tell you everything
I know about it.
All I ask is your strict attention.
I expect you to make mistakes.
But don't make excuses.
That's the stick.
That controls things.
You move it forward,
your nose goes down.
You pull it back,
your nose comes up.
These instruments and controls look
complicated. But a week from now, they won't.
Your flight instruments are
in the center. Bank and turn.
Air speed.
Rate of climb and altimeter.
All right.
Any questions?
Good. You, Young.
I'll take you first.
All we do this morning is
to shake hands with flying.
Begin to feel at home in the plane.
Get familiar with the sky.
Get into your chute.
Buckle your belt.
All right, Young.
Follow me on the controls.
Lightly. Lightly. We're flying.
Not hauling a load of cement.
You may be good enough
to come this close, Cassidy.
But I'm not.
Get off the roller coaster,
will you, Ludlow?
Confound it, Ludlow.
Hold your speed constant.
If you're gonna dive her in,
dive her in.
If you're gonna stall her in,
stall her in. But don't vacillate.
You can't learn accuracy
without a constant glide.
Land shorter this time.
Stop using the whole field.
Fly the airplane, Ludlow.
Don't let the airplane fly you.
Here come Al and Mercer.
One.
Two.
Three.
Four.
It ought to scramble those eggs
Mercer had for breakfast. - Yeah.
Hey, Jimmy. Chalk up a
buck against Mr. Ludlow.
Four stars coming up.
Your Ludlow is way out ahead
in the Dumbbell Derby.
Oh, what difference does it
make how good or bad you are.
They don't set us
up to for solo. - Yeah.
Well, maybe they're going
to wash out the whole battalion.
Hey! Hey!
As you were, mister.
As you were.
Oh, hey. Four stars.
Pay up a dollar for the kitty.
I'll pay you up in the room.
- Okay.
We ought to make
you a wholesale price.
You use too much rudder on a left turn,
you feel the wind on your right cheek.
You don't even it up,
you feel it on the other cheek.
What am I doing here anyway?
This is no place for a dumb mechanic.
Don't take that attitude, Al.
Shucks, I'm dumb too but.
What the heck
you can't buck nature.
Young.
- Yeah.
On the line. Right away.
Solo.  - Okay.
Got it?
- Huh?
Jeff's gonna solo.
Hey, fellas, Jeff's gonna solo!
Jeff's gonna solo!
Break the ice.
- Fly the pants off that thing.
We're rooting for you.
- Don't hog me, boys.
Give me air, will ya?
- Don't think too much.
Just relax.
- Go out there and show 'em.
Give 'em the old power play right through
center. And remember, keep your head.
Don't worry about me.
All I got to do is this.
Climb a little faster. And glide a
little further. - Don't get nervous.
I'm not nervous.
- No.
What do you got that flying suit
on backwards for then? - Huh?
Come on. Let him do it by
himself. He's a big boy now.
Gimme the other arm.
What are you thinking about?
- Young.  - Yes, sir.
Come on, Young. You're going out
to solo. Not to get married. - Yes, sir.
Good luck, Jeff.
- Thanks.
Ya.
Boy oh boy.
Flier.
- Mickey.
Oh, would you mind? You're
casting a shadow in my reflector.
What's the matter? Haven't
you ever seen a bomber before?
Never with landing gear like that.
Aren't you making kind of free
with that camera around an Army Post?
Look. I'm trying to
make a series of pictures.
For a national magazine.
With full permission and cooperation
of the United States Army.
We'll set up over there for the next
few pictures. - Okay, Miss Bartlett.
Bartlett. Bartlett. Bartlett.
Oh.
See here. Carolyn Bartlett. I know you.
Photography's dynamic
symmetry girl, yes.
Kansas corn silos.
Steam turbines.
Private eyes on the blast
furnace, sure. - Yes.
And I must say I find you even
more interesting than Junior Bergman.
Oh, no no. As you were.
- Hey, dopey.
You're in clover.
She likes class poses.
You know her?
- Do I know her?
Come here.
Miss Bartlett. I'd like
you to meet Mr. Cassidy.
How do you do?
- How are you?
Can I help?
- At what?
Yes. Would you like to
hold my reflector for me?
Oh, yes, ma'am. Here.
- Mickey, give it to Mr. Cassidy.
And get my other camera,
will you? - Okay, Miss Bartlett.
Hang it over here.
Now there you are.
A little more.
Come on. Some more.
Now that's fine.
Now you just hold it there.
Cassidy.
Cassidy!
Here, sir.
Hold that, will ya?
Now's your chance
to get a picture of some real flying.
My instructor can't wait
to get in the plane with me.
It gives him a chance to
catch up on his sleep. Oof.
You know it surprises me every
time that guy gets off the ground.
Really? He seems
rather capable to me.
Yes, sir.
- You're wasting time.
You stand by to meet the ship when
you're scheduled next. - Yes, sir.
In the back.
Take me out to a practice area and
show me some improvement. - Yes, sir.
Cassidy.
Your progress is a fair average.
You're a little bit on the cocky side.
Just in case your head is getting a
little bit too big for your buttocks.
I'm going to show you a couple of things
that you'll have to learn very soon.
This first is what we call a slow roll.
Check your belt.
Okay, sir.
Stop.
All right, Cassidy.
Climb back to 3000 feet.
We'll do it again and you'll
follow me through on the control.
I said climb her back to 3000 feet.
Lt. Clankton speaking.
- Hello.
Flying Cadet Cassidy wishes to report
he just fell out of an airplane, sir.
All right.
What?!
You men who have soloed are
starting to feel like pretty hot pilots.
During the past week
several minor violations
of flying regulations have cropped up.
One pretty serious one.
So go easy on trains.
Cattle.
Individual combat.
And outside loops.
That's all.
Cassidy.
Cassidy!
- Oh, yes, sir.
Stay with us, will ya?
- Yes, sir.
It's a good thing that big
dumbbell's a natural born flier.
You men that haven't soloed it yet.
I'd like to offer you a little tip.
The Army has just
so much time to devote
to finding out whether
each of you is a flier or not.
So make every minute in the air count.
That's all.
Ludlow.
I want to see you a minute.
Would you say that
I know my business?
I think so around here, sir.
And why am I losing out with a man
that's got everything
it takes to make a flier?
What's on your mind,
Ludlow? Family?
Money?
Women?
Just tell me I'm through, sir.
I can take it.
Why don't you forget her?
I don't know what you're
talking about, sir. - I think I do.
I can't forget her. I keep seeing her
the way she was  the night we busted it up.
I keep hearing
her say you're a flop.
You'll never be anything
but a $15 a week grease monkey.
I was sore too. I told her
to beat it and she went.
And with another guy.
She said she was
going places. And she will.
The quickest way she can.
After that, I threw off
my job and pulled out.
Things weren't going
to be going so well.
So I kept telling myself.
It's just bad breaks.
But after a while I began to
wonder. Maybe it was me.
I always wanted to fly.
That's one of the reasons
I joined the Air Corps.
But it was more than that, sir.
You see I have to know about myself.
If I wash out, then she's right.
I never told that to anybody, sir.
Suppose she is right.
I know a lot of swell guys that
are $15 a week grease monkeys.
Now the trouble with you is
that you're trying too hard.
Relax.
Stop tensing up.
It's part of learning to fly.
The big part.
I know that, sir.
- Ludlow. Look.
Fliers are just like all other men.
And they fall into
the same two groups.
Those that women have made happy.
Those that women
have made unhappy.
But whether they're
lucky that way or not.
They just keep plugging along
at their job like everybody else does.
Now if you can't forget
this girl, don't.
Stop trying. But get
this through your head.
You can still make a whale of a flier.
Ludlow.
I'm sending you up for a check ride
with a flight commander tomorrow.
I've told him I thought
you'd make a pilot.
I still think so.
Now don't make a monkey out of me.
Catastrophic instability is
a characteristic of an aircraft,
which having deviated from level flight
tends to increase the deviation.
Look, Jeff.
I've soloed, haven't I?
Now why do I
have to learn this junk?
You want to know what you're
doing, don't you? - Hey Jeff?  - Yeah.
You're want over at
Lt. Roger's office right away.
Ha, he must need
some expert advice.
Cadet Young reporting, sir.
Perhaps you know about Miss Bartlett's
presence at the post, Young. - Yes, sir.
She's looking for someone
to photograph as the average cadet here.
You've been selected.
- Who? Me, sir?
You will cooperate with Miss Bartlett
whenever it doesn't
interfere with your duties.
Miss Bartlett is a very charming girl.
It was nice of her to select me.
But Miss Bartlett didn't
select you. The Army did.
I came down here to
be a flier, sir. Not a model.
Did you ever see any
of those screwy pictures she takes?
Mr. Young, we didn't call you
here to give a class as an art critic.
This is official.
- Yes, sir.
I'm so sorry to
trouble you, Mr. Young.
It's no trouble at all.
Now would you mind
stepping over by the window?
Hmm. Turn your
profile into the light.
A bit afraid of the mouth.
And the line of the jaw there.
Oh, dear.
What do you think, Mickey?
Lean over so he can see.
I don't think the chin's gonna do it.
What was the name of the cadet
with you yesterday?
Cassidy.
I really feel it that Cadet Cassidy
might be more suitable.
That's all, Young.
Send Cadet Cassidy over.
Yes, sir.
Now look, dopey.
Catastrophic instability
is the characteristic
of an aircraft
which having deviated from...
Hey, I think I got it now.
Catastrophic... - Yeah.
What's the matter?
Maybe I'm crazy.
- What's the matter?
They want you over at
the public relations office right away.
Masters, would you take
this Greek god to Ronson's office.
But don't chip the profile.
Come on. Hurry up.
They're waiting for you.
The Lady of the Lens
is on the loose. - Oh.
Ohh! Lady of the Lens? Ha, ha.
Come on, professors.
Come on.
He's going to be
the great lover of the Air Corps.
Roll up your flaps, will ya?
That's nice talk to a hot pilot.
You're in a class all by yourself,
aren't you? - That's what they tell me.
Just watch me up there for a
while and maybe you'll solo too.
Aw, come on, Al.
Put it in the hanger.
Gimme those.
I told you to lay off.
Hey, you can't quit now.
I'm on the deck.
Ludlow.
Break it up. Break it up.
You're supposed to be
a gentleman down here, Ludlow.
You're not in the garage now. - You
don't have to tell me where I belong.
Or what I'm going back to.
But before I go, I...
Lucky he caught you, mister.
They wash you out fast down here
for striking an upperclassman.
Now what's this all about?
Who started it? - I did, sir.
We had a little argument.
I got sore and I popped him.
I don't blame him for losing his head.
- You report to the orderly room
with proper uniform to walk
a punishment tour. - Yes, sir.
You stuck your neck out, mister.
But you're in enough trouble.
We'll skip it this time.
That's all.
You don't have to take any
wraps for me. - I'm a real chump.
I hate to see anybody get washed out
before they had a chance to do
what they came down here for.
What's the difference? They'll send
me up in the washing machine tomorrow.
I'm sorry I put the rib on.
I know just how you feel.
That's a laugh.
How can you know?
You've never been in
a storm in your life. - No?
I've been in a storm
ever since I came here.
Every time I walk
down that flying line.
And see those faces,
they nearly drive me nuts.
300 guys all daring Jeff Young the
3rd to be as good as Joe Doakes.
I never figured you
were afraid of anything.
I tell you something else.
The louder I talk,
the more scared I am.
That's strictly
between you and me.
Here.
Try wearing these tomorrow.
They were lucky for me.
Keep swinging, Al.
You still gotta chance.
Now watch me talk
as I'm out walking the tour.
Would you look up please?
Thank you.
Can you suggest any other
points of interest, Mr. Cassidy?
Ludlow. You're next.
It's gonna seem funny
not getting in with these anymore?
What are you talking about?
The seat of those pants will be worn
out before you turn that chute in.
Yeah, I'm not kidding myself.
I picked Grady.
Collins.
Anderson.
When they send you up in the washing
machine, it's a one-way ticket home.
The flight commander's
ready for you now, Ludlow.
Come on. Climb in.
I can't do it.
I know I'm through.
Why do they have to drag it out?
You're not through.
So why lie down and quit?
I'm not a quitter.
I know when I'm licked.
Give me out of this thing.
You report to that flying line if I have
to smack you down and carry you there.
You came here to fly.
You're gonna fly.
Now dump that flight commander into
the ship and ride the pants off him.
Come on.
Hey fellas, congratulate me. They
just passed me on my...  pylon eight.
What's the matter with him?
- Only bad news out there.
The worst.
- Yep.
Did you hear him cry on his
pillow last night? He's a funny guy.
Yeah, you're funny too.
Like a wing breaking off.
What did I say?
- Oh, shut up.
Cadet Ludlow reporting, sir.
Ludlow.
Before I send you up
to the flight commander,
I want you to take
the ship up alone. - Alone?
You heard me.
He's going up solo.
Come on, Al.
Allah, be merciful.
He's in trouble.
Takeoff. There's a BT in trouble
beyond the south end of the field.
My motor's conked.
Get the nose down.
Get it down.
Gotta keep flying speed.
Pick a field and relax.
There's one.
No good.
It's downwind.
Find another one quick.
Only got 400 feet.
Come on. I can get in that one.
Turn now.
Don't change your mind.
Turn.
Relax.
Loosen up.
That field's small. Have to
cut those treetops and fish later.
Cut in a little soon
now and stay high.
You can kill altitude. But you can't
get it back without your motor.
Keep flying speed and relax.
Now fishtail her.
Still too fast.
Once more.
That's better.
Okay. Level out.
Drop her in.
Don't dive at the ground.
Careful. Careful.
Don't hit those trees.
You have to switch before you
hit. Maybe I can ground loop her.
Hit that left brake.
Hit it.
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
Are you all right?
- Sure.
Okay, was it?
What happened, Ludlow?
Motor conk out on you?
Yes, sir. - You got plenty of
gas and the valve is turned on.
It must have been a vapor lock.
Well, we can fly her out of
here. We'll have to truck her.
I don't know how you got her
in here without a shoe horn.
Well, Ludlow. Now you see the value of
knowing  how to make a short approach.
Yes, sir.
Not a scratch.
Is this a student you were going
to send up for a wash-out ride?
What wash-out ride?
That's Navy stuff.
Dunking the last guy to solo.
I never heard of them doing it down here.
- Course you didn't. I just made it up.
Scrap this.
Nice going, Al. Nice going.
That's setting her down on the dime, Al.
- Congratulations, boy. You really did it.
How is Number One?
- Thanks.
They turned the trick.
- Go ahead. Keep him.
That landing was one for the record, Al.
- And they used to call  him "knucklehead."
Yeah!
- Store's closing.
Checking off this reservation to spend
our first weekend in San Antonio.
We're gonna pop all the beer joints.
Oh, gee. I can't go
with you. I got a date.
Oh, gosh. I'm late now.
Go get my suit creased.
Ah, ha ha ha.
Now do you understand
catastrophic instability? - Yes.
Ha ha ha.
Don't forget this war dance
is on me. - We'll settle that later.
Oh, no. I just drew a
month's pay. 75 bucks.
I'm showing you the bright lights.
How many please?
- Two please. - Two?
Si.
- Hey, look.
The center throws
me the ball back.
And I get it and I tuck
it underneath my arm.
Let's break up the whole
thing. - I'm right on your tail.
Well, well. A woman's
work is never done.
What pose is this?
Life-like flying cadet?
Occasionally, I come out of my
darkroom and see Al. - That's fine.
Do you mind if we try to
liven up the party? - Not at all.
Now, waiter.
Two chairs please.
Yes, sir. Coming right up, sir.
Oh, excuse me.
Miss Bartlett, this is Mr. Ludlow.
The hottest pilot in the class.
- How do you do?  - How do you do?
Mr. Cassidy was just telling
me the most fascinating story.
Do go on, Mr. Cassidy.
Oh, yes, about the time he had
the ball on the two-yard line.
Skull fractured. - No. No,
it wasn't a fractured skull.
It was a broken rib.
- Oh, that's right. How silly of me.
Quiet, please.
- You see he's tired.
Irritable. Overworked.
Overexposed.
Look. How about my
having this next dance?
Certainly. If you can find
someone to dance with you.
Ha, ha, ha, ha.
- Oh.
# I love is hungry for a chance.
# Of romance.
# For I was born to love.
They ought to put that
on the menu. - Yeah.
How'd you like to
meet her? - Oh, no.
You just wait here and I'll show you
how it's done. Excuse me.  - Certainly.
Jeff.
# To be true.
# They insist.
# For I was born to love.
# If I could find just the one I belong.
# I would call it a day.
# Get him to stay.
# And then get older and it's gone.
# And gone.
# My love would be a lovely thing.
# How'd I sing.
# For I was born to love.
Shall we?
Darling, I never
dance with a customer.
If you dance with me, I'll put
you in the Air Corps. - Fine.
I don't think I'm
the type for wings.
Oh, I think so.
Say, who are you?
- Jeff Young.
Now I know you're crazy.
So. It's fourth down. We got
98 yards to go for a touchdown.
Now then.
Should I play safe and kick or
should I take a chance and run?
I said, should I kick or run?
Well, how many men on base?
No.
Strictly speaking, behind that
guy's back, he's kind of conceited.
Yeah, certainly.
Tom, would you like to dance?
- Hmm. Yeah.
Are you really Jefferson Young?
Just Jeff to you please.
You don't look like your pictures.
I'm sorry you're
disappointed. I'm not.
You look just like you should.
Got me all figured out,
haven't you? - Yes, I think so.
Smarter than I am. I never
know what I'm gonna do next.
Oh, Miss Bartlett.
I'd like you to meet Miss uh...?
Vaughn. - Miss Vaughn. - How do you
do? You sang beautifully, miss Vaughn.
Thank you.
Who's that cutting in on your girl?
Oh, that's uh that's Tom Cassidy.
My girl?
Who says she's my girl?
She does.
With her eyes.
Aww. You're way off your course.
My life would be a lovely thing.
How I'd cling.
But I was born to love.
No. Really?
Say, Al. I'd like you
to meet Miss Vaughn.
She was born to love.
Mr. Ludlow.
- How do you do?
You two dance together.
I have to make a separate pass.
Hello, Al.
- Hello, Sally.
Well. That's a warm welcome.
Layoff, Sally.
It started all over down here.
Why'd you follow me for?
- Don't flatter yourself.
I'm down here with the band.
Okay, Al, if that's how it is.
That's how it is.
You messed up my life once.
That's enough.
- Don't worry.
I struggled along without you. I just
hope you find what you're looking for.
Is that really Jeff Young the 3rd?
Don't waste your time, Sally.
He's way out of your league.
Think so?
Is that you, Tom?
Tom, can't make it today.
The average young American is
boning for navigation quiz.
But if I can be of any help,
I'd only be too glad to.
Provided you don't shoot
around the chin.
Thanks. I think I have
about everything I need.
You mean you're finished?
- Mm-hmm. - Then what do you do?
Go home. - Where is that?
- San Antonio. - No kidding? Really?
That's fine. I'll be
over Saturday afternoon.
You'll find me
photographing some bananas.
I'm going to
Guatemala City tomorrow.
Guatemala City?
I wish I'd known you were leaving.
I'd been a little more... well I uh...
Yes?
- Uh.
You got my pictures
yet, young woman?
Yes. They're over here, colonel.
Why don't you
take off in a balloon?
They're excellent.
Creeping up on the enemy.
They won't be dry til
tomorrow. - Well, I can wait.
Oh.
- What's that?
I have to take some negatives out.
Well, be careful.
No light in here.
Hey, ever tell you about the time the
Comanches were surrounding Fort Conner?
No. - I spotted
them in my balloon.
And down I come on
them raining sandbags.
You know, colonel. I hear there's a
full dress review on the parade grounds.
Really? - Mm-hmm. - Well, somebody
ought to tell about these things.
I can't keep a whole
army waiting. - No.
Bye.
Look. Do you have
to go to Guatemala?
Just working girl, you know.
I have to go where they send me.
What's Cassidy doing in
that one? - This one isn't Cassidy.
I don't remember seeing him
around here. - You ought to know him.
You see him everyday.
He's no glamor boy.
His ears are too big.
But he'll make a
magazine cover, just the same.
That's a good face.
A good home-made tough face.
There's a lot of moxie there.
You'll never see this baby
goose-stepping in a colored
shirt with his arm outstretched.
Quite a guy.
What's his name?
Yankee. Joe Yankee.
He's a composite of a lot
of the cadets down here.
They didn't have my chin.
Might be.
- It was a funny thing.
I've got a composite
picture too. A girl.
Miss America.
In the green smock.
Always got her hand in hypo
solution. Knows all the angles.
And waits for the benefits.
- That's rather cute.
Can I kiss you?
Mm-hmm.
- Mmm.
Oh, darn. And every time I try to have
a good time in this Army, a bell rings.
Grr.
Ohh.
- Well, I...
Say, that's fine, Mercer.
Congratulations. - Thanks.
I'm turning my students over
to you. You know most of them.
Ludlow.
Wilcox.
Young.
Front and center.
Lt. Hopkins is going to be
your flying instructor from now on.
I didn't know you
were leaving us, sir.
He's just been named
Flight Commander.
Congratulations, sir. - Thank you.
- We'll miss you, sir.  - Thanks.
Congratulations. - Thank you.
Cassidy and Masters are still upstairs.
They'll probably be in in a minute.
Hey, look out!
Get down.
Get out of there. Clear
the ship before it explodes.
Get going. Come on,
you men in that trash truck.
Bring those extinguishers in here.
What do you think killed the motor?
Cover the gas tank.
Here's another gas tank.
Easy, fellas.
- Let him rest.
Are you coming around?
You're okay, buddy. Take it easy.
I'm sorry.
- It's all right, man.
Sorry. - Sorry for what?
For avoiding a collision?
For saving another man's life?
How about you? Are you all right?
- My hand's just a little burned.
Young. Take Ludlow over to the hospital.
Have them take care of those hands.
Thanks.
- I'm all right.
All right. Come on.
Oh, nothing very serious. They'll
be all right  in a couple of days.
Go ahead. Say it.
You know I let you pull
Masters out alone. They all know it.
Now what are you talking
about? I just got there first.
Sure. You just got there first.
Couldn't find him. - He came
back here for about five minutes.
Changed into his civilian clothes.
And left. - Did he say anything?
Yeah. It doesn't
make sense though.
I hand him a couple
letters from Guatemala.
Addressed to Jeff Young
the 3rd just as plain as day.
So he says he isn't the guy
that they were written to.
And he tears them up and
throws them in the wastebasket.
You didn't save me the stamps.
Come on.
Get me your laundry.
All present.
Good night.
Where do you think
you're going? - Into town.
Don't be a dolt. Why
stick your neck out too?
I got to find him.
That guy's in a real storm.
# My love would be a lovely thing.
# Promising.
# For I was born to love.
Hello.
That.
Now I know why I came down
here. - What took you so long?
I was trying to be a flier.
But you won't be if they catch
you down here on a weekday night.
Eh, let 'em catch me.
I'm through.
I'm no Joe Yankee.
- Who?
If I want to fly, I'll buy a blimp.
You can buy anything
you want. - Yeah.
Anything but wings.
Look. Stick with
me tonight, will you?
Don't leave me alone.
Come on.
Let's get out of here.
Johnnie, tell the boss I'm
leaving early tonight. - Yes, ma'am.
Well. Isn't it kind of late for
you to go around ringing doorbells?
They told me at the Colonnade,
Jeff is with you. - Eh.
Well, if it isn't old Al.
Take a seat, cadet. Take a seat.
Have anything on the house.
Nothing's too good for a hero.
Joe Yankee.
The hero of the day.
Or will it be wave my
hanky, wave, wave, wave?
Ever hear of Joe Yankee?
He's kind of a cross between
Sir Galahad and and Daniel Boone.
He's full of moxie.
- We'll talk about that tomorrow.
Right now, you're going
back with me. - Oh, no, I'm not.
Sally and I are taking
a little trip tomorrow.
She isn't looking for Joe again.
Jeff Young is good enough
for her. - Plenty good enough.
Yes.
New Orleans.
Sun Valley. Mexico City.
That's it. Mexico City.
See the world while it's still here.
Sal.
Here's to us.
Ice.
For my drink.
Not my head.
Lay off him.
You're getting what you want
down here.- You want his dough.
I couldn't be on the level, could I?
You never were with me.
Tell him to go back to the field.
You must think I'm crazy.
I'm always wanted to
go to Mexico. - Listen.
How long do you think it
would last? Jeff's no dope.
What happens when he
sobers up and find you there?
A cheap little gyp
with her hooks in him.
You tried that once before
and got into a lot of trouble.
Now tell him to go back to
the field or I'll spill. - Just try it.
Colder than a well digger's ice box.
Jeff.
- Have some flask.
Let's dance.
- Jeff.
You better run along before
you get any more trouble.
Why don't ice cubes come
in single packs instead of in litters?
Jeff, did you hear me?
- Yes, I heard you.
We're taking off for Mexico. And
planes don't leave from Randolph.
Let's wait until you can fly me there.
I'm no flier. That's Al's department.
He's got it. And I haven't.
- Don't make me laugh.
Come on. It's getting
pretty late. - Oh.
So you're running
out on me, huh?
You're one of these
hot and cold propositions.
I'm not running out on you,
Jeff, honey. I'll be waiting around.
I can tell you really don't want to
break away now. You wouldn't be happy.
Uh.
Well.
Maybe you're right.
You're a good kid, Sal.
You're all right. - Come
on. Let's run along now.
You gonna call me in
the morning? - I promise I will.
Early?
- Early.
All right.
Good night, Jeff.
That was smart, Sally.
Not you or your whole Army
can take him away from me.
And don't you forget it.
Nice kid, huh?
- Yeah.
Wipe the paint off
your puss. - Really?
Hmm.
Kelly Field, here we come. The
finest food in the Army for four miles.
Maning. - Oh, forget
the food, knucklehead.
Capt. Mercer never
did like your snap rolls.
Well, he wouldn't wash us out in a
final check. He taught us all we know.
Don't let Hopkins hears
you say that. Just think, Al.
The fastest ships, cross
countries, night flying. - Yeah.
And a pair of wings.
- Aw, this is going to be a cinch.
We're practically at Kelly now.
Flying Cadet Young,
reporting for final check, sir.
What do we do, sit this one out?
Climb on to traffic to
2.000 feet into a practice area.
Show me gentle,
medium and speed banks.
Putrid. Putrid.
Alright. Alright.
Show me some slow rolls.
How did I ever get
myself a job like this?
I can't stand
anymore. Take me home.
Raunchy. Very raunchy. I hate
the pass you men on those rides.
But we have to
get somebody to Kelly.
By the way.
The next job you take, young
lady, better be close to home.
Like photographing
the San Antonio Water Works.
You miss me?
- Missed you?
The day they turned me
loose on cross-country,
I almost made it
non-stop to Guatemala.
Why'd you turn back?
It's rather lonely down there.
Oh. Mr. Camera must be slipping.
I thought he kept
you too busy to be lonely.
Maybe my mind
wasn't on my work.
Let's finish this dance
from the terrace.
Hey, Jeff. You're wanted
on the horn. - What?
Telephone call for you. - Well, tear
it up. I'm not taking any calls tonight.
Jeff.
You'd better take this one.
Oh. I'm sorry, Cally.
Will you excuse me?
Yes, certainly.
You know Mr. Cassidy. You're
wasting your time in the Air Corps.
There's a distinguished career waiting
for you in the diplomatic service.
Yeah?
Hello.
- Hello, Jeff.
Why haven't you called?
- Well, I was busy.
Well, you can't be so busy. I hear
there's a dance out there tonight.
It's just a small party.
Our last night at Randolph.
I can get away early.
I think I'll drive up for a while.
I wouldn't do that, Sally.
Why, Jeff, it's been
weeks since I've seen you.
Now Sally, I thought
we've been all through this.
I thought you were going to be
intelligent about it. - What does that mean?
Goodbye. Good luck.
We've had our fun.
You go your way. I'll go mine.
Don't try and sell me that routine, Jeff.
I wish I could think of a
better ending but I can't. - No?
Maybe I can. I want
to see you tonight.
Sorry, I made other plans.
- Listen, Mister Jeff Young.
You drop up to my
place after that dance.
Or I'll start making
a few plans of my own.
I'm expecting you.
Attention. Orders.
Headquarters.
Flying Cadet Detachment.
The Air Corps Primary Flying School.
Office of the Commandant.
Randolph Field, Texas.
Detachment order.
Order Number Ten.
All existing appointments
of flying cadets
as officers and
non-commissioned officers
in the Flying Cadet
Battalion are revoked.
And the following
appointments are announced.
Effective upon departure
to Kelly Field at 9 a. m. tomorrow.
To be Senior Cadet Captain,
Flying Cadet Ludlow, A.H.
Congratulations, Ludlow.
Al, they picked a
good man this time.
Yeah, but he was just
getting to be a good guy.
Now he has to
start playing grandma.
KELLY FIELD
A very stylish landing, mister.
- You know it's funny.
When I came down, I
wasn't even looking at the field.
Think I can get a job
around here the beacon?
I have a better idea.
Tell me something, Miss Bartlett.
Yes. - How is it nobody
ever married you before I will?
I don't know.
I suppose it's because of the funny
kind of life I've made for myself.
I think really it's because nobody
has to make me want to give it up.
Could you give it up for me?
I know I could if.
You were just Lt. Young.
Not Jefferson Young the 3rd.
Gee, I'd have to live your
way. Can you wait for me?
I think it frightens me just a bit.
Well, don't worry.
After I get my wings, I'm
not going back to Long Island.
Wall Street. And those
tired coming-out parties.
I'm staying with the
Air Corps. For good.
Well.
I guess I am too.
Ho hum.
Good night, darling.
- Good night. Hey, wait a minute.
You shouldn't be out here this
late, Sally. It's against regulations.
I can tell them about a few
regulations you've broken, Mr. Young.
Get in.
- Never mind that.
Sally, you and I are through.
Our account is closed.
Is it?
Oh, come on, Grandma. Button
on your bust and let's get going.
On the double, old lady.
Come on. - All right. Bye, boys.
Just don't let me lose you in
the turns. That's all. - Ho ho.
A skipper from Randolph.
- Yeah, Capt. Mercer.
Well, hello. - Certainly
glad to see you, sir.
Oh, you've been laying
for me, huh? - No, sir.
You weren't as
tough as all that.
Well, I see all three
of you are still here.
Yes, we're still here.
We proved that flying is safe.
I guess you have at that.
- Are you transferred over here, sir?
No, just over here on business.
I've been assigned to a Flying Fortress
Squadron next month out at Marsh Field.
You know. I'd like to
have you men in my outfit.
If you're assigned to Bombardment.
That's where we really
separate the men from the boys.
Well, that lets Cassidy out.
- As you were, chump.
You know how glad I am to see
you three finishing the course.
I'd like to give you one
more piece of advice.
You're at the peak
right now. Hot pilots.
Out in the service,
you will run into older pilots.
Old fuds like me that
aren't what they used to be.
You can fly rings around
them. But have a heart, boys.
Break the news to them gently.
What's an "old fud"? - That's what
Grandma's going to grow up to be.
One more week and I'm
second lieutenant with wings.
45 minutes of safe and sane flying
behind Grandma here and we're through.
You do you want me to do,
dive on the colonel's quarters?
Oh, no. We wouldn't think of it.
What, hop a hedge? Why,
that's against the Scout's code.
Grandma, huh? All right.
I'll give you guys a workout.
Now they'll wash me out
for this, won't they, Jeff?
What sort of a
racket is this anyway?
Graduation Day and they throw
out the best man on the class.
For something he was
no more responsible for than I.
Just because you were the leader.
Everybody hedgehops once in awhile.
We egged you into it.
Tom happened to be
the one who slipped up.
I am responsible. - If you listened to
me, we could have cooked up a story.
Don't you think I felt bad
enough about lying out of it?
And you didn't do me any good
when you horned in on the blame.
Almost got yourself washed out too.
So what's the difference?
I'm quitting anyway. Fed
up with their kind of discipline.
They can have it and take a
running full-twist into the lake.
Aw, cool off.
You'll feel better after they
pin those wings on you. - Wings?
I'll hang 'em in my trophy room.
Where do you get off,
talking like this? You got no beef.
You came down here polo-playing
drip. And they made a flier on you.
I'm sorry, Jeff.
Look, Jeff. You're the
best friend I've ever had.
I just don't want to
see you go off your nut.
I'm washed up. Sure.
Just wasn't in the cards for me.
We both want something
when we came down here.
We both felt the same way.
And if I'm not in the Air Corps,
I want to know that you're in.
But you got the
thing we both wanted.
And you earned it.
The hard way.
That's something
your money won't buy.
Something bigger than you or me.
Stick with it. Jeff.
Come on. Get going.
You got to fly that review.
See you later.
Al. Wait.
Al. You can't go like this.
Ah, the more speed,
the better the takeoff.
Jeff and I have plans
for you. - Well, thanks.
I'd rather be on my own.
Where are you going?
It's a big country. Tell Jeff so
long and to stay on the beam.
He'll know what I mean.
It's from both of us.
Thanks. - How many
aviators do you kiss, sister?
Sally, stop it.
- Try and make it.
I know. I read
about you and Jeff.
A big military wedding
for a dress affair.
Now you don't want to go
out there, Sally. - Oh, don't I?
I'm tired of being pushed around.
So they're giving him his wings?
They won't dare
when I get through.
I'll give them a scandal
that'll shake the Army.
I'll tell 'em a bedtime story
they won't forget. - Al, let her go.
Jeff hasn't seen her in
months. - That's your story.
He's seen me lots of times.
How do you think I got his car?
Let go of me.
Jeff Young can't pick me up and drop
me without seeing where I'm gonna land.
I'll make him marry me.
- Sally, be sensible.
You can't make anybody
marry you. - Can't I?
Who do you think
I am, Snow White?
I'm in trouble.
Jeff gave you kind of
a rotten deal, didn't he?
I'll say he did.
But I'll make him squirm.
I'll take care of that pal of yours.
He's no pal of mine. Not after
the way he kicked you around.
Well, I'm through
being kicked around.
I don't know
what's the matter with me.
I don't want to hurt anybody.
But they're always hurting me.
Look, Sally. Jeff's got
another half-hour in the air.
No sense starting anything
till you had a talk with him.
I think you need a
drink. - I'll say I do.
Might be able to fix something up.
Why aren't you up there?
They washed me out.
Wouldn't you know it.
The same old Al.
You and me both make a couple of -
also-rans.
Come on, Al. I need that drink.
Going up? - Not yet,
but I will be in 10 minutes.
This came for you, sir.
- Oh, thanks.
LT JEFF YOUNG
KELLY FIELD TEX
TAKING SALLY AWAY.
WE ARE GETTING MARRIED
AL
Where's Miss Bartlett?
- Back at home.
Well, if you see her first,
tell her I'm looking for her.
Oh, there you are. I've
been looking all over for you.
Carolyn. Al's gone.
I just got this.
Oh, no. - What made
him do a thing like that?
Can't you imagine?
- No, I can't. I had no idea...
Jeff. Have you been seeing Sally?
Yes, I have.
She threatened to go to the commandant.
I wanted my wings so... I saw her.
I gave her a check.
Do you think that
takes care of everything?
What did you expect me to do?
Jeff, one can't use a
checkbook for a conscience.
What's that got
to do with us? - A lot.
I've had a swell
time on my own, Jeff.
I've got to know what I'm giving
it up for. - Look. Just because Sally...
She was here this afternoon.
I spoke to her. And so
did Al. - What did she say?
Don't you know?
Al drove away with her.
You wouldn't be getting your
wings today if it weren't for him.
A pleasant thought, isn't it?
Jeff, I wonder if you're
worth what he did for you.
No, I'm not.
Lawrence, P.T.
Thank you, sir. - Congratulations.
Mr. Lawrence. - Thank you, sir.
Wilcox, D.A.
Congratulations. Mr. Wilcox.
- Thank you, sir.
Young, J.
Congratulations, Mr. Young.
- Thank you, sir.
Arden, M.
Congratulations, Mr. Young.
- Thank you, sir.
Congratulations, Mr. Arden.
Rutherford, D.
Quinn, A.J.
KANSAS CITY
Why, Mr. Vanessa.
And me, a respectable
married woman for six months.
Sure, I like it.
I'm up to my elbows in diamonds
and down to my knees in silver fox.
Cut the clowning, Tony. Haven't
you got a spot for me at the Paradise?
I don't wanna trip to
Florida. I want a job.
I know. They got
big oranges in, Florida.
Un-uh. Doctor told me
to stay in Kansas City.
Smoke's good for what
I've got. Vanessa.
Okay, Tony.
Skip it.
I guess you and I don't think
alike. I'm sorry I bothered you.
The wolf. He was a nice
kid when he was a barber.
Czar of the numbers
racket is something else.
Did you...?
- No, nothing.
Don't bite my head off. I just wanted
to know how you wanted your eggs.
Scrambled.
It would've been a commission
job anyway. - Don't kid me, Al.
You didn't want that job.
You don't want any job.
Except flying. - I told you
I was through with flying.
How about cooking those eggs?
- No, I'm sick of cooking for you.
I'm sick of this cheap dump.
I don't have to stay here.
I can skip any time I want to.
You think the baby's stopping me?
Well, there isn't any baby.
There never was.
I knew that, Sally.
Then what did
you marry me for?
So you didn't want to help me.
You didn't care anything
about me. I didn't matter.
What a sucker I've been.
Trying to make a go
of a two-cent marriage
while all the time you're
grandstanding for a guy named Jeff Young.
It's on me, isn't it, Al?
MARCH FIELD
LAND OF THE
FLYING FORTRESS
Where's the ship we
borrowed from Hamilton Field?
Over in Hangar 2, sir.
They just pulled her in.
What about that turbo supercharger
on 32? - Another two hours, sir.
That's just dandy.
So they sent us a B-17B, huh?
How about 32? She
going to be ready on time?
Not for another two hours at least, sir.
- And all we've got is 20 minutes.
Good thing we sent to Hamilton
for a spare. We'll have to use it.
Did she come down with
a full enlisted crew?
I don't know, sir.
I was just on my way to check.
We better find out. I want to
go to the crew that came with it.
You can relieve those men.
- All right, sir.
All right, sergeant. Tell your men
to knock off. We won't use that ship.
Crew chief?
- Up front, sir.
What's the rest of your crew?
- They're getting something to eat, sir.
I can have them
back in five minutes.
Al!
- How are ya?
Gee, you're looking great, fella.
See you're still with it.
Where you been? I dragged the
whole country for you. - Did you?
Oh, I... am I moved
around pretty much.
How is Sally?
Well, last I heard, she was in Florida.
Been through worst stuff, you know.
How's Carolyn? - Oh, I haven't
seen her since graduation.
She's up north somewhere. I keep
myself too busy to think about her.
Say, crew chief on a bomber,
that's doing all right in a year.
Oh, acting crew chief, sir.
You know, expansion.
Oh, don't give
me that "sir" stuff.
By rights, I should be taking
orders from you. - Young.  - Yes, sir.
Come meet your
commanding officer.
What's wrong with the emergency
release? - The door doesn't drop, sir.
Air Corps supply won't have
parts until tomorrow. - Well, Ludlow.
Can't stay away from it, can you?
Well, if I can't fly them, sir,
I can at least polish their wings.
I'm glad you're back
with us. - Thank you, sir.
I'll go get the report, sir.
It gets in your blood, doesn't it?
- There's a man who should be flying.
Hmm. - Can we
do something, sir?
And I've got a friend
or two in the chief's office.
Cases have been
reconsidered before.
Right now, we've
got other things to do.
She's all ready to go, sir,
except for that emergency release.
Well, we can't ground the ship for that.
Take care of it first thing tomorrow.
Yes, sir. Oh, sir.
This test is a new type
of experimental flare
on the way back tonight.
But don't install it in the bomb bay
until all the flares have been released.
Say, Al. I spoke to Mercer
about another crack at Kelly.
He said he'd go to bat for you.
- Do you think there's a chance?
You know Mercer.
If there's a chance, he'll swing it.
You really think so?
- Sure.
Look, right now,  I'm
racing to a pilot's meeting.
But when I get back tonight,
we have a lot to talk about.
Where can I find Lt. Young?
Al. - What are
you doing here?
They followed me here. The police
are out there now. - Get out of here!
But, Al. I'm your wife.
I'm in a jam. A bad one.
Tony Vanessa's dead. Somebody
killed him. They said I did it.
Did you?
- No.
- Yes and I'd do it again.
You were born to kill
somebody, Sally. - Hit me.
Hurt me. - Shut up!
You can't stay here.
But I... You've always helped
me. You've never let me down.
You got any money?
Here. Take this.
When you see your chance, step out of
the hangar and get back to Los Angeles.
Will you meet me there, Al?
- You're on your own, Sally.
Al, please. I don't know where
to turn. I got to talk to somebody.
Please.
Tomorrow night, Al. Please.
All right. All right.
I'll meet you at the
bus station tomorrow night.
They must have turned
me out labeled "sucker".
Now get out of here.
We're taking off right away.
I'll see you
tomorrow night, Al.
Al, they're here.
Al!
Here we go again, boys.
- We're on our way.
The old man says we're going upstairs.
Here we go to play war games.
Yep. But it feels real this time.
- There's supposed to be an air raid tonight.
You all right?
Navigator to Commander.
Drift correction.
Two degrees left.
We're 45 seconds ahead
of our last checkpoint.
Put the manifold pressure
back to 23 inches.
Navigator to Commander.
Over Monterrey.
Anti-Aircraft Company.
Battery B. 52nd Monterrey.
Warning this command.
27 heavy bombers passing over here.
At estimated altitude 12.000.
Changing course from south to east.
Navigator to Commander.
Over Santa Barbara.
Directions to 32nd Squadron.
Extinguish your navigation light.
Hold your altitude at 12.000.
Navigator to Commander.
Estimate over Glendale.
One and 1/2 minutes.
Shows Los Angeles blacked out.
Bombardier to Commander.
Objective visible.
Mercer to 32nd Squadron.
Squadron approaching objective.
Bombardier, stand by to
release magnesium bombs.
And trail on assigned target.
Bombardier to Commander.
Opening bomb bay doors.
Directions to 32nd Squadron.
Formation 3000 feet above
preparing to attack on our left.
Squadron change formation.
To Javelin down.
All combat crew members,
maintain battle stations.
Here we go.
Mercer to 32nd Squadron.
Enter overcast.
Use regular ascent procedure.
Rendezvous on top of overcast.
Mercer to 32nd Squadron.
Proceed individually to simulated
occupation of dispersed airdrome.
Head for Muroc Dry Lake.
Simulate occupation
in about ten minutes.
Better get those experimental
flares installed. - Yes, sir.
Tentative results from GHQ, sir.
VS-1 to WMZ.
Commanding General First Wing.
GHQ Air Force, Marsh Field.
White Pursuit MP...
- Al.
Al, get me out of here.
I can't stand it here.
I can't breathe.
Let me go up front, Al.
Are you crazy? Do you
want them to see you?
Stay right here till I come and
get you. And stay put. - Al.
Look out for those flares. In fifteen
seconds, they  could blow us all to glory.
Understand? - Al, I can't stand
it in here any longer. I can't!
You will.
I'll knock you cold.
Al, don't leave me.
Al!
- Live flares!
Live flares!
Open the bomb bay.
- Open the bomb bay doors.
Bombardier. Open the bomb bay doors.
Hit the emergency release
before it explodes.
Close this.
- What was that?
Where's the throw?
Straight.
We got it.
Keep going.
He caught it.
He caught it. - Get out that
chute. We're going down.
Are you crazy? That's against
all regulations. - We're going down.
Capt. Mercer.
He has serious burns, sir.
And head injuries.
Looks like internal injuries too.
I'm afraid he's dying.
Adrenaline, quick.
Yeah.
You're a fool.
Water.
Who taught you to land a plane
in the middle of the night in this spot?
Like this.
- Alcohol.
I didn't. - You're
pretty seriously hurt, sir.
We have to get
you to a hospital.
You're staying
right here? Jones.
Right here, sir.
Contact Marsh on
the main transmitter.
Tell them we're
staying here. - Yes, sir.
Never mind that message.
They'd okay it at Marsh.
We'll never get out
of here. That ridge.
We're taking off.
Anybody like to stay?
All right.
Get that stretcher.
Yes, sir.
Be careful.
- Easy now, fella.
All right. Set him down
here and get him covered up.
Check.
All right. Give me all
the manifold pressure she'll take.
Heads are frigid
on the one constrictor blade.
Drop that flap or
it tears the engine out.
She won't pull seven.
Line's busted.
Keep trying.
VS-1 to WMZ.
Ship's vibrating violently.
Well, our wings are still on.
Prepare for crash landing.
Making crash landing.
All right, men. Get in here!
Try pumping it.
Pump it quickly.
Are you all right?
Sally.
Hold it.
Jeff.
Oh.
I say.
Make it go away, Al.
Thanks.
Thanks, Al.
This isn't hurting.
- No.
A really swell guy.
Oh.
Sally.
She got on the ship.
She was in trouble.
Yeah, I loved her.
I couldn't help it.
Lt. Young said the court
would never believe
that I didn't know my
wife was aboard the ship.
He said I'd be finished for good.
I never get another chance.
If he knew he had to go but. There
was no sense in both of us taking it.
That's why he pleaded
guilty. To shield me.
That's all.
No further witnesses.
- The room will be cleared.
While the court
deliberates its verdict.
Good luck.
- Why, Carolyn.
I heard about this and thought
you might want to see me.
Thanks for coming.
- I'm here to stay this time, Jeff.
If you want me.
- Yes, I want you.
But they're about to tie a tin
can to my tail. - It doesn't matter.
Maybe not to you.
But it will to a lot of people.
Darling.
A lot of people will never
know what you've done.
But I know.
I'm proud.
No matter what verdict
they reach in there.
I'm proud of you.
On the specification, charge one.
Not guilty.
The court finds that
Lt. Young's decision
to disregard Capt. Mercer's
command was justified.
Under the extraordinary circumstances.
Capt. Mercer's life was at stake.
And Lt. Young had
a reasonable right
to doubt the binding
nature of a command
given by a man so gravely injured.
On the specification, charge two.
Not guilty.
Goodbye, Jeff.
Good bye, sir.
Ludlow.
You made a monkey out of me
once at Kelly. - Don't do it again.
I won't, sir.
- Can I get a kiss?
You wanted wings,
mister? Go get them.
Blow hard, lieutenant.
You're a big boy now.
Into the air, Army Air Corps.
Give 'er the gun, pilots true.
And the wings will see you through.
Subtitles by: Mondo @KG