?? (tattoo)
Gentlemen, Nazi motorized divisions
are already massed on our frontiers.
Unless a miracle happens,
we shall be invaded.
This factory will be
one of their first objectives.
I have special instructions here
from the minister of the interior.
‘‘In no circumstances
must Herr Bomasch
or his G.K. armor plating...
be allowed to pass into Nazi hands.’’
But my work is not yet completed.
The tests that you have made were
good enough to show its possibilities.
Isn’t that understating it?
If it’s successful, it will revolutionize
defensive warfare.
And it is a revolution
that we do not wish to have
brought about by the Third Reich.
-Then I am to leave the country.
-As soon as the Nazi invasion starts.
I have here passports
for yourself and your daughter.
Arrangements have been made
for you to carry on your work
in another country.
Where, you will be told
when the time comes.
I have made out lists —
Ours?
No. Theirs.
If we resist German protection,
Prague will be bombed.
Protection. Protection from what?
Give me a direct line
to the Ministry of the Interior, at once!
What?
The minister left 10 minutes ago
for the Central Radio Station.
The German command
has given the order to march.
At this moment, Nazi troops
are streaming across our frontiers.
In our present defenseless condition...
resistance is worse than useless.
Citizens of Czechoslovakia...
We must bear the trials
that lie ahead...
with fortitude and courage.
Be of good heart.
And remember —
long live Czechoslovakia!
But will the British government
give me facilities?
Everything is arranged.
You will be met at Croydon.
Here are the details.
Now, you haven’t a minute to lose.
The plane leaves the airfield
in half an hour, and it will be the last.
-But, uh, will you be there?
-I must stay.
Axel, your daughter.
Is that you, Anna?
You have heard?
Listen, dear.
I don’t want to alarm you, but we
have to leave the country at once.
Go to the airport.
I will be waiting for you.
Immediately. Do you understand?
Yes. Yes, at once.
Where are we going?
England?
Yes, of course.
-What’s happening, Miss Anna?
-Martha, I’ve got to leave at once.
Help me put some things in a bag.
Anna Bomasch, you are under arrest.
-We cannot wait any longer!
-Please, another moment!
My daughter was leaving at once.
But the city’s occupied already.
We must go!
Away! Come on!
Schnell! Schnell!
Marsch.
Marsch!
Aufschliessen!
Halt!
Turn right.
Edward Klein, for laziness.
12 lashes.
My heart will never stand it,
Herr Doctor.
-Heart’s fit.
-I have been under treatment for —
Take him away. Next man.
Karl Marsen, for insubordination.
20 lashes.
Good for twice the number
by the look of him.
You will soon learn that it’s better
to keep your mouth shut...
and to do as you are told.
Thank you.
I have no wish to become a Nazi.
We shall also teach you
that insolence does not pay.
With the aid of those
pillars of Nazi culture —
the whip and the jackboot.
-Silence!
-I shall say what I like!
You hate the truth...
because, in the end, it will destroy you
and your bankrupt philosophy.
You will perish
because you have nothing to offer...
because you can’t forever replace
tolerance and decency...
with brute force, because you —
Stand away from him.
Get back to your work.
Better leave me.
Mmm?
Halt!
Get along. No talking.
Good Samaritan.
I wanted to thank you
for yesterday.
The swine!
Don’t look at me.
We shall be seen.
Why did they send you here?
Oh.
I’m a desperate character.
I had a little school
on the Sudeten border.
I was ordered to abolish our language
and to teach in German...
by an illiterate Nazi group leader.
So here I am.
Shh.
-And you?
-My father escaped to England.
I almost went back with him.
-Back?
-I was at school there.
They arrested me
to find out where he was hiding...
and because I couldn’t tell them —
That’s all.
England.
Well, good luck to him.
I have been a fool. I —
I should have held my tongue
and-and waited.
-We shan’t always be here.
-No?
Somehow, I’m going to join my father.
How?
-Well, we have friends outside.
-Yes.
But between them and us —
There must be a way.
Past searchlights, machine guns,
barbed wire?
I should take any risk
if I thought there was a chance.
But there is none.
There isn’t one of us
who doesn’t lie awake —
-Keep your mouths shut!
You know the order!
Get back, you. I told —
Silence.
What is it?
Do you know him?
He studied with me
for a job in the civil bureau.
He might help us.
-But isn’t he a German?
-Yes.
From the Sudetenland.
When it was occupied by Germany,
he was desperate.
I gave him the advice.
Become a good Nazi, Paul.
Join the party... and wait.
Then you think that —
Yes.
Now there may be a chance.
-What’s wrong up there?
-It’s fused!
It’s all right!
-You should be asleep.
-Karl, what’s that noise?
-That’s the Goodwin lightship, miss.
-We should be in England
in an hour or two.
But it'll be light then.
You don’t mean
we’re going ashore without
any passports in broad daylight?
In broad daylight!
?? (brass band)
Why not?
Come on. Only a shilling.
-Aye, aye, knock it.
Turn it up. What’s the idea?
-Oh, I’m so sorry.
Think you’re the Mauretania?
I might have had a Lillian Gish
on the end of that.
-I’m very sorry indeed.
-All right. Granted, me ol' cock.
-Have you caught anything?
-New eels.
Oh! That’s a night fish.
You’ve been out in a ketch.
Not like me — fishing to keep away
from the old woman.
-Where do we change?
-The beach.
-And then London?
-Yes.
There I shall go to see
a friend of my family.
He fled to England last September.
He'll help us.
He’s living at a place called
Hampstead. You’ve heard of it?
Yes. Karl, if you only knew
how glad I am to be back here...
where people can still laugh
and be happy.
Come away, Alfie.
If you’re not falling in something,
you’re dragging in something.
Go on.
-Good evening.
-Uh, good evening.
-I should like to see Dr. Fredericks.
-Have you an appointment?
No, but, uh, if you would give him
my name. It is Marsen. Karl Marsen.
-Well, will you come in, please?
-Thank you.
Now, if you will take this to Gilby's,
the opticians.
They’re just around the corner.
If you mention my name,
they will make up your little girl’s
glasses at a reduced charge.
Thank you, Doctor.
And don’t worry.
With care, she will grow out of it.
-Thank you, Doctor. Good night.
-Good night.
There’s a gentleman to see you,
Doctor, a Mr. Marsen.
Marsen?
Oh, very well. Show him in.
-The doctor will see you now.
-Thank you.
Good luck.
Mr. Marsen.
-Good evening.
-How do you do, Doctor?
I was given your name.
I’m suffering from an, uh, eyestrain
and should like a test.
-Headaches and so forth?
-Hmm, yes.
If you will be good enough
to sit in this chair, please?
Thank you.
-Warm this evening, isn’t it?
-Rather.
I hear there may be a storm brewing.
Now, will you read the top line,
please?
K, M, S...
Q, R, Y.
And now the line underneath.
M, O, 2...
6, 7, 3, G.
I don’t think that is quite right.
Will you repeat it, please?
M, O, 2...
6, 7, 3, G.
--Heil Hitler.
Well?
I have to report that on instructions
from Gestapo headquarters...
I successfully made contact
with the woman Bomasch...
in Concentration Camp Number Four,
Reichsprotektorat of Bohemia.
I escaped with her, as arranged,
on the 27th of July...
and came ashore
this morning at 11:15,
from the freighter Stovendam.
We are staying at
an apartment house...
at 124 Paddington Lane, Marylebone.
Good. She has, of course,
made no attempt to locate her father.
No. I am awaiting your instructions.
This is all we know.
Bomasch is working for the British
admiralty. Where, we have no idea.
He is certainly well hidden
and well guarded.
-Therefore, we must move cautiously.
-Understood, sir.
So do not appear too eager.
Impress upon her that you are aliens
and must move carefully.
Suggest that she places
an advertisement to this effect...
in the personal column
of the London Times...
signed perhaps with some nickname
which her father will know at once.
You will see that that advertisement
is repeated daily until it is answered.
When that happens,
you will report to me instantly.
-You understand?
-Yes, sir.
That is all. Heil Hitler.
--Heil Hitler!
I see that fellow Ribbentrop’s
going to Moscow.
Hmm. So did Napoleon.
Miss Bomasch,
you’re wanted on the phone.
Nice time of night to ring up,
I must say.
-Who is it?
-Oh, he didn’t say.
Hello? Yes, I’m Anna Bomasch.
In the Times, yes. Who is it?
Yes, I’m alone. Who is it, please?
I can’t answer questions.
Now please listen carefully.
At the post office in Prairie Street,
a letter is waiting for you...
containing a railway ticket.
Go to the destination on the ticket,
and when you get to the town...
ask for a man named Gus Bennett.
You’ve got the name? Gus Bennett.
-Yes, but who do I ask?
-Everyone there knows Gus Bennett.
You say nothing of this to anyone.
That is most important.
Hello?
Hello!
-Yes?
-It’s Anna. May I come in?
Yes, come in.
Karl, I’ve just heard.
Somebody telephoned.
-We found him.
-Where?
-I don’t know yet.
-But, uh, what did he say?
Karl, I’d love to tell you,
but whoever it was said
I wasn’t to say a word to anyone.
-Oh.
-I don’t mean you’re just anyone.
-Of course you’re not, but —
-Anna, I —
I would much rather you didn’t tell me.
We don’t know what your father
is doing, and it’s probably right
you should take precautions.
There’s no one in the world
I’d rather confide in.
I don’t know what I’d have done
if it hadn’t been for you.
No.
-You are happy now?
-Mm-hmm.
Well, that’s all that matters.
Good night, Karl.
-?? (man singing)
-I’m looking for Mr. Gus Bennett.
I was told I’d find him here.
Oh, he’s along here, all right.
You hear a warbling note
like an air raid siren?
Well, that’s him singing.
-? Only love can cheer the day ?
-Over there?
Churns out the same moldy songs
from 9:00 in the morning.
A human barrel organ, he is.
-? Lots in life may be denied ?
-?? (piano)
? But hearts can laugh ?
? When love’s inside ?
? For only love can lead the way ?
? As time rolls on and on ??
The song of the century!
When ‘‘Home Sweet Home’’
and ‘‘Annie Laurie’’ are forgotten,
this song will live on.
Now, madam, only the price
of a stick of rock.
Sixpence, sir. The ballad of the age.
‘‘Only Love Can Lead the Way.’’
Here, buy a copy
for the sergeant major.
Thank you, gentlemen! Thank you!
Anyone else want to buy a copy
of this haunting melody?
How would you like to be haunted
for a sixpence, miss?
-Mr. Gus Bennett?
-In the flesh. You want me to
autograph it? I'll throw that in.
-I’m Anna Bomasch.
-How do you do?
Don’t go away, ladies and gentlemen!
I’m not gonna sing again yet.
-I was told to come
and see you, Mr. Bennett.
-Hmm? Who by?
-I don’t know.
-Is this a gag?
Well, somebody phoned me.
They said you’d have news
of my father.
Your father? Never heard of him.
Somebody’s pulling your leg.
‘‘Only Love Can Lead the Way.’’
A tonic so far.
We give the tonic.
You provide the ‘‘so far.’’
Thank you, madam.
Hey, don’t go away. I’m just
going to tear off another number.
Then we'll have a talk.
I’m now going to sing
the sentimental song hit of the year.
They say the hand that rocks
the cradle rules the world...
but, believe me,
it’s songs like this that fill it.
? It’s true ?
? Oh, what it does to me
to know it’s true ?
? She loves me ??
Are you — Are you sure
it was Gus Bennett they said?
-Yes, I’m certain.
-Your father’s not
in the song business?
-No.
-Well, it’s beyond me.
How did you lose him?
-He escaped.
-Escaped? You mean
he’s still at large?
-I-I mean, you
haven’t seen him since?
-No.
You see,
I was in a concentration camp.
-Were you really? Where?
-Near Prague.
Prague.
-You here by yourself?
-Yes.
-Anyone know you’re here?
-No.
Would you like another one of these?
No, thank you.
Alfie?
I don’t understand it.
It’s extraordinary.
Well, it amounts to this.
You don’t know my father...
you don’t know anything about him,
and you can’t help me.
Is that him?
Father!
Anna!
Here it is —
Brightbourne, a health resort.
But I hardly think that Herr Bomasch
is there for his health.
You notice across the bay
is the Dartland naval base.
Reports says he’s been there
three times in the last week.
Probably conducting experiments, sir.
Precisely. We can’t afford
to delay a moment longer.
There’s another reason for haste.
Any day now, Poland may provoke us
into invading her in self-defense.
England will not stand by Poland.
We have the personal assurance
of Herr Von Ribbentrop as to that.
Hmm. So I understand.
Nevertheless,
instruct Fredericks that we are
putting arrangements in hand at once.
Very good, sir.
? You nonchalantly go around ?
? Completely unaware ?
? It’s just another ordinary day ?
? You meet a sweet
who sweeps you off your feet ?
? Your heart skips a beat
and runs away ?
? You can’t recall a tender thought
to show how much you care ?
? You can’t think
of a single thing to say ?
? You'll meet, so meek
You'll talk, but you don’t speak ?
? Your heart skips a beat
and runs away ?
? It may be Tuesday or Sunday ?
? Thursday or Monday ?
? Love never warns you at all ?
-Is the coffee ready?
-It won’t be a minute.
-Thank you, dear.
-?? (woman continues, indistinct)
--Oh, hello.
-Hello there.
-Come to see Father?
No.
-Want some?
-Thank you.
-Where did you get that from?
-Post office stopped it.
-Why?
-I gave them instructions.
What have my private letters
to do with you?
A postmark’s a dangerous thing.
-This letter’s to a friend of mine.
-British?
-No.
-Refugee?
I’m not going to be cross-examined.
I must remind you that
the government pay me a wage —
small but regular —
to look after your father.
It’s obviously not small enough.
You don’t suppose I’d write
to anybody I couldn’t trust.
Why, if it wasn’t for Karl,
I wouldn’t be here.
What did you say?
-He escaped with me.
-But you never told me.
-I told my father.
-But not me.
If I didn’t, it’s simply because Karl
is an alien without a passport.
He was afraid he might be deported.
-Known him long?
-No. What are you doing?
Just want to check up on him.
Have you ever heard
of an organized escape?
-Organized?
-To lead them to your father.
But that’s fantastic.
Karl doesn’t even know where I am.
Are you sure of that?
-Of course. I told no one.
-Good.
Honestly, I don’t want to throw
a monkey wrench into the romance.
Thank you. I appreciate that you’re
inspired by the highest motives...
and that you'll go to any lengths
to pursue them.
-Any lengths.
-Even to exhibiting yourself
in public as a singer.
Well, nature endowed me with a gift,
and I just accepted it. That’s all.
It’s a pity it didn’t endow you
with a voice.
Nothing that happened to me
in that concentration camp...
was quite as dreadful
as listening to you day after day...
singing those appalling songs.
With those few words, you’ve knocked
the bottom out of my entire existence.
A pity I only knocked it.
-Mr. Bomasch about?
-Yes, he is.
Admiral Baldwin
sends his compliments.
He’d like Mr. Bomasch
to have dinner with him this evening.
-And his daughter.
-Hmm. I'll tell him.
Uh, just a minute.
Didn’t Admiral Baldwin leave for
the Mediterranean last Tuesday?
No. He’s aboard the flagship
lying off Dartland.
-But I understood that —
Isn’t he going too far out for Dartland?
Sorry to barge in.
I say, Charles, the wife’s just phoned.
-I understand you’re
coming over to tea on Sunday.
-Yes, so I believe.
Well, she wants you to remind Beryl
to bring some recipe book —
pickling walnuts or something.
-Oh, yes. Will do.
-Right.
-Oh, hello, Randall. How are you?
-Hello. Hi.
We were just discussing
the Bomasch affair.
Oh, yes, you slipped up
rather badly there, didn’t you?
-Yes, I —
-Well, it wasn’t exactly his fault.
We ought to have known
about Karl Marsen.
The War Office
has been stinking about him.
They take the view that
this armor plating of Bomasch’s...
will make all the difference
in the next war.
Probably nothing of the sort,
but, well, there you are.
And by tonight,
Bomasch will be in Berlin...
where they won’t lose any time before
putting the screws on the poor devil.
Tomorrow night?
That means he won’t be
at the admiralty until, let’s see —
Saturday morning.
That’s about it. Why?
Twenty-four, maybe 48 hours.
Why? What are you driving at?
Well, they got him out of England.
Why shouldn’t I get him back?
But that’s quite impossible.
Why? I know my way about.
I was three years in Berlin.
-Drinking lager.
-Mmm. Vodka now, isn’t it?
What about the Polish situation?
Germany may march at any moment.
You know what that means.
I shall be back before then.
Well, sir?
Well, you know perfectly well
I can’t give you permission to do it.
And the fact that
you make the request at all
shows you’re not yourself.
-Don’t you think so, Gaskin?
-Oh, well, I —
I quite agree with you.
Now, I suggest you take
a week’s sick leave...
to enable you to get
a complete change of air, hmm?
Thank you, sir. I understand. I think
it might be very good for both of us.
Mm-hmm. Now, I expect you’d like
to have a little chat about it.
Yes, I would, sir.
Oh, well, uh, Charles, you won’t forget
about that recipe, will you?
No, no. I'll remember.
Now look here.
I don’t know what your plans are...
but I expect you'll want
a few letters of introduction.
Mm-hmm.
Reichssender
K?nigs Wusterhausen calling.
Early this morning,
the Polish hoards attacked Germany.
The führer immediately gave orders
to our glorious army
to invade Poland...
and to destroy
these intolerable aggressors...
of peace-loving Germany.
Naval High Command, Herr Major.
-How can I reach you?
-I'll ring you tonight.
I'll be waiting. Good luck.
All identity cards.
All identity cards to be shown.
Identity card?
Come on, come on, come on.
I’ve worked here for 10 years.
You Gestapo fellows must want a job.
-All right, all right.
-This is a fine country to live in.
-Hey. What’s that?
-Nothing.
-Name. Department.
-Schwab. Records. Intelligence.
-Report that man.
-Excellent, Officer.
While we have men like you at home,
we have nothing to fear. Nothing.
Oh, I have an appointment
with Commander Kampfeldt.
-Where can I find him?
-Second floor, sir.
Thank you.
This is a very grave matter, very grave.
It has just been reported to me
that you’ve been heard
expressing sentiments...
hostile to the fatherland.
-What, me, sir?
-What is it?
Major Herzoff to see you.
He asked me to give you this.
Can’t you see I’m engaged?
I warn you, Schwab,
such treasonable conduct will
lead you to a concentration camp.
But, sir, what did I say?
You were distinctly heard to remark,
‘‘This is a fine country to live in.’’
Oh, no, sir. There’s some mistake.
No, what I said was,
‘‘This is a fine country to live in.’’
Huh?
-You sure?
-Yes, sir.
Hmm. I see.
Well, in future, don’t make remarks
that can be taken two ways.
-Much wiser not to talk politics at all.
-Yes, sir.
-You may go.
-Heil Hitler.
Heil Hitler.
This is a fine country to live in.
This is a bloody awful country
to live in.
Shall I show Major Herzoff in, sir?
-Uh, yes, yes.
-Yes, sir.
Please.
Major Herzoff.
-Heil Hitler.
-Sit down, Major.
-Thank you.
Sorry to keep you waiting.
‘‘This is to introduce to you
Major Ulrich Herzoff...
of the Corps of Engineers.
Major Herzoff is in Berlin
on an important technical mission...
for which he requires
admiralty assistance.
I am sure, my dear Kampfeldt,
that you will give him
your best cooperation.
Heil Hitler.’’
Et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
I wish these War Office fellows
would learn to write properly.
Signature might be anything.
Whose is it?
Well, I have no idea.
As usual, I was taken
from one office to another.
-I suppose it couldn’t be Sardvitz.
-Sardvitz?
Or did he go in the purge?
-I can’t remember.
-I believe he did.
Hmm. Whoever he was,
he spoke very highly of you.
He did?
Might be Meidvidtz.
Not very likely though.
However, the important thing is,
what can I do for you?
I want to refer
to certain technical evidence...
given before the Naval
Heavy Armaments 1935 Committee.
If you will let me have a report
of the copy, Commander.
Certainly. It will take only a moment.
I have my own filing system here.
A copy of the Naval Heavy Armaments
1935 Committee’s report.
-Have you been in Berlin long, Major?
-No.
I only left the Siegfried line
last Tuesday.
Really? How is it there?
Things are pretty hectic, I expect.
Pumping night and day.
I was there in a consultative capacity.
Steel fortifications.
You possibly have heard.
Oh, yes, yes. Major Herzoff, of course.
Looks rather like Stuckner.
But I believe he is doing
diplomatic work in the Balkans.
-And who is not?
I’m afraid we haven’t a copy
of the 1935 report, sir.
-What’s that?
-We have one of ’34, but not ’35.
Are you sure there
was a ’35 committee?
I sat in it myself
as army liaison officer.
I beg your pardon.
Very well, very well.
It’s these fellows at the top.
They forget to send copies on.
Perhaps the construction department
might be able to help.
The very thing. They might have one.
I'll ring them at once.
-Oh, I’m sorry —
-No trouble at all.
Commander Prada.
I have with me Major Ulrich Herzoff
of the Corps of Engineers.
He is well known
for his splendid technical
achievements on our west wall...
as you’re no doubt aware.
He will be greatly obliged
if you can give him some assistance.
You'll see him at once?
Thank you, sir.
1935, you said. I guess
I could get hold of a copy for you.
Now, Commander Prada, you may
be able to help me more directly.
-You know, I just left the Siegfried line.
-Mm-hmm.
So Kampfeldt said.
How is everything?
The Krupp’s armor plating
is the trouble.
Confidentially,
that’s why I am in Berlin.
Do you realize that
the steel used by the Czechs
is better than anything we have got?
Mm-hmm. So I’ve heard.
But surely, now that we control
the Harska works —
Not enough.
We let the only man who counted
there slip through our fingers.
-Bomasch.
-Yes. I knew Axel Bomasch
personally.
I was present at the first gunnery test
of his G.K. plating. Incredible results.
Where is he? Working for Britain.
But if we can’t trace this 1935 report —
One moment, Major.
You will be surprised to hear that
Bomasch is no longer in England.
What?
He was brought back to Germany
only a few hours ago.
In fact, he’s in this building now.
But this completely alters my plans.
Perhaps you can arrange for me
to see Herr Bomasch at once.
I’m afraid it’s impossible.
He’s with the controller.
Surely there’s no harm
in my asking him a few questions.
It’s beyond my province, Major.
I'll pass you on to
Captain Viengarten, but frankly
I don’t think it will get you any further.
The controller’s office
is rather like the kingdom of heaven...
and, if anything,
a little more exclusive.
But you are no longer living
in a decadent democracy...
ruled by a pack of raving intellectuals!
This is the Third Reich,
and the führer does not tolerate...
stupid, insolent obstinacy!
You have been asked to work for
Germany, Herr Bomasch, and you will.
Can’t you leave him alone?
You’ve bullied and shouted at him
ever since we got here!
-He’s had no sleep!
-He must agree!
Can I have another word with him, sir?
As you please.
Anna. It’s useless for your father
to resist like this.
You must persuade him. You will
both be given reasonable freedom.
Freedom here?
In time, you will see things
the way I do...
the way everyone in Germany does.
I’m not a German.
Germany is as much your country
as it is ours now.
We don’t hate the Czechs.
We only wish to protect them.
As you’re protecting
the people of Poland?
You have been too long in Britain,
listening to their smug hypocrisy!
If I listened to hypocrisy in Britain,
it was not from the British.
I was doing my duty...
as a citizen of the Reich
and a subject of the führer...
for whose sacred mission
no sacrifice is too great.
That sounds rather like something
you learnt from a book.
For years, you’ve had this sort
of thing drilled into you until
it’s all you know or care about!
You’re a fanatic
with a set of stupid, fixed ideas!
If you hadn’t made me hate you more
than I thought I could possibly
hate anybody...
I think I should feel sorry for you.
You have expressed yourself
very clearly, Fraulein Bomasch.
You will be placed
in a concentration camp until
your father comes to his senses.
-Must you drag my daughter into this?
-It rests with you, Herr Bomasch.
Hello? What, here?
Very good.
Admiral Hassinger is on his way up.
The Chief of Naval Staff,
Vice Admiral Count Hassinger.
Come in, my dear fellow. Come in.
Strasse, let me present Major Herzoff
of the Corps of Engineers.
I expect you have heard of him.
The man behind the Siegfried line,
eh, Herzoff?
Only one of the men, sir.
The führer is responsible for the line
as he is responsible for everything.
Well, what progress?
You remember me, Herr Bomasch.
I did not expect to see you again here.
And you, Fraulein Bomasch.
I see you have not forgotten.
It must be... four years.
Major Herzoff is preparing a highly
confidential report on armor plating.
He has been on
several missions to Prague.
-He met Bomasch there.
-Just one moment, sir.
Marsen, conduct Herr Bomasch
and his daughter into the next room.
-Mr. Bomasch.
-Maybe we shall meet again, later.
I thought it unwise
to speak in front of Bomasch.
So far, we’ve made
no impression on him.
I do not agree.
He looks 10 years older.
My orders are to obtain quick results.
At the Reich,
we are rather inclined to believe...
that the knuckle-duster
is the best diplomatic weapon.
Do I understand that you question?
I question nothing.
I am an army officer.
Personally,
I do not follow any of this at all.
Bomasch is not the man
to be bullied into cooperation, sir.
Well, what do you suggest?
I knew Fraulein Bomasch in Prague.
She has a great influence with
her father and is the one person
who can make him change his mind.
Oh, Marsen here has tried that,
but she refused to listen.
He is largely responsible
for tracing Bomasch in England...
completely outwitting
the British military intelligence.
So, may I express
a soldier’s admiration...
for one who can carry out
his mission under the very eyes
of the enemy secret service?
Thank you, sir.
But if I may say so,
I hardly think the captain...
is a suitable person
to influence the lady.
And who do you think
would be more suitable?
Why, uh, myself, for instance.
-You?
-Why not?
Herzoff was very friendly with her
in Prague, you know.
A little more than friendly.
You saw the way she looked at me
when I came in.
Oh, yes, of course. Seems to me
you are a bit of a dog, Herzoff.
A technician, Admiral. One does
not talk about these things...
but I think if I were to spend
a few hours alone with her...
I might induce her
to reason with her father.
Oh. What do you think
about that, Strasse?
I cannot promise, mind you.
Four years is a long time.
It seems to me it is worth attempting.
After all, the business is urgent,
Strasse.
It is indeed, sir.
You really believe that you could
influence a girl in a matter of hours?
-Shall we say overnight?
-I see.
Knowing Fraulein Bomasch, sir,
I doubt whether even his qualities...
will make any impression on her.
-You aren’t acquainted
with my qualities.
-Strasse, we'll let him try it.
No harm done if he doesn’t succeed.
Leave all the arrangements to me.
This requires a knowledge of
maneuvers. Come along, Herzoff.
You may be right, my dear.
Bennett may be trying to help us.
But why have they
brought us to this hotel,
provided you with clothes?
It doesn’t make sense to me.
Well, Bennett’s behind it, obviously.
He’s organized the whole thing.
How?
Well, how did he manage
to get into the German admiralty
as a Nazi officer?
But I don’t see how he can
get us away from here, Anna.
Oh, Father, don’t worry about it.
Perhaps you’d better go
to bed now, eh?
We'll find out what it’s all about
in the morning.
-Good night.
Good night, my dear.
Come in.
-Fraulein Bomasch?
-Yes.
Thank you.
-You are expecting me. Major Herzoff.
-Yes, sir. Good evening.
Your room is Number 18.
Your bags have been taken up.
-My flowers arrive?
-Yes, sir. The lady has them.
-Thank you. Good night.
-Good night, sir.
My darling,
you look as charming as ever.
Those same sweet lips,
like warm carnations.
Those sweet, mysterious eyes,
darker and softer...
than the bluest dusk of August violets.
As the poet has it,
and I hope he was Aryan.
No one under the bed, I trust.
Uh, bring me a bottle of Krug ’28.
-That will be excellent.
-What’s happening?
You may have gathered that we were
partners in a highly romantic interlude
in Prague four years ago.
-By the way, did you like the flowers?
-Does that matter?
-It cost me 12 coupons.
-Well, go on.
Well, tomorrow morning
I’m going to phone the admiral...
and say that your father is now
prepared to work for Germany.
-What?
-I shall say that I persuaded you
to reason with him.
They’re bound to ask me
to take you both along.
The Gestapo man downstairs
will let us pass and then —
-Yes, but how do you know he will?
-They listen in to the phone.
They always do.
Then instead of driving
to the admiralty, we shall go
to a meadow outside Berlin...
where a plane is waiting.
I see. But why should the admiralty
believe you’ve persuaded me?
I shall indicate that, uh, once again
you have succumbed to my charms.
Once again?
It happened in Prague, I’m afraid.
And you told them
a fantastic story like that?
Fantastic? Well, it was four years ago,
there was a harvest moon...
and I was younger
and more dashing then.
But you really mean all this?
It sounds far too simple.
I have a very simple mind.
But there is one
small complication. Uh...
I shall have to spend the night here —
in a purely professional spirit,
of course.
-That is necessary?
-Well, sort of fits into the picture.
The place is absolutely
crawling with Gestapo.
-Have you any sporting instinct?
-Why?
Well, I'll, uh, toss you
who sleeps on the couch.
But you’re treating all this
as if it were some sort of joke.
-You don’t seem to realize
how much depends upon it.
-It’s no good being intense about it.
-You don’t think I like the idea
of a firing squad, do you?
-What?
England may be at war
with Germany tomorrow.
Oh, I see. But don’t you think
I ought to tell my father about all this?
-No.
-Why not?
It’d hardly look right for a lovesick girl
to go popping back to her dad.
That'll be the waiter. If you can
pretend you find me unbearably
attractive, so much the better.
-All right. I'll try.
-Thank you.
My little Anna.
?? (whistling tune)
?? (whistling continues)
-Is it, uh, raining?
-No, miss.
?? (whistling continues)
Is anything the matter?
That tune you were whistling, sir —
it is an English tune, isn’t it?
-How do you know?
-I heard it on the radio
from London last night.
Are you not aware that listening
to the foreign broadcasts is forbidden?
-That there is a strict penalty?
-Oh, I’m sorry, sir.
I will not report
you on this occasion, but see that
you are more discreet in future.
Get out.
--(sighs) Very awkward.
Lucky it wasn’t ‘‘Rule, Britannia!’’
I handled it rather neatly, I thought.
If a woman ever loved you
like you love yourself, it would be
one of the romances of history.
As I’m unlikely to think
of an adequate reply to that,
I think we ought to drink a toast.
England expects that
every secret service man
this night shall do his duty.
--Flat.
-They’re ringing your room.
-I'll take it here. It looks better.
-Hello? Is that call for me?
It’s German Admiralty.
Yes. Herzoff here. Yes, sir.
I’m sorry to disturb you at this hour,
Herzoff, but we have to alter our plans.
We have just received instructions
from headquarters in Munich...
that Bomasch is to go there at once
by the first train.
But this is ridiculous, sir.
Couldn’t you delay it for a few hours?
Impossible. It is on the führer’s orders.
The train leaves in an hour’s time.
But, sir, what is the use of sending
Herr Bomasch to headquarters
in his present frame of mind?
What do you suppose
the führer’s frame of mind
would be if we didn’t?
I’m sorry, Herzoff.
-What’s happening?
-They’re sending you to Munich
at once.
-There’s only one chance.
-What?
-Leave the hotel, scuttle —
an old German custom.
-But the guards downstairs.
We got into the admiralty.
We'll get out of here.
Get your clothes on.
Tell your father we leave here
in five minutes.
I’ve been instructed to leave
immediately with Herr Bomasch.
I shall not require you. Dismissed.
-Shall I get you a taxi, sir?
-I'll call one myself.
-- Good morning, sir.
- Good morning.
I’m here to escort Herr Bomasch
and Fraulein Bomasch to Munich.
The controller phoned me
10 minutes ago.
I was about to drive them
to the admiralty myself.
My orders are to take them
straight to the station.
The train leaves in 50 minutes.
Evidently a misunderstanding
on my part.
-Very well. We are ready.
-You, sir?
Certainly. Were you not told?
I have the admiral’s authority
to travel with them.
He feels it essential that
Herr Bomasch should be persuaded
to comply with our wishes...
before he reaches headquarters.
I was progressing extremely well
with Fraulein Bomasch
when this happened.
I see. Very good, sir.
-Zigaretten! Zigarren!
-There’s not a copy
of this week’s Punch?
-Please?
Punch. English magazine.
Very humorous.
You must have a copy.
No.
She hasn’t got a Punch, old man.
-Hasn’t she?
-No.
Well. Sold out, I suppose.
You will all leave here
and find places elsewhere.
This compartment is
commandeered by the police.
Come along. No delay, please.
They've got La Vie Parisienne,
old boy.
La Vie Parisienne? All right.
Don’t bother about a Punch.
Oh.
Everyone’s hopped it.
Must have got
in the wrong train, I expect.
--We can have a side
each to ourselves now.
-Put our feet up.
-There.
Bought a copy of Mein Kampf.
Occurred to me it might shed a spot
of light on all this how-do-you-do.
-Ever read it?
-Never had the time.
I understand they give a copy
to all the bridal couples over here.
Oh, I don’t think
it’s that sort of book, old man.
This is the compart —
Why are you still here?
-What?
-You must find other places at once.
We have first-class tickets, you know.
Outside, please.
This compartment has been
commandeered by the authorities.
-That is beside the point.
-Yes. We are British subjects.
Yes. Look here.
‘‘We, Edward Frederick Lindley,
Viscount Halifax...
His Majesty’s Principal
Secretary of State’’ et cetera...
‘‘request all whom it may concern...
to allow the bearer to pass
without let or hindrance...
and to afford him or her’’ —
Outside!
-Hmm.
-No good arguing, I suppose.
-Apparently not.
Waste of time,
all this bilge in the passport.
Come, please.
-It’s hopeless.
We'll never get away now.
-We'll think of something.
-Outside. Come along. Hurry!
-All right. All right.
Hel —
Excuse me.
Now, don’t forget
that you’re terribly attracted to me.
The two guards’ compartment
is in there, sir.
All right. Thank you.
-Would you like to face the engine?
-Whatever you like.
Did you notice that German officer
who came into our compartment?
Yes. Why?
Well, I could’ve sworn
it was old Dicky Randall.
Dicky Randall?
--Yes. We were at Balliol together.
You must have
heard me talking about him.
He used to bowl slow leg breaks.
Played for the Gentlemen once.
Caught and bowled for a duck,
I remember.
Oh, yes. Dicky Randall.
Well, if he’s a German officer,
how can he be Dicky Randall?
Well, I knew him quite well.
His rooms were next to mine.
Why on earth —
You don’t think
he’s working for the Nazis
like that fellow what’s-his-name?
Traitor? Hardly, old man.
He played for the Gentlemen.
Only once.
It was last Easter. I was looking
in a shop window in the Graben...
and I saw the reflection of a girl.
For a moment, I thought it was you.
-Were you by yourself?
-Yes. Why?
I just wondered.
It’s a blackout.
You know what that means
so far west as this.
England and France
have declared war.
We have nothing to fear.
The nation is behind the führer.
Yes, but how far behind?
We’re stopping.
Everybody out at once, please!
Everybody out on the platform.
Everybody out
of the compartment, please.
Everybody out at once, please.
-Why are we stopping?
-I don’t know yet, sir.
Just had the order.
Everybody out, please.
Everybody out. Everybody out.
-How far are we from Munich?
-About an hour’s journey.
All passengers off the train, please.
All passengers off the train.
-What’s happening?
-Everybody —
Heil Hitler!
This train is required for troops.
There will be only a small amount
of room available for passengers.
-My party must have
the same accommodations.
-Oh, yes.
The train leaves again in 20 minutes.
May I have your carriage number,
please, sir?
-Yes. It’s, uh, 0735.
-0735.
Oh, I beg your pardon.
Aren’t you old Dicky Randall?
Major Herzoff, Corps of Engineers.
Oh, I’m frightfully sorry.
It was very silly of me,
but it’s an amazing likeness.
Yes, you’d better come along,
old man.
Extraordinary. English, I presume.
-Apparently.
-They’re a very peculiar race.
We have a small waiting room, sir.
Perhaps you would prefer
to wait in there.
-Thank you.
-This way, please.
Please. Please, this way.
Everybody off the train now, please!
Everybody off the train!
You know, you — you made me feel
painfully embarrassed, Caldicott.
Well, I can’t help it if old
Dicky Randall has a double.
You must realize that we’re traveling
in very difficult times.
--What’s the matter?
I can’t help thinking
of your face when he said,
‘‘Major Herzoff, Corps of Engineers.’’
Well, all I can say, Charters,
is that when it comes to humor...
we live in entirely different worlds.
This waiting room is required.
Every passenger must wait outside.
Come on.
Und you too, please.
Come on. So quick like possible.
-This is getting beyond a joke.
-Yes. We can’t stand for this.
Come on, please. Out.
Everybody out so quick as possible.
Everybody must wait outside.
All passengers must wait outside.
Please go.
No good being undignified, old man.
No, quite right.
Come on. Please, please, please,
please. Come on. Come on.
Come on. So. Please.
Please. Please.
Oh, Major. May I phone Munich
to notify them of our delay?
Of course.
My absence may provide
the opportunity for Fraulein Bomasch
to approach her father.
It might help.
You seem to have made
a considerable impression
on the lady, Major.
I apologize for
doubting your capabilities.
Stay on guard here.
See that no one enters or leaves.
Understand? No one.
-That man who spoke to you,
did you know him?
-Yes, I did. A fellow called Caldicott.
It’s probably the first time
he’s ever left England before
the end of the cricket season.
-Just my luck.
He gave me a very nasty moment.
-No one would have guessed it.
I was a member of the Foreign Office
operatic society.
Do you know I once played Pooh-Bah
to the Foreign Secretary’s Ko-Ko?
-Have you thought of any way
of getting us out of this?
-I have.
A car will be waiting at Munich
to take us to headquarters.
We'll be quite a crowd,
and I shall ask for a second car
so that we can be alone.
-Suppose they don’t give it to us.
-They will.
Because by that time, we shall
be on the verge of persuading
your father to work for Germany.
You, on the other hand,
must be asking for time to think.
-You get the idea?
-Yes, but —
Then we only have
the chauffeur to deal with.
And after that — Switzerland.
-Switzerland?
-Well, we can hardly break through
the Siegfried line.
Yes, but Switzerland’s a long way
from Munich.
If we can bluff them
into giving us that car, we'll make it.
So from now on, Mr. Bomasch,
you’ve got to make up your mind...
whether to keep your armor plating
or let it go rusty.
-Is that quite clear?
-I think so.
And you’re still so crazy about me
that you would sell the armor plating
for a very small lock of my hair.
All right.
You can’t sit here!
-Why not?
-This truck is required.
Come on. Off, off, off, off, off, off.
I suppose these bags
aren’t required too?
Off, off, off, off, off, off, off.
Pushed about from pillar to post
by this railway ever since
we got on the train.
-Everything we sit on
seems to be required.
-It’s monstrous.
-We shall write to
the company about this.
-Hmm!
You’re not at war with England yet,
you know.
But you are mistaken.
France declared war this afternoon.
Und England declared war
this morning. So!
Achtung!
War.
Yes.
-Good heavens.
-What’s the matter?
My golf clubs.
Where are they?
I lent them to Max in Berlin.
Like a fool, I said he needn’t
bring them back till next Wednesday.
Probably seen the last of them.
Yes. I expect they'll require them
for something or other.
I read in the paper that
they’re pulling up park railings.
I don’t see the connection, old man.
Well, your clubs are steel, aren’t they?
-Yes.
-So.
There you are then.
Whip shafts too.
Especially made for me.
Why not get in touch with Max?
-How?
-On the telephone.
Ask him to send them
to London immediately.
It’s a desperate chance,
but it’s worth taking.
I shall never be able to replace them.
-Oh, uh, telephone?
-Hmm?
Stationmaster’s office.
Captain Strasse? Marsen here.
-I’m speaking from Kurtbaden.
-Oh, I beg your pardon.
It concerns Major Herzoff, sir.
I think a full inquiry
should be made at once...
in view of something
which happened a few minutes ago.
A few minutes ago?
You mean he’s with you?
Admiral Hassinger
gave him the authority.
Hassinger did? He never told me.
That’s very suspicious.
Yes, but the admiral himself
introduced him.
I'll ask him. I'll phone you back.
Uh, what is your number there?
Yes, yes, yes. In a few minutes.
Admiral Hassinger, please.
Hello?
I want a long-distance call to Berlin.
Oliver 2-4-double 6.
What? Yes.
Yes, of course it’s important.
-It’s all in German.
-Hmm.
What?
Well, how long then?
Oh, all right.
Blasted junction’s
engaged by the military.
They'll call me back.
These people seem to have no idea
of business as usual.
If I were asked
to give a snap judgment,
I should say that was an ‘‘S.’’
-More like an ‘‘F.’’
-I do not know, sir.
I used to know someone
who made his S’s like that.
-Someone in the War Office?
-Well, no.
Ach. We can’t afford to waste time.
You didn’t give him
permission to travel
with the prisoners, did you, sir?
No, no. But he may have assumed it.
If you remember, we more or less
gave him carte Blanche.
The only thing is to check up
with the War Office, sir.
-I suppose so.
-War Office.
If he’s right, this will be
very serious for you, Kampfeldt.
Very serious indeed.
The letter was addressed to you.
There’s no denying that, Kampfeldt.
Quite right. I’m afraid I shall have
to sack my secretary.
Hello?
--That'll be our call.
Aufschliessen!
Hmm! What infernal impudence.
I'll bet it’s my call.
Marsen speaking. Yes, sir.
Listen, Marsen. You were right.
We have been completely fooled.
Herzoff is not known at the War Office.
There is no officer of that name
on the army list.
Then, uh —
Yes, sir. Obviously. An enemy agent.
I say, Charters,
there’s another phone in there.
What? Oh. Lucky.
--Hello? Hello? Hello!
-Gone dead.
-Hello!
-Why not try the thingamy? Yeah.
-You know, the... gadget.
-Oh.
Hello —
It’s the extension.
That chap out there.
Well, perhaps he'll be off the line
in a minute.
-Shh!
-What’s up?
They’re talking about what’s-his-name.
You know, Herzoff.
No. He doesn’t suspect.
Yes, sir. I see.
All passengers aboard, please!
No time to stand here now, sir.
The train is leaving.
What?
Listen, we can’t afford to take risks.
Carry on with Herzoff to Munich.
Let him think he’s getting away with it.
Understand?
I'll get on to army headquarters there.
Very good, sir.
All passengers aboard, please!
-Everybody on the train!
-What is it?
Well, as far as I can make out,
Herzoff isn’t Herzoff.
-What?
-No.
They’re sending an escort to
arrest him — when we get to Munich.
-Herzoff?
-Yes.
Well — Then —
-Listen, if — if Herzoff isn’t Herzoff —
-What?
-Well, he must be Dicky Randall.
-Yes.
Everybody on the train!
All passengers aboard, please!
All passengers
on the last two coaches only!
All passengers aboard!
-All passengers aboard.
-After you, Major.
All passengers
on the last two coaches only.
on the last two coaches.
All passengers aboard.
All passengers
on the last two coaches only.
on the last two coaches.
All passengers aboard.
Keep within call. I shall need you
at Munich, perhaps before.
-One thing emerges
very clearly from all this.
-Caldicott!
-The train! There it goes!
Oh, my, my! That’s a mess!
-That was a near thing.
I thought we were going to be in
this infernal country for the duration.
Oh, my Lord.
Don’t anticipate, old man.
What were you saying
just now about something
emerging very clearly?
-I said?
-Mmm.
-When?
-On the platform.
-About something emerging?
-Mmm.
What was it?
-What was what?
-What emerged.
-You never said.
-Oh.
We do not wish to persuade you
to become a National Socialist,
Herr Bomasch.
I explained that to your daughter.
Have I not?
And you may work
wherever you choose, Father.
-Isn’t that so?
-Quite.
-After all, we should have our freedom.
-I know, my dear.
But freedom is strangely interpreted
in this country.
I do not agree with you,
Herr Bomasch.
Freedom in Germany is a great
advance on freedom elsewhere.
It’s properly organized and controlled
by the state.
I’d much rather
we kept politics out of it.
Herr Bomasch unfortunately
refuses to understand...
the sacred importance
of the Nazi world mission.
-His stay in England perhaps.
-No doubt. A corrupt influence.
A corrupt country.
Controlled by
international Freemasons
and the Jew Churchill.
But since you wish it, Herr Bomasch,
we will drop politics...
and discuss it
from a more personal basis.
I’m certain, Charters,
that what you were about to say...
was that we’ve stumbled
on something pretty serious.
There’s no doubt which side
Randall’s playing for.
-Ours?
-Yes.
Yes. That’s what
was emerging so clearly.
It’s up to us to find some way
of warning him.
Yes. Come on. Let’s find him.
-I say, Caldicott.
-Yes?
-Do you think
we’re wise rushing into this?
-How do you mean?
Well, I mean we’ve no proof
that Randall’s working for England.
-Well, everything points to it.
-Yes, but is that enough?
We’re enemy aliens...
and these Nazis are pretty free
with their firing party.
Hmm. Well, ought we to let that
stand in our way?
Well, certainly not.
I mean if — if we were certain.
As it is,
we’ve just got to bear it in mind.
I don’t see what else he can be doing.
For all we know,
he may be an international crook.
Crooks don’t generally play
for the Gentlemen.
Raffles did.
That’s fiction.
Still, you may be right, Charters.
Of course, if we were certain,
we’d do our duty and take the risk.
Yes, of course.
As it is, I can get on with Mein Kampf.
Haven’t got out of Hitler’s boyhood yet.
And, Herr Bomasch,
what is even more important...
your daughter will be able to live
with you or wherever she pleases.
-You must give me time to think.
-Certainly.
We should be in Munich in...
40 minutes.
Indeed. For the first time,
I will be sorry when the journey’s over.
Yes. I — I can believe that.
I think we should
order something to eat.
An excellent idea.
Just in case we do not
find headquarters in a very...
hospitable frame of mind.
-Please.
-Oh, sorry.
You don’t choose to stand up
when a German officer passes?
You see, we’re English.
Your passports.
Oh, beg your pardon.
You’re quite right.
The English should not stand up.
They should go down
on their fat bellies and crawl.
-Now look here!
-So, you are standing up.
Very well. We shall generously permit
you to run back to England...
no doubt to find yourselves safe jobs.
Meanwhile, you may sit down.
-‘‘Fat bellies.’’
-‘‘Safe jobs.’’
As if they weren’t all
taken by now anyway.
Caldicott, this is absolutely
and finally the last straw.
-Yes, Charters.
-We'll warn Dicky Randall at once,
come what may.
I’m with you, old man.
It’s things like that
that bring it home to you.
Sandwiches, biscuits. Yes, sir.
Will you take tea substitute
or coffee substitute?
Tea for me, please.
-Tea.
-Fine.
He’s in there.
That Gestapo fellow’s there too.
Yes. A couple of
storm troopers in there.
How the devil are we
going to pass him the word
without that fellow spotting it?
-We’ve got to do it somehow.
-Yes.
Of course, he —
he might come out for a minute.
I mean, most people do.
We must act, Charters. It’s no good
hanging about on the off chance.
Excuse, please.
-Wait a minute. That steward.
-What about him?
Well, he’s bound to come back
sometime to bring their order.
By Jove, yes.
Here he comes.
-?? (whistling)
-Excuse, please.
-Oh, what —
what time do we get to Munich?
-In about 30 minutes, sir.
Thank you.
-All right?
-Yes. I put it underneath a doughnut.
Good. What?
But how do you know they’re for him?
Well, I suddenly remembered
that Dicky Randall always
had doughnuts...
sent up to his room for afternoon tea.
That’s very clever of you, old man.
-Better get along there, hey?
-Mmm, right.
-Oh, my Lord.
-Why, what’s up?
Why, I’m — I’m wondering
if it was doughnuts.
-What?
-I — I believe it was rock cakes.
Have you made all arrangements
for transport at Munich, Marsen?
Every arrangement, sir.
-Will there be more than one car?
-Almost certainly two.
Then let’s see, that will make seven.
Rather a crowd.
I think in order to finish my talk
with Herr Bomasch, you had better
take the second car.
Very good, sir.
I believe Herr Bomasch
is really beginning to see that
I am doing my best to help him.
I’m sure he knows that.
Yes, yes, Major.
Your attitude has been
most reasonable.
You must remember it’s
only a few hours since Father
was taken out of England by force.
Captain Marsen
was only obeying orders.
Members of the Gestapo are
frequently asked to perform duties...
which others find too objectionable.
Some are objectionable.
Others I find extremely satisfying.
I often envy you your opportunities.
What is that, the bill?
I will pay.
No, please. I am escorting the party.
My dear Marsen, it’s my privilege.
In fact, it is an order.
Terrible. The way prices
have gone up already.
Excuse me.
-Yes, I-I’m Randall.
-How are you, old man?
-You remember me?
-Yes.
-This is Charters,
an old friend of mine.
-How do you do? Well, what is it?
-We don’t know what
you’re up to, of course.
-Never mind about that.
But whatever it is,
you appear to be on the spot.
Tell him about it, Charters.
Well, I was phoning Berlin
about my golf clubs.
By the way,
I’m resigned to the fact I shall
never see them again, Caldicott.
-Yes, well, get on with it.
-I was just coming to that.
I was telephoning
and got on the other chap’s line —
you know, that Gestapo fellow.
I overheard him saying they were
sending a military escort...
to arrest you when you get to Munich.
You see, you’re rumbled.
They know that you’re not Herzoff.
Now listen. I can’t tell you everything.
There isn’t time.
But I’ve got to get
that old man and the girl
out of this country at all costs.
Oh, a — an official job.
Are you two fellows game to help me?
What, against Germany?
I'll say we are
after all they’ve done to us.
What do you say, Caldicott?
-Absolutely, old man.
Backs to the wall.
-I hope not.
I say, could you give me
a little more room to think?
-Is there any tea left?
-Yes, I think so, Ulrich.
There’s no time for tea.
We reach Munich in a few minutes.
Oh, time for just one cup.
Cake, darling?
No, thank you.
I am afraid I must ask you
to drop this little comedy.
It is very entertaining, but I have
certain formalities to attend to.
Comedy? What do you mean?
Oh, thank you.
You’re merely pretending
to be infatuated with this man.
There’s no such person
as Major Herzoff.
He’s a British agent trying to get you
and your father out of Germany.
You must be crazy. Ulrich.
I don’t propose to waste the time
of the Gestapo denying it.
Thank you.
You — You’re going to
give yourself up?
Well, they have lots of proof,
Mr. Bomasch.
An escort will be waiting at Munich
to take you in charge.
You can’t do this.
-He’s an enemy agent.
-Weren’t you?
Didn’t you do exactly the same
as he’s doing?
With a slight but important difference.
I wasn’t caught.
-Are you just going to
sit there and do nothing?
-Now, please don’t make a scene.
-Don’t you realize what this means?
-Yes, I do.
But he has a gun, and I haven’t.
And he’s got a couple
of reserves next door.
Who do you take me for —
Bulldog Drummond?
Can’t you be serious even now?
I told you this would happen.
I told you your scheme
was absolutely childish,
but you wouldn’t listen to me.
Why didn’t you stay in England
instead of coming over here...
and deliberately throwing
your life away, you fool?
I have no time to listen
to this ridiculous display.
Steiner! Dreimund!
If there is more than one major
on the train...
how are we to know
which one to arrest?
Our man’s got a Gestapo officer
watching him.
Hmm. Who has not these days?
--The train.
-Heil Hitler.
-Heil Hitler!
Marsen. I’m on instruction
from Fifth Army Headquarters
to arrest Major Herzoff.
I fear you will need a stretcher.
The prisoner tried to escape,
and I had to, uh — to deal with him.
You will find him in
the last compartment, Coach 66.
Uh, what — what transport have you?
-Two cars.
-Excellent.
Now, this is Herr Axel Bomasch
from Harska and his daughter.
They are in protective custody,
and I have instructions...
to take them to General Von Komwitz
without delay.
With your permission,
I will use one of the cars.
-Certainly.
-I'll leave you to take charge
of the prisoner.
Will you show me my car?
-Brunner.
Take this S.S. officer to the car.
-Coach 66 you said?
-The last compartment.
Full length on the seat.
Sergeant, get a stretcher
from the stationmaster and follow me.
Olson, you will take the S.S. officer
and his party in your car.
One moment.
Is your chauffeur to be trusted?
I think so. He is a very old member
of the party.
Anti-Russian perhaps. I think
I’d rather take one of my own men.
-I’m traveling to a place
of the greatest secrecy.
-Very good.
-You will not be needed, Olson.
-Very good, sir.
Rumplemeyer, you will drive.
-Heil Hitler.
Come on, quick.
Right, man! Right!
You’re not in England.
-Oh, I’d forgotten.
Not much of a life, a secret agent.
And the pay is bad too, sir.
I was just thinking, Charters.
In the last war, the army took over
Lord’s Cricket Ground
for drilling troops on.
-Wonder if they'll do it this time.
-Shortsighted, you know.
Better pull up here, Charters.
We can’t get to Switzerland
by any of the main roads.
Let me take over, will you?
Age around 22, height 5’4’’.
Slim figure, dark, brown eyes.
That’s the lot.
Phone these descriptions to all
stations within a hundred-mile radius.
A report has just come in, sir,
that the car has left the city
by the south road.
So they are making for Switzerland.
-We take the road.
-Very good.
There’s one thing that’s worrying me,
Randall, old man.
It may be silly of me, of course, but —
How exactly are we going
to get across the Swiss frontier?
I know a little place
where I used to go climbing —
about 8,000 feet up where
Switzerland and Germany meet.
You’re not going to ask us
to hang about on ropes, I hope.
I’m not, but they may. There’s
a narrow road leads right to the top.
-What’s over the top?
-Switzerland.
-Anything in between?
-6,000-feet drop.
-Well, how can we, uh —
-Skip it.
Skip it?
-There’s a car following us!
-Is there? Well, here we go.
Don’t let them get away!
I'll have to change the wheel!
Watch the road, Charters.
Hello! Anybody here? Caldicott.
Anybody around?
-Switzerland.
Good morning to you, sir.
Good morning.
-Are you in charge here?
-Yes. There’s only me.
-I want to cross to Switzerland.
-Now, sir?
-Yes, now.
-But we’re at war.
I had orders yesterday
to close the teleferic.
My orders come from a higher source.
Higher than the chief of police
at Maxberg?
-Gestapo headquarters at Munich.
-Oh.
I have been instructed to show
this lady and gentleman safely
out of Germany.
I better ring Christopher.
Yes. Right away.
-There’s a car coming.
Looks like them.
-There are five of them altogether.
-Keep an eye on them.
-How are the goats, Christopher?
Yes, thank you, Christopher. I got it.
And the butter.
Do you want to be dismissed
for incompetence?
They'll be leaving in about
two minutes, Christopher.
I shall require to see your papers, sir.
Have you got your passports?
How long does this take
to cross the valley?
-About four minutes.
-Once it’s in midair,
can it be stopped?
Why, yes, sir,
if anyone wanted to stop it.
Will you follow me to the office?
This way, please.
-Can you see them?
-No, but I can hear the engine.
-How does this thing work?
-That shouldn’t be difficult.
-Well, how?
-Yes, obviously, this starts it.
-Yes?
-Yes. This is the speed regulator.
-Speed regulator, right. Get in quick.
-All of you! Quick! Caldicott!
-What about you?
-I'll start it and then jump on.
They’re here!
-Come on. Jump in.
-Yes, but they-they'll stop us
halfway across.
Get in, will you!
Come on! Quickly!
There it is!
Stand aside!
Olson, go around back!
The téléférique!
They’re potting at us!
Duck down!
Get down there and draw his fire.
I'll get in over the roof.
Right.
Come here and stop the machinery!
Come back!