[music playing]
[singing christmas carols]
[laughter]
Now, matron, we mustn't
keep Santa Claus waiting.
Santa Claus!
[singing christmas carols]
Merry Christmas.
Oh, Countess!
Merry Christmas, [inaudible].
But Countess!
Merry Christmas, doctor.
You have no right to be here!
You can't keep me out of this.
But...
Me, I've never been fond of
children's Christmas parties,
- and I'm [inaudible].
- But...
After all, this is much my
nursing home as it is yours.
- But...
- Or hers.
Well, nearly as much.
Of course it is, but you have just
had a very serious operation.
Whose fault's that?
It was you who kept on
about my grumbling appendix.
Grumbling appendix, indeed.
I believe you invented
the whole thing.
[singing christmas carols]
[inaudible]
Happy Christmas.
Happy Christmas, Jean.
Happy Christmas, Francois.
May we see mother?
We'd like to show her the cake.
Oh, I'm sure it'll be all right.
Miss Cavell's not about.
She's not supposed to know this.
Yes, I know, Jean.
She's in the children's room.
I'm sure it'll be great.
Thanks.
Matron, the Countess has called.
Countess?
Yes, she's with Dr. Depage
in your sitting room.
[inaudible].
[inaudible], the cake is here.
Would you like to see it?
Look.
Jean made it all by
himself, didn't you, Jean?
Good boy, Jean.
[inaudible]
I made the icing.
Countess, what are you doing here?
I'm walking.
Merry Christmas.
I told her to rest,
but she's [inaudible].
Oh, stuff and nonsense.
Clear off.
I don't need you.
Who's is that?
Madame [inaudible], Suzanne.
She's quite a character.
Do come here.
Want to go to the Countess?
Would you [inaudible]
come to Madame?
Matron, could you come to the
small ward at once, please.
I have to go and see
young Madame Rappard.
She's very poor.
I may need you doctor.
The excitement...
the boys were here.
They have a surprise for you.
A cake for the children starving.
And she wanted so much to see it.
I'm not supposed to know.
I understand.
Don't spoil it for them.
No, I won't.
Merry Christmas, children.
Merry Christmas, [inaudible].
[cheering]
Waiting for you.
Please, go.
[SOFTLY] Stay with her yourself.
Send down if you need me.
Yes.
[children cheering]
What a beautiful cake!
This is you, I suppose.
It was Madame Rappard's
idea, wasn't it, Jean.
Yes, mother wanted to thank you.
We all did.
How very kind.
Is it as good as it looks?
Would you like to
try it, Miss Cavell?
I think you better
cut it, Francois.
[music playing]
Oh.
Your mother, rest her soul,
would be so proud of you.
Thank you, grandmammy.
Oh, goodbye, grandmammy.
Don't worry.
It'll soon be over.
Goodbye, Francois.
Be sure and take care
of grandma and the shop.
Of course.
Look, Jean.
My first bake!
Ah, it's as light as a feather!
Don't worry, [inaudible].
Keep [inaudible].
[music playing]
Goodbye, Jean.
Be brave.
Be brave!
[music playing]
[scream]
Madame [inaudible]!
Madame Countess, why don't we
go before we are all killed!
Leave the Chateau?
Certainly not.
Nothing would induce me to.
[bomb sound]
Madame la Countess,
Madame la Countess!
Stop making a noise
like a stuck pig.
Charlotte, pick up that bell.
[FEARFULLY] All right,
Madame la Countess.
Straighten the picture.
You know how I hate
crooked pictures.
But what is the use?
In a few moments we
will be all dead!
It would only be anticipating
the inevitable by a few years.
[bomb sound]
Albert...
Yes.
The picture.
[music playing]
They're only a few miles off.
[inaudible].
Did you hear what [inaudible]?
Burning the village
and killing the wounded!
[loud] They are [inaudible]!
[music playing]
Your poor mother, rest her soul,
would rather you'd been
born blind than to have
you look on such a sight.
[music playing]
[soft music playing]
Good evening, Madame Rappard.
Matron, I am glad to see you.
I'm so worried about Jean.
Why, what's happened?
They said he's been
captured by the Germans.
Madame Rappard, you musn't
believe all you hear.
Brussels is so full of rumors.
Yes, but they say they're
shooting all the prisoners.
[inaudible]
Jean!
Oh, Jean!
[inaudible]
[inaudible], my boy.
I was captured, but I escaped.
They saw me in the square
and they're after me!
Don't let them catch me!
No!
Atten hut!
Madame Rappard.
[german word] hut!
Quick!
Quickly.
Oh.
[inaudible].
[speaking in german].
Ah, English.
I am.
Who lives here?
This lady.
As you see, she is not very well.
Are there any
questions I can answer?
We are building troops.
How many she take here?
Four.
Jean.
They are building
soldiers in the house.
Keep very quiet.
[speaking german].
Madame Rappard.
[speaking german]
Where [inaudible]?
You have to be very brave.
They're building
soldiers in the house.
Oh, what are we going to do?
What are we going to do?
Now, don't worry.
But they'll be sure to find him.
Keep him hidden until after curfew.
Get some of his old
things together,
and I'll come back and take
him to my nursing home.
Oh!
Oh, God bless you!
[bell ringing]
[dog barking]
Fraulein, do you know
it is past curfew?
I do.
You should be in your house.
I'm on my way to
a very urgent case.
[bell ring]
We might be able to get him away.
One of the soldiers is
asleep in there by the stove.
We must try.
Is everything ready?
Yes, he's got his
clothes in there with him.
Come along then.
[loud noise]
Oh.
What happened?
Oh, I've taken every
bit of skin off my knee.
That's what comes of having
a horde of men in the house.
Oh.
[music playing]
Reported numerous escapes.
Prisoners of war
from temporary camps.
Probably seeking
refuge in Brussels.
Immediate action demanded.
Captain, you will take the
necessary steps to apprehend
any refugee soldiers and
advise the civil population of
the penalty for harboring them.
[inaudible]
What is it?
Search all houses.
And if you find anyone
looking suspicious,
arrest him, and report
immediately to your sergeant.
I'm one of the lucky ones.
If you can see some of the others
lying wounded in
trenches and shell holes.
If you can only do something
for them like you did for me.
We have to think of you now, Jean.
We must do something quickly
to get you out of Brussels.
Miss Cav... Miss Cavell.
I must see her at once!
I'll call [inaudible].
Will you wait in the sitting room?
[inaudible].
Oh!
Oh, my dear!
They're making a house-to-house
search for the prisoners!
Oh, sister.
Please return to the ward.
Now, what is it?
Soldiers.
The soldiers, I heard them talking.
Madame Rappard, you must keep calm!
Where is he?
He's quite safe.
He's up in one of the small wards.
Oh, they'll be sure
to find him there!
They'll be sure to find
him there, [inaudible].
You must rest quietly.
I'll bring him down and
we'll take him to the cellar.
Oh, yes!
Yes, um, that will be much safer!
Halt!
[speaking german]
[inaudible]
Go there, Jean.
Over here.
Now bolt the door inside and don't
open unless you hear my voice.
Yes.
Wait!
Listen up.
Help me with this.
[speaking german]
[music playing]
[inaudible].
You cannot go up there without
the permission of the matron.
What is it, sister.
They say they have
an order to search
the home for escape prisoners.
Very well, they will search.
[inaudible]
[music playing]
Good evening, Madame [inaudible].
Why, Mason, what brings you here?
Is there somewhere
we can talk quietly.
Why yes.
Down in the cabin.
There's only my good
for nothing husband
cooking supper down
there, and you know him.
That's as good as being alone.
You remember Madame Rappard?
You mean that poor thing in the bed
next to mine who left
those two nice boys?
It's about the older boy Jean.
He was taken prisoner
but he managed
to escape and make his way
back to his grandmother.
I have been hiding him, and now I
wonder would you help by
taking him across the frontier
into Holland?
Of course I will.
When will he be here?
We're due to leave at
7:00 in the morning.
Oh, I'll see that he gets here.
And when you're
across the frontier,
would you send this
card just to let his
grandmother know that he's safe.
Of course, I will.
[bells chiming]
God bless you, Miss Cavell.
[music playing]
Jean!
We're at the frontier.
They'll search.
Keep quiet.
What happened [inaudible]?
Oh.
In there?
Oh, cognac ala masa moulya.
Well, how about one?
[speaking german]
Bottoms up.
You're welcome.
Oh, Colonel.
Would you be an angel and
post this card for me?
What?
You post the card for me?
Oh, yeah. [speaking german]
Yes.
Thank you, General.
[music playing]
Madame la Countess!
Madame la Countess?
[inaudible]
What is.
[inaudible].
They must have caught
them hiding in the woods.
What are they doing with them?
The... They're going to shoot them!
Madame la Countess!
[speaking german]
Don't be a fool, Charlotte.
Of course they're not.
You don't shoot prisoners of war.
[gun shots]
[inaudible], you hear?
[inaudible]
You foul brute.
You're a disgrace to your uniform.
You hear me?
Do you understand what I'm saying?
I can't speak very
much your language.
But I know what you say.
Then why did you do it?
Why did you do it?
It was commanded.
You mean... oh, my God, [inaudible].
That's horrible!
Madame, war is horrible.
They were in civilian clothing.
According to the log of
war, that makes them spies.
They shot them.
I never thought I'd
live to see such things.
Horrible.
Everywhere, all
over the countryside
they're hiding out
in barns and ditches.
Most of them wounded, sick.
Charlotte, told me that if you
go to the far side of the woods
you can hear them
moaning, crying for help.
Is the matron in?
Yes.
Can I see her?
Oh, I have such good news for her.
Well, I'm sure she'll
see you, Madame Rappard.
Thank you.
He's safe!
I just got the card!
Oh, God bless you.
God bless you.
Oh, Madame la Countess,
she saved my boys' life.
God will bless her.
[crying] God will bless her.
[music playing]
JEAN [VOICEOVER]: I'm
one of the lucky ones.
You can see some of the
others lying wounded
in trenches and shell holes.
If you can only do something
for them like you did for me.
MADAME COUNTESS [VOICEOVER]:
Charlotte told me
that if you go to the
far side of the woods
you can hear them
moaning, crying for help.
[music playing]
[inaudible], an
angel from heaven.
Not quite, but I'm well on my way.
Snatched from the jaws
of death, I called it.
[inaudible] you'll be
quite safe in the ward
as civilian patients.
And then we shall arrange
to get you into Holland.
I'm afraid it will be some
time before you can move,
though... your foot is septic.
Go on, is it?
Yes. [inaudible].
Bungey, the name is, Miss... Private
Bungey of the East Kent regiment,
commonly known as the Buffs.
We'll have to be
especially careful, Bungey,
or your English will give you away.
Ello, ello, ello.
Woah.
Careful over the cobbles, cabby.
Yes, it is a little unsteady,
but the Countess has never
driven an ambulance before.
Oh, I see.
Blimey!
Oh, sister.
I have four cases outside I
wish to isolate in a small ward.
Will you see that it's made ready?
Yes, matron.
Um, there's a villager to see you.
I'll deal with that later.
But the officer said it was urgent.
- Officer?
- Yes.
He's a German officer.
He's in your sitting room.
What is his regiment?
He didn't say.
He said he wished to
speak to you personally.
Very well. I will see him.
Attend to the ward, sister.
Yes, ma'am.
An officer has called to see me.
Drive around the back of the
house and wait for me there.
Madame Cavell?
I'm Dr. Gunther of
the Army Medical Corp.
We are transferring the first
contingent of our wounded
here today.
You will remove all civilian
patients to their own houses.
All Belgium, French and
British wounded must be handed
over to the German authorities.
Very well, Dr. Gunther.
They're bringing German
wounded into the home.
Well, what are we going
to do with these men?
We can keep them down in
the cellar for a few days.
That's where I keep Jean Rappard.
All Belgium and French
soldiers hiding in the town
are to be delivered up
as prisoners of war.
They don't know us
yet, Madame Rappard.
yet, [inaudible].
Remember [inaudible]?
What are you looking
for, my friend?
They've rolled into [inaudible].
How many?
Four.
[music playing]
[gasping]
I'm afraid it's hopeless.
Just a few minutes now.
Poor boy.
So young.
[speaking german]
What is he saying?
He thinks he's a prisoner of war.
He wants to be set free.
[speaking german]
You shall be free.
Very soon now.
Sorry if I'm late, ladies.
Oh, no, Madame la Countess.
We were learning.
Eager for your work, eh?
Yes, indeed, ma'am.
Good.
He's sleeping.
If I can be of any help, please
don't hesitate to send for me.
Thanks.
What is it, nurse?
The Countess is here.
She's in your private sitting room.
I have to go down to the
small isolation ward first.
Please stay here, nurse.
Some friends have
promised to help and
we're making plans to leave.
Tomorrow night, I hope.
Use the identification
cards coming through.
[speaking french], bien.
Merci.
How about me?
Oh, no Bungey.
You must wait until
your foot is better.
I thought you said it
wasn't skeptic anymore.
No, I didn't, but you'll be
too dangerous for the others.
I'm sorry, Bungey.
Good night.
Bonsoir.
[inaudible], Bungey.
[inaudible]
Good evening, Countess.
Only three of the
men will be leaving.
The English lad is not
fit for the journey.
He must go later.
Were you able to get the
identification cards?
[inaudible]
Madame Moulin, when
can barge will leave?
Whenever you wish, matron.
Tomorrow night then.
And Madame Rappard,
is everything ready?
Everything is ready, matron.
Francois will guide
them to the back.
Francois will watch
the back of the house.
You will watch the front.
[bells ringing]
Courage, Madame Rappard.
You have your identification cards?
Oui Madame la Countess.
[knock on door]
[inaudible]
Four men [inaudible].
All clear.
Follow your instructions implicitly
and you'll soon be out of danger.
Bon voyage.
[inaudible]
Well, Bungey, your turn.
Don't think so, [inaudible].
Unkind word and I shall
cry my bloomin' eyes out.
Would you be an angel
again, [inaudible]?
[speaking german]
[music playing]
Gentlemen, the new military
governor of Brussels,
[inaudible] General [inaudible].
General, [inaudible], head
of the political department
[inaudible].
Captain Heinrichs, Chief of
the [inaudible] espionage.
Lt. Schmidt, [inaudible].
Captain Heinrichs, [inaudible].
Captain Heinrichs, you
are head of [inaudible].
Yavolt, Excellence.
Will you look at that.
Would you mind, Excellence, tell me
how this came into your hands?
It was taken from
a derelict Belgium
soldier who was captured last night
on the outskirts of Brussels.
But Excellence, this should
have come directly to me.
I have given instruction
that all papers referring
to the traffic of escape
prisoners and derelict soldiers
shall pass through my hand.
[inaudible], Excellence...
I want no argument,
Captain Heinrichs.
I have been sent to
[inaudible] to restore
discipline amongst the population
and the [inaudible] occupation.
And I mean to do so.
This traffic and escape prisoners
has been going on long enough!
I am convinced there is
an organization behind it.
This map is the clear proof.
Unravel this, and we'll get to
the heart of your organization.
[singing]
One of these days, I
suppose these simple Germans
will wonder, if no other cargo goes
over the frontier, [inaudible].
[inaudible] poker player,
I'd say we had a full house.
Patrick Doland?
Yes, ma'am.
Issac Rosenthal?
Yes, [inaudible].
James Colsac?
Ey, [inaudible].
What about me, Miss?
Can't I go on the next load?
We'll see how you are, Bungey.
Oh, I'm all right.
Look at me!
London [inaudible] it is.
It's all right.
I did it on purpose.
[inaudible]
Oh, I'm not, am I?
Now will all those whose
names I've called give me
their Army identification card.
Good night, you all.
Good night.
Here.
Thank you.
You know, [inaudible].
I don't want to grumble, sir.
I [inaudible] with a nice
square meal after [inaudible].
We're lucky to get in at all.
It must be very
different [inaudible].
[inaudible].
But what wouldn't I give for
a nice pint of [inaudible].
Perhaps [inaudible].
And then perhaps a nice
stable kidney pudding
with plenty of
kidneys and the gravy
running all over the base.
How many can you take on
the next trip, Madame Moulin.
As many as you like.
I don't think these [inaudible].
There's seven more
will be here on Friday.
Then 11 must go tomorrow night.
I can take them.
[inaudible] off and
transferred to the German
identification cards.
Can that be done by tomorrow night?
Yes.
You, Madame Rappard?
It's all arranged.
Francois and I will guide you
as far as the [inaudible].
And the other boys, we'll take
them on the tram [inaudible].
Mama, look out!
[music playing]
[inaudible]!
British!
Yes.
We must take him to Brussels.
Oui.
We must hide him.
[speaking german]
[inaudible], clean
up [inaudible].
[inaudible]
Edith, my dear, this
must be the last.
We must stop it.
How can we stop?
While any of these men
are needing our help,
we must go on.
If one of them should
be caught and shot
will be our fault. Swab.
But we searched the
whole wood, Herr Captain
and can find no trace of him.
Lt. Schmidt.
Offer a reward, 500
francs, for any information
leading to his
arrest, dead or alive.
Search every hospital, and instruct
all doctors and officers to
report any unusual cases.
Yavolt, Herr Captain.
Lean heavily on me.
That's right.
[inaudible], but I must
get you downstairs.
If we meet anyone on
the way, don't speak.
Ah, Lt. von Schultz.
Your promotion is overdue.
Donka, el Captain.
Now this map indicates
a secret organization
going on [inaudible]
escape prisoners.
Yavolt, Herr Kapitan.
And I'm relying on you to uncover
this entire organization,
uh, Captain Schultz.
I will earn my
promotion, Herr Captain.
Madame la Countess.
Another one has arrived.
[inaudible] is he stable?
No, Madame la Countess.
This one came to the lodge.
He's waiting outside in the hall.
Ask him in.
Madame la Countess,
you have the reputation
for being a good friend.
Well?
I have escaped from
a German prison camp.
From what prison
camp did you escape?
[inaudible]
What nationality are you?
French.
What do you expect
me to do for you?
Help me to get out of
Belgium and back into France.
I am anxious to fight
again for my company.
Charlotte, take care
of this poor man.
See that he has food
and drink, and lock
the kitchen so that he won't
be disturbed while he's there.
Wee, Madame la Countess.
Merci, Madame la Countess.
This way, please.
Brussels 9046.
This Brussels 9046.
May I speak to the chief of police?
This is the Countess Mavon.
Would you send an escort to
the Chateau Mavon at once.
I have a French refugee
prisoner of war here.
I'm keeping him locked in
the kitchen until you arrive.
Not at all.
It's a very great pleasure.
Cavell.
We're being watched, my dear.
I was followed here by the
man talking to those workmen.
And last night a stool pigeon
flew into my [inaudible].
What did you do?
Pinched his wings
a bit and handed him
over to the German authorities.
I thought they'd understand
the same language.
He had the loveliest
Franco Prussian accent
you've ever heard, my dear.
Francois Rappard.
One.
What are you looking
for, my friend?
A safe road and a quick journey.
Who sent you?
Number 33.
Read it again.
"I have almost earned my
promotion, Herr Kapitan.
But I have not yet reached the
heart of the organization."
How [inaudible]?
Through Dr. Gunther.
Was addressed to him
to be delivered here.
Where is Countess?
At 149 [inaudible].
Oh, let me see.
That's the nursing home run by...
The English woman, Cavell.
I'm sure.
[buzzer sound]
Dr. Gunther.
This note.
I found it on my desk.
It must have been put there
by someone who knows the house.
Have you seen anything
suspicious here?
No, Herr Kapitan.
I've carried out the instructions,
but I've seen nothing.
What about the woman Cavell?
She's cooperative
and a generous person.
[inaudible] she's an English
woman and must be watched.
Fraulein Cavell.
Where does that lead to?
The boiler house.
I should like to see it.
Very well.
I will take you down myself.
You can hay or sneeze no, man.
I don't want to.
Now I've gone past it.
Fraulein Cavell.
A number of escape
prisoners have been making
their way out of the country.
It would be a very serious matter
for those who engage
in this traffic
if they should be caught.
Whether they were men or
women, Fraulein Cavell,
they would incur the
severest penalties.
It is our duty.
It is your duty.
Matron, are you all right?
So tired.
It's too much for you, matron.
Why don't you lay down...
[inaudible] suspect.
These men are in great danger.
We must get them away at once.
[inaudible], he's
not fit to be moved.
Send word to the
Countess, Madame Rappard,
Madame Moulin for tonight.
Yes, matron.
Now you know the routine.
You follow the guide
and in pointed groups
as far as Moulin.
There you will be handed
over to the other guide.
You have your identification cards?
Yes.
You know the password, safe
road and a quick journey.
Now I'll see if all is clear.
Goodbye, Bungey.
Don't forget your promise.
Not a drink till you are
safely across the frontier.
Nor you, Pierre.
No, we won't forget, Miss Cavell.
There's other things that I won't
forget neither... no
[inaudible], none of us.
God bless you.
Bye.
Au Revoir, Pierre.
Godspeed, Jacques.
Bonsoir.
Bungey.
Oh.
[inaudible]
What's that for?
Your supper.
Oh.
I thought that you wanted
me to get inside it.
It's a good one.
Comic.
I'll see you later.
Ey.
And maybe bring you some cognac.
Oh.
That's different, isn't it?
Here, here, what about Pierre
and the other [inaudible]?
I'll give them just five more
minutes and then we're off.
[inaudible].
I wonder what [inaudible].
Fantastic!
The whole of the German secret
service fooled by a few women!
Yes, [inaudible].
And I can tell you more than that.
I'm sure you can.
You're the clever one.
Yes.
And shall I tell you something?
You know who I am?
No.
I am Captain William Schultz of the
German military intelligence.
How many?
One.
Madame la Countess,
you will come with me
to Captain Heinrichs' office.
England, and to
play some cricket,
and to see [inaudible] again.
Norridge.
Yes, do you know it, matron?
It's my home.
Give it my love.
I demand to know why
I've been brought here.
You do not know?
I do not.
You are under arrest for
assisting prisoners of war
out of the country.
Now, all you do is follow the guide
and you will soon be safe.
Yes, matron.
I understand perfectly.
Don't you ever want to
go back home, not here
among all these foreigners?
There's only one
human race, my dear.
Yes, I suppose that's true.
What would they do if they found
out you had gotten me here?
I mean ought'n you to
hand me over to them
now that I'm all right again?
You think I've nursed
you back to life
to hand you over to be shot?
I'll see if everything's ready.
How dare you.
Officer [inaudible],
[speaking german].
Do you know this man?
Or this?
An informer and the worm.
I congratulate you on your
friends, Herr Captain.
We'll have to go without
your identification card.
Nothing's gone wrong, matron.
Oh, no, no.
You have your emergency ration?
- Yes, ma'am.
- Your money?
Yes.
Come along then.
All clear.
Goodbye, Richard.
Goodbye, matron.
I shall never be able
to thank you enough.
God bless you.
[inaudible] Miss Cavell,
I arrest you for harboring
escape prisoners of war.
[speaking german]
I've just seen the signal!
We're at the frontier.
There's danger.
You'll have to swim
forth 100 yards upstream,
and you'll be safe.
You Madame Moulin.
I am.
You're under arrest.
[speaking german]
Get your hands off me!
I don't like it, [inaudible].
I don't like it.
You can get no information
from the military authorities.
I hear unofficially
trial is imminent.
If you could establish
espionage it would be simple.
Yeah.
But we have no
[inaudible] evidence.
But there is an alternative.
We can charge her on a Section
58 of the military code which
makes furnishing
the enemy with men,
an offense punishable by death.
Go yourself and see the lawyer
representing Miss Cavell.
Tell him to impress upon the court
that she is a woman who has
sacrificed her life in all
this storm of hatred,
trying to create a refuge
of goodwill and forgiveness.
I will, sir.
But you mustn't stress yourself.
I will bring out all the
points made by your ministry
in my speech for her defense.
But your presence at the trial
would cause a great prejudice.
The German judges would feel
that you were exercising
a kind of supervision.
Oh, I wouldn't have that happen.
But you will keep us
well advised, won't you?
Of course.
I suppose at the worst it could
only be a term of imprisonment.
That's the worst.
Thank you.
Of course, you are
the public prosecutor
and I have no wish to
interfere with your conduct
of the case, [inaudible].
Certainly.
There may be a [inaudible]
of checks [inaudible]...
[inaudible]
that the military code
applies only to Germans
supplying the enemy with men.
A law which is good
enough for Germans
is good enough for these people.
Of course, we would have been
to see you before, matron,
if I'd been able to get a permit.
Yes, I know.
It seems more like seven
years than seven weeks
since you left.
It has been a long time.
Everything has progressing quite
satisfactorily with the home.
Oh, yes, matron.
We've been carrying on as
though you were with us.
That's right.
And you'll soon be back again
for the directors of Institute
have arranged for an advoca...
You're not permit to discuss
any matter in connection
with the trial.
Surely, I'm permitted to
tell Miss Cavell what...
You will discuss nothing with her
in connection with her case.
That is the condition
of your [inaudible]
under German military law.
That may be all right for
Germans, but I'm an American
and I think it's...
I'm not interested what you think.
They can't stop me from telling you
an attorney has been
engaged for your defense.
Mary, my dear, don't
distress yourself.
It can do no good.
It's all so unfair
to those of us who
know how much good you've done.
Oh, [inaudible].
I know just how you feel.
GERMAN GUARD [OFFSCREEN]:
Fraulein [inaudible].
Sister, take her back
and let her rest a while.
Yes, matron.
We'll come and see you soon.
That situation calls
for the severest penalty.
Pity [inaudible].
Leniency would only be
mistaken for a weakness.
OFFICER [OFFSCREEN]: The
charge then is to be [inaudible]
through the death penalty.
I wish an example made.
The network of conspiracy unravels,
but it's still [inaudible].
As far as purpose, the furnishing
of soldiers to the enemy.
Directed in Brussels
by this woman, Cavell,
and her accomplices
who are here on trial.
There has been steady traffic
to [inaudible] Germany,
and [inaudible] enemies under
this woman, Cavell's direction.
Men of military age have succeeded
in passing the frontier.
It remains to be seen
whether what has been charged
against them constitutes
their [inaudible],
or whether the true purpose
of this organization
was that of espionage.
[SARCASTICALLY] Espionage.
[inaudible]
Spying.
Spying
I wish to call the head of
our counter espionage, Captain
Heinrichs.
Captain Heinrichs.
You know [inaudible] Miss Cavell?
Yes.
Will you produce a
statement taken by yourself?
I do.
The statement taken
correct in every detail.
It was taken with every precaution.
No possibility of error.
Is it suggested that this
organization existed not only
for the purpose of providing
the enemy with men,
but also for espionage?
I have no proof of
that, [inaudible].
All of your witnesses
has been drawn from
military intelligence service.
Is there no independent
or civilian witnesses?
[speaking german]
[inaudible], I have one
important witness whose
evidence alone should be sufficient
to convict all the prisoners.
I call Francois Rappard.
Francois Rappard.
Francois!
Francois Rappard, do you
know the accused, Miss Cavell?
Yes.
Did you, at the request
of the woman Cavell,
conduct fugitive soldiers
through [inaudible] border?
Yes.
Did you hear them
say that they were
going back to join the Army
and fight against Germany?
Francois Rappard!
Did you hear them say they were
going back to join the Army
and fight against Germany?
[scream] Don't
tell them, Francois!
[crying] [inaudible]
I know, [inaudible].
I know, dear.
We are doing
everything in our power.
Yes, we know, Mr. Gibson,
and we're very grateful.
But we can't understand
why they wouldn't allow
you to be present at the trial.
Her defending counsel said it
would prejudice her if I did.
But he assured me she would
receive a perfectly fair trial,
and that he would do
his utmost independent
and the best of his ability.
Let the court put itself in
the position of this woman.
Dedicated as she had
been throughout her life
to the service of the helpless.
And ask themselves what they
would have done in the face
of the irresistible impulse to
assist those unhappy fugitives
whom she had hidden in her house,
or given assistance from her purse.
Her only motive in
acting as she has done
was to save men whom she
thought to be in danger
and help them escape
from the country.
She never for a moment
had it in her mind
to do an injury to Germany.
The law of Miss Cavell is
far above any military code.
A law infinitely higher than
war and the idea of [inaudible].
The life of that woman belongs
to the sick and wounded.
The lives that many Germans
soldiers owe to her skill
in the early days of the war dries
out against the
shedding of her blood
by the German authorities.
If what she has done is
deserving of punishment,
then detention for the
duration of the war
is the maximum penalty
that should be inflicted.
Could it be doubted
that this organization
was a premeditated
conspiracy to undermine
the German authorities?
Was it not plain from the fact
that the enemy was benefited
and Germany injured
by their action?
By their breach of law, these
people put in danger the lives,
and probably cause for
death of brave German
soldiers in the front line.
The head of this organization was
undoubtedly the woman Cavell.
It will be said that
she was a nurse.
A nurse has obligations
beyond military code.
To make use of her calling
as a cloak for recruiting
soldiers to the enemy
was a gross abuse
of her noble profession.
[german]
Miss Cavell, please.
Do you wish to say
anything further to what
has been said on your behalf?
I have nothing further to say.
You admit having assisted
soldiers to cross the frontier?
I do.
How many of these men did you
assist in leaving the country?
About 200.
Did you know the offense
is punishable with death?
I did.
Against the woman Cavell, I
demand the penalty of death.
[music playing]
The case against the
woman Cavell is closed.
Sentence will be discussed
and put to the vote.
[music playing]
[inaudible].
Please do not be afraid.
He demands the extreme
penalty, but they
would never carry it out.
Thank you.
You are very kind.
[bell ring]
[inaudible]
I think we all seem sentimental
because she's a woman.
Precisely.
Is there any thought in your mind
this woman was the leading spirit?
None whatever.
Then there is no more to be said.
I confirm the sentence.
[inaudible]
Have an order drawn
up for my signature,
directing it to be carried
out as early as possible.
Gentlemen, good day.
[inaudible] Thank you.
My dear nurses.
Your charming letter
gave me great pleasure,
and your lovely flowers
have made my cell gay.
The roses are still fresh.
But the chrysanthemums did not
like prison any more than I do.
Hence, they did not live very long.
If you were in my
place you would realize
how precious liberty is.
But I hope by the time
this letter reaches you,
you will have better
news [inaudible].
[speaking german]
Fraulein Cavell, I
have to read to you
the sentence of the court.
Judgment given this day by
military tribunal of the Courts
of Justice Brussels against
Edith Cavell, directors
of the Berkendael Medical
Institute for treason
commit in time of war.
Sentence, death.
We carry it out at dawn.
Is there anything you wish?
I would like to see
an English chaplain.
[inaudible], Fraulein.
[speaking german]
I [inaudible].
Gentlemen, what can I do for you?
Will you inform,
Mr. Excellency,
if the sentence in the Cavell
affair has been promulgated?
Any information that
you are entitled to
will reach you at the
proper time, Mr. Gibson.
I... I understand that.
But would you tell me
if the court has passed
sentence on the prisoner.
The court has not yet
published its findings.
Then I presume no sentence
would be carried out
until it has been made public.
The sentence will be carried out
when the legal requirements
of the Imperial [inaudible]
has been fulfilled.
Good day, Mr. Gibson.
Good day, [inaudible].
[playing music]
[speaking german]
Firing squad, you'll meet
5 o'clock tomorrow morning.
- Kirk?
- Ya.
- [inaudible]
Rammler?
May I have leave
of parade, Sergeant?
I wish to report sick.
Yellow fever, Private Rammler?
I am... I am sick.
There's an ugly word for
this complaint of yours.
I don't mind fighting,
but this is murder.
You refuse to be ordered?
I do.
Private Rammler, you are
arrest for insubordination.
[speaking german]
[music playing]
Would you please be seated.
I have called Mr. Gibson.
This note has just
come for you, sir.
It's very urgent.
Oh, thanks.
Oh, Sister Watkins has just
called to see you, Mr. Gibson.
Better go and see her.
She may have news.
Mr. Gibson, Miss Cavell
has been sentenced to death.
What?
Yes, and it's tomorrow morning.
It can't be possible!
I assure you it is so.
We were told by the deputy
governor, Mr. Gibson.
Excuse me, sir.
Mr. Whitlock wishes to
see you immediately.
Wait here, I'll be right back.
[inaudible] we're being fooled.
Read that.
This confirms what
Sister Watkins told me.
I want to write a note.
They're going to kill her, sister.
I know it.
They can't.
They couldn't.
If only I weren't tied to this bed!
Couldn't have caught
it at a worse time, sir.
Get that to [inaudible].
See that he reads it himself.
Very well, sir.
If you will forgive
me, I'm a little dazed.
I'm distressed to meet you
under these circumstances.
If there is anything
I can do to help.
So much to do before
my work was finished.
[inaudible] Institute,
the [inaudible].
It is God's will.
God's will.
Sometimes so difficult
to comprehend.
That is what my mother
would say if she were here.
Will you see that a
message reaches her?
Tell her that I am
quite happy, that I have
no regret for what I have done.
Oh, Gibson.
[inaudible]
Your Excellency, I have the honor
to bring you a personal note.
[inaudible] from my minister.
I can do nothing in this matter.
But surely, your Excellency, you
don't wish me to
understand that you intend
the sentence to be carried out.
I have no say in the
matter, Mr. Gibson.
Decision rests with the military
government, [inaudible].
But your Excellency...
The military governor of Brussels
is the confirming authority,
and no one can interfere.
I know, but couldn't...
I doubt if the Kaiser
himself could do so.
You mean this woman is in
the grip of your war machine?
I mean nothing, Mr. Gibson.
When is the sentence
to be carried out?
I have not been informed.
Governor.
They've treated you considerately
whilst you've been here?
Oh yes, they've all been very kind.
But thank God for these few
quiet weeks before the end.
Life has always been hurried
and full of difficulties.
This time of rest has
been a great mercy.
[inaudible], Mr. Gibson's
here to see Excellence.
He's out.
His Excellence is out, Herr Gibson.
I wish to see him.
I'm afraid that's not possible.
But this is most urgent.
I have a message for him
from the American minister.
I'll see he gets it first
thing in the morning.
You know perfectly
well, Captain Heinrichs,
that would be too late.
As the Governor's had a
very trying day, Herr Gibson.
I dare not take the responsibility
of disturbing him.
Oh, don't worry about
the responsibility.
The American minister
would take that.
Unfortunately, Herr Gibson,
this is military headquarters,
not the American embassy.
I have my orders.
Why this is...
Mr. Gibson, at the opera.
Thank you.
[music playing]
Please, I'll tell him
at the end of this act.
But this is my [inaudible].
I must see him immediately.
This is the general's
own private box.
You cannot go in.
I wish to see General Von Ehrhardt.
He cannot be disturbed.
My name is Gibson.
I'm from the American Embassy.
Please tell him I'm here.
Mr. Gibson, [inaudible].
Most irregular I know.
But my minister will
take the responsibility.
What is your business?
General, there is a rumor or I
have been told that Miss Cavell
has been sentenced to death.
Yes, sir.
Moreover, the sentence is to
be carried out in the morning.
At dawn.
[gasp].
Well, don't you
realize what it means
if you execute this woman?
German will be banded
throughout the civilized world.
Don't you realize what a
terrible disservice you
are doing your own [inaudible]?
To fail in my duty would
be a far worse disservice.
The maintenance of
good order in Brussels
requires these penalties
be carried out.
The maintenance of
order could never
require the murder of a woman.
Your language is hardly
diplomatic, Mr. Gibson.
Moreover, it is most inexact.
One doesn't apply the term
murder to the execution
of those who have
been very convicted
on their own admissions
of capital offenses.
Tried before a secret tribunal.
Denied all communication
with her legal advisor.
Is that your [inaudible]...
I have no wish to discuss the
procedure of our German courts
[inaudible].
If that is all you have
to say, Mr. Gibson.
I have much to say.
A sense of horror so
strong, your Excellency
will make allowance.
This affair, it all seemed
so simple and logical to you.
[inaudible] and tragedy.
A crime against humanity.
You regard is a
crime against humanity
the punishment of people
for a military offenses
in time of war?
Yes, but your Excellency, a woman?
[inaudible] mixed up in
these affairs, Mr. Gibson.
Very well, then imprison her.
Put her out of the way
until the war's over.
No recommendation
to mercy was made.
The court has decided to
punish her with death.
Who knows thy cross before
my closing eyes shine
through the gloom and point
me to the skies, heaven
and morning grace, and
earth's [inaudible] shadows
flee in thy, in death
alone abide with me.
Amen.
[marching]
[speaking german].
EDITH CAVELL [VOICEOVER]: I
have no fear nor shrinking.
I have seen death so often.
It is no longer strange
or fearful to me.
[speaking german].
[music playing]
[singing]
Standing, as I do, before
God and eternity, I realize
that patriotism is not enough.
I must have no hatred or
bitterness towards anyone.
[music playing]