[MUSIC PLAYING]
What is it?
What's up?
I don't know.
Something woke me.
Something I heard.
Something.
What was it, you idiot?
It's downstairs.
Something downstairs.
Has there been a
raid here lately?
No.
[WATER TRICKLING]
It's the water from the tap.
You've got the jitters.
Mm, no wonder.
You're just a kid.
[GASPS]
What is it?
It's nothing.
We are just getting
in from the opera.
There.
Listen.
There's someone coming.
It's a three-story drop.
We've got to get
away across the roof.
You know the way?
Yes.
Down the hall, past the center.
Boo.
Raise your hand.
Over there.
Stand by the window.
All right.
You, there.
Come on.
You there?
Whom do you mean by, you there?
Oh, a gentleman.
His excellence, dieter.
General [INAUDIBLE].
Keep your hands up.
I mean you, you scum.
May I see your passport?
I have no passport.
We'll take care of you, my pet.
What have you got here, Kobel?
A couple of tough getaways.
Are the Vienna police
allowed to strike
a man when they make an arrest?
A lot more is
allowed than you think.
Get them dressed and put the
handcuffs on them, Kobel.
Yes, sir.
Kobel.
I'll keep your name in mind.
Next.
Personal record.
Name?
Ludwig Kern.
Date of birth?
November 30th,
1918 in Dresden.
A German?
No.
No nationality.
Deprived of citizenship.
At 19?
What crime did you commit?
None.
Go on.
Our whole family was
deprived of citizenship.
They told us to get out of
Germany or be locked up.
If we were going
to be locked up,
we wanted it to be somewhere
else, not in Germany.
Hmm.
I can understand that.
Where'd you go?
Czechoslovakia.
Oh, why didn't you stay there?
I was picked up one
day and asked to leave.
I had no passport.
I went into Hungary, but I
was told to leave there too.
How long have you
been in Austria?
Three months.
You're all alone here?
Yes.
How have you lived?
I had some money.
How much?
I've got 12 shillings now.
I suppose you've been
peddling without a permit, hmm?
All right, then, illegal
entrance into Austria.
Know the sentence?
14 days detention.
When you've served your
time, you'll be deported.
If you return, you'll
be liable to punishment.
Sign here in evidence
that you understand.
Yes, I understand that
you can have dinner, drink
a glass of wine, and
then go home to bed.
Home.
But the spark of life called
Ludwig Kern must sleep in prison
or stumble through the woods in
darkness longing for company,
but afraid of everybody.
Why?
Our blood has the
same temperature.
Our eyes are made alike.
Our nerves react alike.
And yet, we're separated.
It's like an abyss between us.
There's something called a
passport, a scrap of paper
with nothing on it, but a name
and a few meaningless dates.
To the right,
first and last name.
To which border do you
wish to be conducted when
you've served your sentence?
Czech border.
We'll see to it.
Take him away.
Next.
Kobel.
Personal record.
Name?
Steiner.
Josef Steiner.
Born August 31st,
1897 in Munich.
You're a political
fugitive from Germany.
Yes.
Escaped from concentration
Camp Dachau, May 11th, 1935.
Yes.
This gentleman here from
Munich wants to talk to you.
Are German secret agents
free to operate in Vienna?
Special orders.
I suppose you know I
may choose to be deported
over any border I like.
You can't send me
back to Germany.
Your rights will be respected.
Go in there.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Thank you very much.
Next.
Well, captain,
so we meet again.
I've been looking
forward to it,
but under different
circumstances.
Naturally.
You'd like to pay me
back some old scars.
I don't blame you.
But between ourselves,
may I congratulate you
upon your escape?
Was more daring than any of
your exploits at the front.
You get those machine guns and
through that high voltage wire,
I would have sworn it
couldn't be done Without help
from friends outside.
What do you want, Brenner?
Names of your friends.
I have none.
Captain, we
should like to know
the names of the other
members of group four.
And naturally, we are willing
to pay you for that information.
A passport.
And you may return to
Germany whenever you like.
[CHUCKLES]
Oh, I hope you don't
doubt our good faith.
Oh, no, no.
But in that case, you
can go wherever you please.
France or America
or anywhere else.
Don't be a fool, captain.
No one will ever know where
that information came from.
And after all, the
necessity of the state
is above the code
of the individual.
Not above mine.
Then I advise
you to change it.
Just compare our situations.
Yours is hopeless.
You're a man without a country
or a legal right to live.
A living ghost.
My situation, on the other hand,
is a secure and comfortable one.
And all that stands
between us is this.
There's a great deal more than
a passport between us, Brenner.
Shall we leave personal
feelings out of this?
You'd be insane to refuse
such an opportunity
to save yourself and--
No.
Then you won't
give us the names?
No.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Steiner, look.
Isn't there someone
in Germany whom
you would like to see again?
Someone that's dear to you.
Someone you love.
No.
Very well then.
Shall see.
For the moment, we can't
arrest you here in Austria.
but don't depend on that.
The situation here may change
now any day and when it does,
you'll be very glad to
give us that information
and on our terms,
my dear captain.
I'll take that chance.
Have it your own way.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Number five.
First time in a coupe, Kern?
You'll get used to it.
At least you have peace
while you're in here.
Man on the streets without a
passport is a corpse on parole.
All he's really expected
to do is commit suicide.
Is there anything
at all to eat here?
Just ring for the head waiter.
I had a roast
chicken in my trunk.
My first chicken in two years.
I saved up for it.
Was going to eat it today.
Don't cry about
it until tonight.
Then you can assume that
you've already eaten it.
That'll make it easier for you.
Yeah, yeah.
What?
That's nonsense.
Is that the same thing?
Is that the same thing at all?
I never eat chicken.
Yo, you haven't got a
roast chicken in your trunk?
Even if I had, wouldn't be.
Can't stand chickens.
Vomit up afterwards.
No, loss for me, the chicken.
Did anyone ever
hear such drivel?
Now why do I go round with you?
Even if chicken
here, wouldn't eat.
Wouldn't eat?
Good heavens.
How about eggs, pollock?
Chickens eggs?
Little eggs.
Yes.
Fond of little eggs.
Very fond of little eggs.
He's fond of little eggs.
Very, very fond
of little eggs.
Four, six, eight, 12 eggs.
Six boiled.
Other six fried.
With little potatoes.
With little fried
potatoes and bacon.
Shut your mouth!
No, no, no.
Wait, wait.
My good luck, I got through
with a bottle of brandy.
Oh.
Try it.
Go ahead.
Part of this?
Got to learn.
Nip is a nip to a man
without a country.
You better have some too.
No, thanks.
I don't belong in your crowd.
Pardon me?
You're not in jail for
your health, I trust.
I'm in jail because
of my profession.
I'm no fly by night
fugitive without papers.
I'm a substantial pickpocket
and professional gambler
with full rights of citizenship.
[LAUGHTER]
Would you condescend
to exercise your right
to gamble at our expense?
Have you any money?
I could manage a little.
Business is business.
It's pretty dark in
here for us amateurs.
What we'll do
about more light?
Candle.
Match.
Say, say, you couldn't get a
cigarette out of him, could you?
Cigarette.
Oh.
Aren't you going to play, too?
No, not now.
A little tired.
Card for you.
Diddly boom, boom.
King.
Oh, ace of hearts.
Ace of spades.
Know any more
tricks like that?
Not many.
Maybe I can teach you a few.
[WHISTLES]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[LAUGHS]
Why, she's laughing at it.
She's been laughing
at us all the time.
[LAUGHTER]
Homesick, baby?
Come on.
Where's your mom?
She's dead.
In exile?
Where's your father?
Prague, I think.
You got his address there?
Mm-hmm.
But I don't know if he--
As soon as we get out
of here, I'll put you
over the border of Prague, hmm?
Listen, in the
meantime, you better
begin to learn how to
look after yourself.
Get handy with guards
with your fists.
Get tough.
Come on.
Join the game.
Sorry.
[CHATTER]
Why don't they take us across?
Don't be impatient.
They have to show us
through the woods.
Don't forget, the Czechs
will be waiting over there
to send us back.
Here we go.
All right.
Come on.
When are you coming
back to Austria?
Never.
That means tonight.
Huh, you refugees.
It's not like handling
a first class criminal.
You're detracting from the
dignity of my profession.
There's Czechoslovakia.
Cross over at the
bottom of the hill here.
Better have a drink first.
Thanks.
Hurry until you get to
the bottom of the hill,
then you can take your time.
Yeah.
We're over.
Cigarette?
Thanks.
I'm going back in an hour.
Why are you on the road?
You're 100% Aryan.
And you?
50%.
I was wondering why you--
Oh, I'm simply an ex-soldier
who hates the gang that rules
Germany.
Naturally, they
don't like me either.
Why are you going
back to Vienna?
Because it's there my friends
might send me news of my wife.
Your wife?
She's still in Germany.
I don't know what's
happening to her.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH] That's the
way it looked tonight I escaped
from the concentration camp.
I hid for a week at
a friend's house.
I sat in a locked attic room.
I didn't dare light
a light or smoke.
I spent the whole day
writing my wife a letter.
At night, my friend brought
me a bottle of water and food.
He was going to try
to deliver the letter,
find out if it were possible
for me to see my wife
before I left Germany.
For four days, I
waited while my friend
tried to deliver the letter.
Finally, he told me he hadn't
dared to give it to her yet
as she was too closely watched.
I told him not to try anymore.
I was afraid something
might happen to her.
And I knew, too, that
my friend was in danger
as long as I stayed
in his house,
I decided to wait no longer.
My friend had bought
me money and clothes,
so I left the house the next
morning in a laborers jacket
carrying a box of tools.
I had intended to leave the city
immediately, but I couldn't.
I hadn't seen my
wife for two years.
I had to see her once more.
I walked to a marketplace
where my friend had told me
she bought her food.
Don't look around.
Go on walking.
Have they done anything to you?
Are you being watched?
Now?
I'm going to make my
way to the border.
I won't be able to write you.
You must divorce me.
You must go tomorrow.
Say you want to divorce me
because of my political views.
Say you hadn't realized
before what they were.
It's only to make you safe.
It would drive me crazy if
they did anything to you.
You must divorce me, then
they will leave you alone.
I love you, Marie.
I love you more than
anything in the world.
I won't leave
unless you promise.
I'll give myself up
if you don't promise.
Do you promise?
Right.
I'm going to turn back now.
Between butcher booth.
You go right.
Come around to meet me.
I just want to see you
once, then I'll go.
If you hear nothing, it will
mean I got safely across.
Then I saw her face.
Three days later, I
crossed the border.
I wish there was
something that I could--
How old are you?
19.
I'll soon be 20.
Well, well, well.
Almost 20, hey?
This is no joke,
is it, baby, huh?
Try to make the best of it
but don't look for favors.
Individuals or nations,
it's all the same.
As long as they're
safe and comfortable,
they don't give a hoot
what happens to others.
It is the misery of the world.
That's why progress is so slow
and things slip back so fast.
You believe it?
No.
[LAUGHS] All right.
All right.
Maybe it might be worse, huh?
I got a wife, and
you got a father.
They still care
what happens to us.
As long as we got one person
who does care, just one,
I guess it's all right.
But remember what I told you
about getting tough, huh?
And don't look for favors.
How much money have you?
12 shillings.
That will get you to Prague.
No--
Go ahead, take it.
I still have enough for myself.
Thanks.
What are you going to do
about the Vienna police?
Oh, I'm not worried.
That gambler taught me a
few new tricks in jail.
I'm going to try to pick
up enough money at cards
to buy myself some kind
of forged passport.
And there's one policeman
I'm going to look up.
Kobel is the name.
Good luck.
Oh, by the way,
what's your name?
Kern.
Ludwig Kern.
I'll write it down for you.
Oh, I'll remember.
My name is Steiner.
Yes, I know.
I'll drop you a line.
General delivery
to Prague, yeah?
Take care of yourself.
Sure.
Oh, and Thanks for--
So long, Kern.
So long, Steiner.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
How many?
Two.
Three.
One.
50.
Double.
Can I take a peek?
No.
Double 100.
I'll call you.
Four kings.
Four aces.
[WHISTLING]
We'll play another round.
Sorry.
Next time.
Thank you, sir.
The boy slipped up that time.
No rough stuff, gentlemen.
It's the last thing I want.
I'm trying to get out.
We'll go with you.
Stop him!
How are you?
Good evening.
You're a German, aren't you?
I was.
In that case, naturally,
we recommend a dead German.
No, sir.
I want to work here in Vienna.
I couldn't with a
German passport.
In that case, there
is only the Austrian.
With that, you can work.
Suppose someone
makes inquiries.
The office word was issued.
Who's going to unless
you get into trouble?
300 shillings.
We have a fixed price, 500.
If it had been the
German passport,
we might have made a deal.
But Austrian passports
are hard to get.
It's a gift at 500.
350 is my last word.
That's what I pay to
the bereaved family.
This sort of thing
comes high, my friend.
Just not something like this.
Fresh from the grave,
you have to lay down
cold cash and lots of it.
You can have it for 450.
We're losing money,
but we like you.
Oh, I like you, too.
400.
Have you got a photograph?
It's a deal.
It's good for a year.
John Huber.
Workman.
Fair exchange, John Huber.
The living won't help
us, it's up to the dead.
Good night.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
This can't go on forever.
Let me forget her, God.
I try and try and all the time.
I know she's alive.
Marie.
I've got to I forget you.
Tear you out of my mind
and eyes and blood.
Forget.
Sit down.
Warm, isn't it?
Yeah.
Summer, you know?
Yes.
Summer.
Help me.
Marie.
Just see how drunk
you are, my pet.
My name is Elvira.
Kobel.
Hello.
Is that you, Kobel?
This is the station house.
There's somebody making
trouble on Elizabeth Avenue
near Anna Street.
You better get down
here right away.
[WHISTLES]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[DOORBELL RINGING]
What do you want?
I want to speak to
someone who lives here.
Who is it?
Well, I'd rather not shout
it through the whole house.
I'd like to
speak to Herr Kern.
Kern?
Yes.
Herr Sigmund Kern.
I'm Ludwig Kern.
Relative?
Oh, yes.
I--
He doesn't live here.
Look, I don't blame
you for being suspicious,
but when you see him,
will you tell him
that I'll wait at
the Hotel Bristol
just as long as I can manage it?
That may not be for long.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
No.
[PANTING] [SCREAMS]
What is it?
Well.
Excuse me.
I must have gotten
the wrong room.
Ah-huh.
I thought the
police were raiding.
I got in the wrong room.
[VIOLIN PLAYING]
Oh, I beg your pardon, but
would it disturb you if I smoke?
Not at all.
I smoke myself.
Oh, please.
They're the same sort I smoke.
Well, that's the
cheapest kind you can get.
It's almost as if we told
each other our life histories.
I think this place
tells most of it anyway.
Have you been abroad long?
Over two months.
That's not long.
Is to me.
Hmm.
Learning to forget,
that's hardest.
Forget what?
Past.
Everything.
You think one must?
Yes.
Think one can like that?
Thank you for the cigarette.
LUDWIG KERN: Learning to
forget, that's hardest.
RUTH HOLLAND: Forget what?
LUDWIG KERN: The past.
Herbert.
This is the end of it for us.
This end for good and
all, you understand?
I've been waiting to tell
you this for a long time.
But the fool that I
was, I didn't do it
because I wanted to spare you.
Oh, Herbert.
I'm so sorry if you've gotten
difficulties through knowing me.
Here in the newspapers,
"Herbert Bending
labeled as a
profaner of his race.
Engaged to marry a Jewess."
I'm in the newspaper,
too, Herbert.
Well, what of it?
What does that matter?
What difference
does it make to you?
Well, it makes
all the difference.
It means I have to leave school.
Three years of hard
work gone for nothing.
I had special
honors in chemistry.
I'd been promised a scholarship.
Scholarship?
You compare that
to my whole career?
It's wrong, I tell you.
RUTH HOLLAND (VOICEOVER):
Is this the boy
I grew up with, played and
danced with, read poetry
and sang with in the
long summer evenings?
Is this the man I sat with here
in the moonlight who told me
he loved me more than life?
No, it isn't a man at all.
It's just something
strange and frightened.
All right.
Goodbye, Herbert.
Now I understand.
You don't
understand everything.
You said you were
willing to wait for me.
You needn't.
I don't want to have
anything more to do with you.
It's a pity that you're not dead
like your father and mother.
I've written this paper
what I think about.
Now you know.
Yes, now I know.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
I'm afraid something
I said upset you.
Wasn't your fault.
I'm very sorry.
Please.
Oh, look.
I really wanted to know if
you'd like to go to the movies
with me tonight.
Movies?
Mm-hmm.
I had luck today.
Made almost 10 crowns.
No, really, I don't--
Well, you can't sit
in there all evening.
That's the way I spend
most of my evenings.
Oh, but you can't.
Well, you'll get more morbid
with those old harpies.
Show begins in 10 minutes.
Oh, come on.
It's no fun at the movies alone.
Get your coat.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[LAUGHTER]
Feel better?
We'll continue the treatment.
It's been a lovely
week, but I can't stay.
I've got to go on to Vienna.
Can't you put it off
until your permit expires?
You see, I've been offered a
place in a chemistry laboratory
with an old professor
of mine needs
a chance to go on studying.
I see.
I can't risk losing it.
No, I suppose not.
Oh, I've got a friend in Vienna.
I just had this through
general delivery.
Read it.
Do.
So, a mind reader.
Maybe after I
find my father, I'll
be able to go back to Vienna.
We might be able to
see each other there.
When do you have to go?
Day after tomorrow.
Then we'll have dinner
together tomorrow evening, hmm?
I think we've got enough.
Ha, ha.
Oh, yes.
For tonight too.
Oh, I wanted this
to be a gay evening,
and that fellow's spoiling it.
Why does he keep
looking over here?
I think he's a Gestapo agent.
Well, I don't care what he is.
You're going to have dessert.
What would you like, hmm?
Apple strudel.
Right.
If you can afford it.
Ah!
Could I have two pieces
of apple strudel for this?
Apple strudel?
Mm-hmm.
And two demitasse.
Are you a guest
here or a peddler?
Do you think you can eat
here without paying for it?
Do you?
I can pay for it.
Well, my friend, there's
only one prescription
for you, the police.
One moment.
May I ask you a question?
You're German
exiles, aren't you?
What's that to you?
Will you sell me the perfume?
No.
Why not?
I have nothing to sell.
Then let's make a barter deal.
I take the perfume and give
you the cake and coffee.
I don't understand
what you want.
I know you are suspicious.
Let me explain.
I live in Berlin, and I
have got to go back there.
But I hate what's going
on in Germany today.
And I am ashamed of what they
are doing to helpless people.
I'd like to help
you if you'd let me.
I'm sorry.
I thought something
quite different of you.
I can imagine that.
Now, go back to the young lady.
I frightened her long enough.
I wish the best of
luck to you both.
Thanks.
Thanks a lot.
What happened?
Wow!
That--
What is this?
Oh, apple strudel.
Oh, say, I wonder, could I
have this chocolate eclair
instead of the apple strudel?
Certainly.
All this has been
ordered for you.
Oh!
Everything is paid for.
Everything?
But--
Champagne with ice, sir
from the restaurant next door.
Champagne?
Ooh, champagne!
Oh!
[NON-ENGLISH SINGING]
[LAUGHTER]
The lilacs are out.
Don't be sad.
I
Know, Sometimes I
don't make sense.
Let's pretend it
was the champagne.
A while ago, you were so gay.
I'd like to be gay.
I would, really.
Or don't.
Oh, I wish you weren't going.
I wish I weren't too.
Well, anyway, we still have
tomorrow evening together.
Yes, we have tomorrow.
Kern, know where
to find a doctor?
No.
You wouldn't.
What's the matter?
Go up to room 18, and
stay with that woman
till I get a doctor.
[BABY CRYING]
There.
They've done the trick.
One more Czech in the world.
We must have a drink to that.
To the greatest
mystery in the world,
birth do you know
why it's a mystery?
Because afterwards, one dies.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Be quiet down there.
Who do you think can sleep?
Stay awake, grandmother.
I am no grandmother.
So much the better
for your grandchildren.
Here.
Do you good.
You were splendid.
How are things going, doctor?
The baby will be all right.
We'll have it looked after.
I was able to tell her that.
Isn't she going to get well?
MAN: Doctor.
Coming.
[SOMBER MUSIC]
Let's drink to the
beauty of the world that
is indestructible.
No right to it,
though, have we?
We have no right to
anything, we refugees.
No business falling in love,
getting married, having
children, anything, have we?
What do you think?
Ruth.
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
Come in.
Miss Holland.
She's gone.
Gone?
Mm-hmm.
Vienna.
Vienna?
But she wasn't
going till tomorrow.
She went today, though.
An hour ago.
Well, didn't she leave any
message, a note or anything?
Not a word.
Thanks.
[LAUGHTER]
Ruth.
Oh, Ruth.
I was afraid I'd miss you.
Is anything wrong?
You told me you
were going tomorrow.
I got word to come at once.
Oh, I see.
From Professor Meyer.
Oh, these are for you.
And I'll write you.
May I?
Where shall I address you?
I'm not sure.
General delivery?
CONDUCTOR: All aboard!
Goodbye.
I've been told
that you might be
able to give me some
information here in regards
to the whereabouts of my father.
Name, please.
Kern.
Sigmund Kern.
[TENSE MUSIC]
And now, ladies
and gentlemen, I
invite you to pass
within these doors
and to share with us the
secrets of the human mind.
The greatest feat of
clairvoyance known to man.
It's stupendous.
It's colossal.
We will read your inmost
thoughts like an open book.
Do not deprive yourself
of this opportunity
to see for yourself a
miracle, a mystery that
defies the laws of nature.
A power that denies the senses.
A force that unites the
atom to the farthest star.
Young man, you do
not believe me?
You are skeptical.
You scoff.
Step up here.
Step up.
Your mind is no mystery
to me, I assure you.
Ah, yes.
Sensitive, retiring,
very uncommunicative.
But I detect a
growing assertiveness.
The beginning of self-reliance.
An uncanny judgment in
choosing friends and a light
headedness that can only
be cured by good food.
Go in, my friends.
Go in.
Buy your ticket as you
enter at a price so low,
I blush to mention.
[LAUGHTER]
How are you, baby?
Steiner.
Huber's the name.
What--
Not a word.
No questions.
No answers until you fill
that void under your belt.
Right over there.
I'll join you as soon
as I finish this show.
I wrote her care
of general delivery
and asked her to
leave word where
I could get in touch with her.
She hasn't bought any
letter here for me, has she?
No, but don't worry.
You'll find her, all right?
Pots luck.
What?
What's up?
We need another assistant.
Oh, one of your
friends, I suppose, yeah?
Hey.
How much does he want?
30 shillings and keep.
30 shill-- say, what
does he think he is?
A moving picture star?
You want to ruin me, Huber?
Must he be paid for living
here and no questions asked.
Well, I'll take
a job without pay.
Ah.
Well, now, that's different.
Now, that's the way to
become a millionaire.
None but the modest
get ahead in life.
But you don't know
Leopold Fessler.
The last surviving
philanthropist.
You will receive 15
shillings cash a month.
I'm satisfied.
All right, then.
All right.
I'll show you your duty.
Here is our carousel.
Your job is to sweep it out.
But most of your work will
be in the shooting gallery.
You'll have to help
Lilo load the rifles.
Lilo, this is Ludwig Kern.
Fraulein.
Remember, people
like to win something.
Our motto is give and take.
But never give as
much as you take.
[LAUGHS] You got
the right idea.
You see that prize?
That's a showpiece.
That's a private possession
right out of my own house.
When the score of 60
wins, it's an heirloom.
Think of it.
An heirloom in this
traditionalist age.
Do you know what an--
nah, of course, you wouldn't.
But remember this.
You must die before you let
anyone get a score of 60.
When I think, I get
gooseflesh all over me.
My wife would murder
me if I lose this.
Yes, I know.
But how can I prevent it
if a man's a crack shot?
Oh, Lilo will assure you.
If anyone looks
too good, you slip
one of Director Potzlochs
Magic Cartridges in his gun.
Tip of the bullet is offline.
See?
I see.
But don't let him see.
Lilo will help you
if things get ticklish.
Come on.
I'll show you where we sleep.
Oh, say, would you
mind, I'd like to run down
to the post-office for this.
Sure.
If I were you, I
wouldn't lose a minute.
Love.
Anything from
Miss Ruth Holland?
Well, you see, I
wrote her, and I'd
like to know if she
received my letters.
She must have received them.
They've been called for.
Thanks.
Miss Holland.
Oh, Professor Meyer.
Have you any friends
outside of Austria
to whom you could go
in case of necessity?
I have a school
friend in Zurich.
I could always go to her.
I'm sorry, my child.
Very sorry, indeed.
But there's no help
for it, I'm afraid.
You mean I have to go
because I have no passport?
It's a shame.
You're doing excellent work.
I've been very pleased.
Must I go at once?
Today?
Tomorrow?
No, but perhaps in a few days.
A week.
Otherwise it may not be
safe for either of us.
Ladies and gentlemen.
Come and look at the finest
collection of trained animals
known to man.
See Alexander, the scarlet
flea in his first--
Could you tell me where
I can find Ludwig Kern?
Do you know where I
could find Ludwig Kern?
His smile is temperamental,
and he swings on a trapeze?
Never heard of him.
Mr. Bartok.
He fires a cannon and never--
Oh, where will I find him?
I just saw him a minute ago.
Try over there by the carousel.
Alexander!
He was here a minute ago.
Try the shooting gallery.
Thank you.
Ruth.
Oh, am I glad to see you.
Look, I've written
and written you.
Yes, I wrote to you too.
Yeah, but I never got it.
No, I know because
you see, I didn't--
Heh, heh.
What's going on?
Why aren't you
attending to business?
Mr. Potzloch, I want you
to meet a very good friend
of mine, Fraulein Holland.
Hello.
No, no, it's no use.
We don't need any
more assistance.
Oh, no, it isn't that.
We just haven't seen each
other for such a long time.
Oh.
Oh, is that all?
No, I think I see.
Well, take the
evening off, then.
Look, show her around.
Show her everything, all
the different amusings.
You know, with that uniform on,
they let you in for nothing.
Go ahead.
Go on.
Have a good time.
Get out.
Whoa.
Good one.
Four more shots.
I'll get a 60 and
win that grand prize.
24.
Two in a row.
48.
Well, he can kiss
that prize goodbye.
Only one left.
Travel.
56.
Oh.
His hand must have trembled.
Try it again.
Give him a chance.
Wins the picnic basket.
Hold on, there.
Something wrong here.
I made a perfect shot that time.
Well, maybe you
trembled a little.
It's the same gun.
A police sergeant
doesn't tremble.
I know the way I shoot.
There's something fishy here.
You did something
to that cartridge.
Give him another shot.
Suppose we make a compromise.
Huh?
Yes.
Suppose you start over again
and take five more shots.
Why should I?
No, don't do it.
--fine fellow like you can
shoot just as well a second
time.
You're the best shot
we've had here in years.
Your wife need never be afraid.
I have no wife.
Oh, that's only because
you don't want one.
I've seen you somewhere before.
How long you been here?
That's none of your business.
You carry papers?
Certainly.
Let's see them.
Well, they're in
the wagon mind you.
All right.
Let's have a look in the wagon.
Say, what right have
you got to question me?
You're--
Ludwig, he's right.
If he's a policeman, he has a
right to look at your papers.
Let me get your passport.
If you would you follow me, sir.
Oh, I see.
You think you're pretty
smart, don't you?
Well, mind your own business,
you filthy little gypsy.
[OVERLAPPING CHATTER]
Outrageous!
I appeal to you.
Is it justice, two
weeks in jail when I
got roast chicken in my trunk?
It will get spoiled by the
time I get out of here.
I never eat
chicken, but I like--
Little Egg.
As I live and breathe,
it's Little Eggs.
And The Chicken.
Remember me?
Remember you?
Why, it's the baby.
Hello, baby, baby.
Say, say, where's
the crazy Steiner?
Oh, he's fine.
You are not so good, I see.
Who beat you up, huh?
Oh, the police.
Oh, baby, baby,
it's time you learned
to take care of yourself.
I wish I could.
Look.
Boom chin, boom chin, boom--
You're a fighter?
Sometimes not so bad.
Well, will you teach me?
We'll try later when
you feel better, huh?
No, right now.
Ambitious, huh?
[LAUGHTER]
No, no, no.
Never mind the hands.
Begin with the feet.
Get light on the feet like--
see?
Not, not, not bad.
Look, you can hit from the body.
Try swing and see how
badly you miss one.
[SCREAMS]
[LAUGHTER]
I was the lucky one, huh?
Hey, quiet in here.
This is no nightclub.
Which one of you is Kern?
Lady to see you.
You thought it was Ruth?
Yes.
Ruth's being deported.
Deported?
Do you know where?
She left this for you.
Oh, thanks.
It's Switzerland.
Zurich.
What's the matter?
It's the way she writes.
Like a stranger.
Like saying, if you must
know, here's my address.
Isn't that enough?
No.
It sounds as though she
doesn't mean to see me again.
Maybe she thought
he'd be better off
looking after yourself.
Women are like that, you know.
I think when I get out of
here, I'd better go to Zurich.
I think so, too.
So does Steiner and Mr.
Potzloch And Steiner
wants you to write to him.
Say goodbye to him for me.
Tell him I'm getting tough.
I'll tell him.
Goodbye, Lilo.
Goodbye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[BUZZER RINGING]
Ludwig.
Well, come in.
Ludwig, come in.
You look half dead.
No, there's no one here.
The family's gone
for the weekend.
Family?
Sylvia and her parents.
Sylvia was my school friend.
Oh.
Oh, I see.
Let me look at you.
Oh, I'm all right.
It's you I'm worried about.
Me?
Why?
Why didn't you write me?
I was afraid.
Why should you
be afraid of me?
How can I tell you?
It's just that people
like us, exiles--
Oh.
Oh, I know it sounds foolish.
But every time I make up
my mind that it is foolish,
something happens.
Yes, it does, Ludwig.
So I thought I ought
to get along by myself,
alone with books and studying,
just as though I were
in a laboratory as
remote, and impersonal
as science is, not caring
for any other human being.
That's what I thought, Ludwig.
I can understand your
wanting to do that.
But you can't, you know.
You know, I think the worse
off we are, the less we have,
then the more important it
is to find companionship.
If there's someone you
care for, just one,
and who cares for you
too, then it isn't so bad.
Oh, Ruth.
Ruth, you shouldn't
keep on fighting
so hard against being happy.
Don't look at me.
Please don't, you know.
All right, darling.
Wow.
That can't be me.
Why, I look I'm a
tramp, a scarecrow.
I'll run a bath for you.
Hmm?
A bath?
You mean with soap and
shower and everything?
Ah-huh.
And then I'll get you some
supper and some coffee
and some brandy.
Oh, that's wonderful.
All we need is
evening clothes, hey.
You could have Mr.
Neumann's dinner jacket,
only it would fit
you like an overcoat.
But I could wear one of
Sylivie's evening dresses.
Shall I?
Yes, do.
Oh, you know, I haven't seen
anything like this in years.
(SINGING) The worms crawl out
The worms crawl in
The worms crawl over
your nose and chin
Oh, ooh, tu
(SPEAKING) Oh, you're beautiful.
Oh, I'm not beautiful.
Sylivia's dress is.
No, you're beautiful, too.
You're like-- you're
like a hazelnut.
What?
I'm not sure myself.
Has something to do with
the hazelnut, though.
Something to do with you, Ruth.
How beautifully that dress goes
with your eyes and your hair.
Everything about you shines.
One lump or two?
One, please.
You know, for someone
else, this might
be just an ordinary,
everyday occurrence,
but for me, it's like--
oh, Ruth, do you really
think that we'll ever
have anything like this?
I mean, a home with two or
three rooms and the right
to work and stay
in the same place.
I don't know.
I can't imagine it.
Well, you wait.
In five or 10 years, you'll
be wearing dresses like that
every evening.
Yes, and I'll be
a famous surgeon
in a frock coat
with certificates
of honorary citizenship
in every pocket.
Your good health, Ruth.
Your good health.
Ludwig.
[YAWNS]
Well, here.
Can we have some music?
Yes, of course.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Where's it coming from?
Paris.
I'm going to try
to get to Paris.
Why?
Well, I can't stay here.
I've got to keep moving.
You remember Leo
Merrill in Prague?
Yes.
Well, he has a pass.
He says it's easy in
France to get a permit
to find work and stay.
Ludwig.
Yes?
I want to go with you.
No.
We can start tomorrow.
Ruth, you don't know
what it's like on the road.
I don't care.
Anyway, my being
here is beginning
to embarrass the Neumanns.
The doorman downstairs
has threatened
to tell the police about me.
Why?
Well, they have no idea
how some men behave when they
think a woman is defenseless.
And did the doorman--
Oh, silly.
Well, that's horrible.
No, it's just
tiresome, that's all.
All right, then.
We'll go together.
From now on, I'll
look after you.
Yes.
[UPBEAT MUSIC]
And you're going to
take your things along?
No.
It will attract attention.
The best way is
to leave casually.
Not too fast, but
just fast enough.
Well, that's-- well, here.
I'll tell you what I'll do.
I'll buy your stuff.
Thank you.
Don't thank me.
I'll make a profit on this.
You know, I kind of
hate these goodbyes.
So do I.
It's simply a matter of
routine but between you
and me, that's the most
terrible thing in the world.
Everything gets to be
a matter of routine.
You know.
I know a man.
He's had four wives die
in the last 10 years.
Now he's got a fifth,
and she's getting sick.
I don't-- I don't have
to tell you these.
I'm looking around
now for number six.
Yes, it's all a
matter of routine.
What will happen
if they catch you?
I'd be better off dead.
Goodbye, Lilo.
You will stay where you are.
This won't settle
you, you know?
[DOGS BARKING]
Good morning.
Huh.
We'd be very
grateful if you'd let
us rest in there for the day.
Where are you going?
We're trying to reach
the French border.
We--
[COUGHS]
She's got a cold.
She got chilled in
the rain last night.
You can stay if you want to.
Thanks.
Thanks very much.
But don't light a fire.
We won't.
You better get out
of those wet clothes.
Get into whatever dry things you
have and get a good, warm sleep.
Come on.
Then I'm going into the town
to try to sell something.
Ludwig, be careful.
Just enough to
buy a little food.
Now, don't worry.
You can keep warm and rest.
Ludwig.
Herr Amos.
But the maid tells me
you are a German exile.
Yes, sir.
No passport?
No, sir.
Well, my wife can have
a look at your things.
Yes, sir.
Oh, I beg your pardon.
What have you to sell?
How much?
30 centimes, Frau Amos.
60 centimes.
How much?
One Franc 80.
Well, I've already given
you the price on that,
Frau Amos, 30 centimes.
I'll see what
my sister thinks.
How much?
I've given Frau
Amos the prices.
I-- perhaps you'd rather
think it over until morning.
Would you like
a cup of coffee?
Well, yes.
Yes, I would if
you have some made.
Yes, yes, indeed.
Just one minute.
Cup of coffee will taste fine.
I haven't had any
coffee in a long time.
Ah!
The coffee's very hot.
There's no hurry.
Take your time drinking it.
[SHRILL LAUGHTER]
There he is, officer.
The man without a passport
banished from the German Reich.
Arrest him.
Come with me.
I'd like to meet you again for
just 10 minutes, five minutes,
one minute.
Did you hear that?
He hasn't injured you yet.
He's only expressed a
wish to meet you again.
Follow me.
Don't you know
who he is, my boy?
He's a local spy
of the Nazi party.
What an idiot I am.
You are with bells on.
Look, officer, there's
someone waiting for me.
I can't be
bothered about that.
And let me tell you,
if you try to escape,
I will have to draw my revolver.
Naturally, that will take time.
So perhaps I better put
the handcuffs on you.
Now, where did I put the thing?
Thanks.
[LAUGHS]
Congestion of the right lung.
She must go to the hospital.
No, I can't go
to the hospital.
We can't pay for the hospital.
Never mind the money.
You are seriously ill.
It's the best thing.
Get dressed, and I
have blankets in my car.
There's no other way, darling.
Ludwig, where will
you stay while I'm gone?
I'll stay here.
How will we see each other?
You can't come to the hospital.
They'll arrest you.
Every night, I'll stand
out in front of the hospital
and look up at your window.
That'll be just like it is.
When?
9:00.
How will you
know which window?
Doctor will tell me.
It'll be dark at 9:00.
I won't be able to see you.
Well, I can only
come after dark.
No, no, you
mustn't come at all.
I'll come.
Now you get dressed.
Don't be worried.
Now, look, you've
got to be brave.
I'm afraid.
I don't want to leave you.
I'm afraid something
will happen to you.
I'll be all right.
Are you ready?
Goodbye.
Smile at me.
Quick.
Don't forget me.
Love me.
All right, but now let's go.
She can't see me.
What's this you're up to?
Oh, it's nothing.
It's just a fool
trick, that's all.
Just a minute.
You know Ammers?
Oh, no.
Perhaps he knows you.
There's a complaint at the
station that fits you exactly.
Come on, put them up, Ammers.
Come on, put them up.
You can't lick me.
Not me.
All goes to make me tough.
Like that.
And that.
Get up.
Come on, get up, Ammers.
Settle your hash.
I'll teach you to
prey on poor refugees.
How's that old, Steinar, huh?
[CLAPPING] Good work.
Doctor.
I didn't hear you.
You were doing fine.
Oh, how is she?
All right.
Everything normal.
I brought you something.
Go ahead and read it.
No, I'll read it later.
You don't want to
read it before I go?
No, not now.
Not so quickly.
I haven't anything
else to do all day.
I see.
Well, I'm going
to the hospital now.
Have you anything
for me to take along?
I can't write here.
But would you give
her a message for me.
Tell her I'll wait
for her every day
at noon at the post
office in Geneva
at the general delivery window.
Is that clear?
Sure.
Oh, and tell her
for me that I--
that I--
She knows that,
but I tell her.
Thanks.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
You hurry up and
get well, darling,
because I'll be there
waiting for you.
Karen.
Kelton.
Nothing for Kern.
Ruth, it's you.
It's you.
How long have you been here?
Since this morning.
Oh, I've been waiting
and waiting back and forth,
back and forth from France.
Now we can both try to
get into France tonight.
The two rooms cost
20 francs with meals.
And we'll be able to live
that way about 10 days.
But I'll have some sort
of job before then.
Hmm.
Paris city of glamour.
You can see the Eiffel Tower--
Mm-hmm.
--if you get into
the right position.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
Professor Meyer.
Looking at the Eiffel Tower.
Well.
Matl told me you'd arrived.
We're all on the run, eh?
They chased me out of
Germany, then out of Austria.
But they'll never catch
up with me in Paris.
Matl?
Professor Meyer,
this is Herr Kern.
What are you doing, professor?
Correcting papers
on the sly, of course,
for a friend of mine who teaches
chemistry at the university.
How would you like to
attend his lectures?
Oh, I'd love to if I
can't get any work to do.
You won't get any work.
That's certain.
Not now.
What does he mean?
You can't get work
without a permit.
But you told me it was
easy to get one in Paris.
That was before the
Austrian Anschluss.
Since that happened, France
is overrun with exiles.
Things are more difficult now.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
There's really nothing
here worth selling.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
Get your things on.
We've got them on already.
Baby.
Get your friends.
We're celebrating.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Ah, chicken.
ALL: Ah!
Chicken.
Yeah.
Come on.
Excuse me.
[LAUGHTER]
[SIGHS]
Here, here, you're stopping
after your fourth chicken.
What's happened
to your appetite?
I can't.
[LAUGHTER]
Clear it away for dessert.
She's very pretty, isn't she?
Yes.
Fine student, too.
But she ought to be
registered at the university.
For the time being,
it's all right, isn't it?
But how long will she be able
to keep it up without papers?
Some fine day, you're both
going to get caught and then--
What's one to do?
Marry.
But we have no papers.
I don't mean that.
Marry a Frenchman.
Well, that would be ideal, of
course, but it isn't possible.
You're wrong.
It is possible.
Durant would marry her.
Told me so himself.
Who?
Durant.
That's right.
You don't know him.
Professor at the university.
Fine fella.
Excellent family, too.
I understand his
uncle's a senator.
He's head over heels
in love with Ruth.
Maybe I shouldn't
have told you that.
Oh, yes, yes.
We're sensible people.
It's-- what's his full name?
Francois Durant.
I see, you're not--
No, no, no.
That's-- I mean, after all,
if that's the way things are,
it's fine.
It's fine.
And everything
would be all right.
Really?
I should have thought that--
but if you do feel that way,
it'll be marvelous for her.
Really marvelous.
You know Francois Durant?
Yes.
Why?
Do you like him?
What do you mean by that?
Just what I say.
Do you like him?
Meyer.
Drunk for the first
time in his life
and what a moment to choose.
He wasn't as
drunk as all that.
Come here at once.
Is no joke.
This is serious.
All right.
Then I'll come to you.
Now then, what's wrong?
You must marry him.
What?
What's that you said?
You must marry him.
My poor darling.
What crazy things
go on in your head?
Well, you must.
Marriage is no longer a
matter of life and death.
But to have a passport or
not to have a passport, that
is a matter of life and death.
Ruth, you mustn't
throw away this chance.
I suppose I'll
never get another one.
Oh, you're not
taking me seriously.
I should think not
when you go on like this.
I go on?
Yes, you listen to an
old fogey in his cups
and you decide you'll be
a hero and get rid of me
without stopping to think
how I might feel about it.
I won't even
discuss it with you.
Why?
Because I love you, you idiot.
I love only you.
Now do you believe me?
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
Pardon me.
I know where we can
get work tomorrow.
Work?
Construction job and
no questions asked.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
Just feel that, Steiner.
Not bad at all.
Isn't it a beauty?
I got it in the halls.
Best in Paris.
[WORDLESS SINGING]
[LAUGHTER]
Say, do you fellas know
anybody around named Steiner?
Huh?
Do you know Steiner?
What's that to you?
There isn't anyone
who has any business
to be looking for Steiner.
Are you Steiner?
No.
Why?
I have a letter for you.
It's from Germany.
Thank you.
It's nothing.
Glad I found you.
I have other letters that have
been undelivered for a year.
It's about my wife.
Read it.
No, stay here with me.
She's in the hospital.
10 days ago, she
was still alive.
What hospital?
Did he tell you that?
Yes.
All right, then, come on.
We'll telephone the hospital.
Well, under some name or other.
And this.
There's been an operation.
There's no hope for her now.
Three or four days at the
most, the doctor says.
I'll leave today.
It's too dangerous.
I have my Austrian passport.
Steiner, you'll be done
for if you cross that border.
When she dies,
I'm done for anyway.
Oh, that's not true.
I know this may sound
heartless, but I
think you should write
a telegraph or anything,
but stay here.
Well, you can't help her
even if you do go there.
I can see her.
She'll be horrified if you go.
Why, if you would
ask her now, she'd
make every effort
to keep you from it.
I have to see her.
Marie my wife.
She's alive.
Her eyes are still
there and her thoughts.
And I'm still there
behind those eyes.
In a few days, she'll be dead.
Be nothing left over.
She'll lie there.
There'd be nothing.
No.
No, she's still alive
for a few days longer.
The last days.
And I'm not to be with her.
No, there's no other way.
The world is ending.
If I don't see her,
I'll simply break.
I'll die with her.
Is there nothing
I can say, nothing
I can do to make you see?
I know what the
stakes are but if there
were a thousand times higher,
I'd still take that train.
Nothing could stop me.
Can you understand that?
Yes.
If don't you get back in 10
days, give this to the kid.
Hmm?
I'll leave your
seats together.
Good luck.
Thanks.
Well, children, I
always knew somehow
that this is how it would be.
Goodbye, Ruth.
So long, Kern.
Sometimes things go
slow, don't they?
Sometimes darn fast.
Come back to us.
We can't do very much for you,
but everything we are is yours.
Always.
CONDUCTOR: All aboard!
Take care of yourselves.
[KNOCK ON DOOR]
Oh, Marril.
Have you seen Ludwig?
He's always been here by 6:00.
I can't imagine what's
happened to him.
I've just come to tell you.
They picked him up as he
was knocking off work.
They sent him to a
prison in Maubeuge
on the border where
they deport aliens.
What else could you expect?
They found him working and
there aren't enough jobs
for their own people.
Here.
He's written you a letter.
He says that not to count on
his ever coming back to France.
And he wants me to--
Marry Durant.
Yes, he told me.
It would mean everything
to him to know
that you're safe and cared for.
Cared for?
Yes, cared for.
That's something nowadays
for people like us.
You might be unhappy for
a while, but that's all.
I won't give him up.
That's not an answer.
That's a resolve.
You'll find out
when it's too late
and resolves are matters at
the head, not at the heart.
Oh, head and heart.
Let me tell you something.
Before I knew him, I felt
old and full of suspicion.
And he's made me young.
He's made me laugh again.
I was hopeless and without
faith and kindness in humanity.
And he's made me cheerful
and full of life.
Yes, and he's done it with
his simple, straightforward
instincts, with his
love, if you must know.
Doesn't he penetrate
even your cynicism, Leo,
to read that letter in
which you renounces me?
Doesn't it mean a thousand
times more than all
the while to do about fine
feelings and ecstasy and all
that rubbish.
I know you mean well, Leo.
I know he told you to
say these things to me,
and I love him for it.
But he belongs to me,
and I belong to him.
Indeed.
And what are you going to do?
I'm going to get him out.
But your nephew assured me
that you do have influence.
My nephew is mistaken.
I sympathize with your
distress, but I can do nothing
for Monsieur Kern.
If you will permit me,
I have an engagement.
If you refuse to help
me, you'll regret it.
And now, mademoiselle?
Either you help me get
Ludwig Kern out of prison,
or I marry your nephew.
Nonsense.
Francois's marriage has
been arranged for years.
Will it convince you if
I were to call him and let
him speak for himself?
Please.
Do you realize
this is blackmail?
Using my nephew.
[LAUGHS] Well, it
looks as though I'll
have to help you whether
I want to or not.
To get you a permit,
mademoiselle,
will be a very simple matter.
But your friend
has been arrested
and to do something for him will
be a great deal more difficult.
[AEROPLANE ENGINE OVERHEAD]
JOSEF STEINER (VOICEOVER):
(WHISPER) Marie.
Marie.
Passport, please.
Your name.
John Huber.
How old are you?
43.
When were you born?
January 29th, 1894.
Where?
Krems an der Donau.
For what purpose are
you going to Germany?
I'm on my way to
visit relatives.
Live in Paris?
No, no.
In Graz.
I was visiting a
relative in Paris.
How long do you intend
to remain in Germany?
About two weeks.
Have you any funds with you?
Yes.
500 francs.
We'll make a note of
that in your passport.
Have you any newspapers,
periodicals or books with you?
No, nothing.
Thank you.
Give me the Gestapo
headquarters in Munich.
Hurry.
For what purpose did
you come back to Germany?
I wanted to see my
wife before she died.
Which of your political
friends have you met here?
None.
It will be better for you to
tell me before you're sentenced.
I've already told you, none.
On whose instructions
did you come back here?
I had no instructions.
With what political
organization
were you affiliated abroad?
None.
Then how did you live?
From the money I earned.
You see, I have an
Austrian passport.
You will be transferred
this afternoon.
I would like to
make a request.
It's a small matter, but
very important to me.
My wife is still alive.
The doctor said that
at most, she can only
live one or two days more.
For myself, I expect neither
sympathy nor favors of any kind.
But I should like my
wife to die in peace.
I beg you to keep me
here for one or two days
and allow me to visit my wife.
Another chance.
I can't give you such an
opportunity to escape.
I won't escape.
If someone watches
the door, there
will be nothing that I can do.
I make this request not for
myself, but for a dying woman.
Impossible.
I have no authority to grant it.
You have the authority.
You could give us
a reason that I
may tell my wife something
that's important for you
to know.
You could arrange
for a reliable nurse
to listen to what was said.
That's nonsense.
Your wife won't tell you
anything, nor will you tell her.
Of course not.
She doesn't know anything.
But she would die in peace.
Colonel, I have
already examined this man
on the subject of group four.
He refused to give me the
names of the other members,
and I'm sure there is no way
of making him talk except one.
May I have the
colonel's permission?
Proceed.
If I make it possible for you
to visit your wife for two days,
will you give me the names of
the other members of group four?
Yes.
Then give them to me.
Will you give me two names
tomorrow, and the rest
of them the day after?
I will give you all the
names the day after tomorrow.
I'll see what I can do.
[KNOCKING ON DOOR]
It's me, Mary.
Joesf.
Oh, Josef.
I want to feel
you're really here.
I knew you couldn't come, but
I've waited for you, for always.
Now I shall stay with you.
You can't stay.
You must go at once, Josef.
There's no danger.
It is dangerous.
You don't know what
it's been like.
I shouldn't last much longer.
I've seen you.
I'll be able to
face it alone now.
Please go.
I've made arrangements so
that I can stay here, Marie.
There's going to be an
amnesty, and I fall under it.
It's true.
I swear it to you, Marie.
No one need know I'm here.
But even if they
do, it won't be bad.
You haven't divorced me.
How could I?
It was only for your
sake so that things
would be easier for you.
I haven't had a bad time.
People have helped me.
That's how I happened
to have this room.
It's been nice to be alone.
You were with me more.
You must go now.
I'll come again tomorrow.
I'd like to be able to
get up and go away with you.
Just when I could be
with you, I must go.
Please don't be angry with me.
[SOMBER MUSIC]
You certainly have
taken unfair advantage
of my kindness, Steiner.
You've kept me waiting
here over three hours.
But after all, it was worth
while waiting for her.
I'll have plenty of
time with you now.
Rest of your natural
life, my friend.
And in a few moments, you will
tell me those precious names
as you promised.
I'll tell them to you now.
[SCREAMING]
The only one I've been
able to help is myself.
What good is this permit to me
if I can't get one for Ludwig?
I'm so worried.
They'll be deporting him any day
now, and he'll just disappear.
I may never find him again.
What is Durant's
lawyer saying?
He says something might
be done to help Ludwig,
but it takes money.
A lot more than we have.
You have enough, I think.
How very much mistaken, Leo.
Unfortunately,
I'm not mistaken.
Not after today.
I hope I get there
before they deport him.
Plenty of time.
All day, in fact.
They never move them across
the border before dark.
Good luck.
Thank you.
Goodbye.
You will be conducted
to the Swiss border.
Understand you're
not to come back.
Sign here then, and see
that you don't come back.
Don't worry.
I won't.
Conductor, what on
earth's the matter?
Wreck, madam.
How long we'll be here?
One hour maybe.
Kern.
Ah.
But they are taking
him to the border.
Now?
Where is he?
Where is he, please?
Where's who?
The prisoner, Ludwig Kern.
Look.
Won't you help me
get him back, please?
He'll be gone.
I won't see him again.
I'll lose him.
Ah-huh.
I understand.
An affair of the heart.
Don't worry, mademoiselle.
Go after him.
Get on the thing
and bring him back.
Quick.
Hurry.
It's a surprise, isn't it?
Is it really an order?
Yes, absolutely.
I congratulate you.
[LAUGHS] Say, look.
Through this piece
of paper, I've
become a respectable
person, a free man who can
do what he likes, haven't I?
Absolutely.
Don't you find that strange?
What's strange about it?
Well, yesterday, I was
a same man I am today.
Yet yesterday, everything
was prohibited, illegal?
Not yesterday.
The day before yesterday.
The date on your
permit is yesterday.
All right. day
before yesterday.
Day before yesterday, my
existence was a crime.
And today, I can
breathe and sleep
and live at peace and
everything's all right.
Don't you find that strange?
Not in the slightest.
I find it quite in order.
You have the right to live in
writing, stamped and signed.
So everything is clear.
Oh.
Come on.
Your girl is waiting.
Steiners money.
He told Marril he wanted
to help us stay together.
You have a cigarette?
Yes.
He wasn't afraid.
He wasn't afraid to hate evil,
to live with self-respect,
to die to keep it.
It'll be much easier now.
We have real papers.
We can go anywhere we like.
We can go abroad
to South America.
Maybe-- maybe even
the United States.
United States.
Oh, but wait.
First thing we'll do,
we'll get married.
Understand married.
We may not have a home
anywhere for a while,
but we'll be together.
That's home, darling.
[MUSIC PLAYING]