? Mon ami Pierrot
? Prête-moi ta plume
? Pour écrire un mot
? Ma chandelle est morte
? Je n'ai plus de feu
? Ouvre-moi ta porte
? Pour l'amour de Dieu
? Ma chandelle est morte
? Je n'ai plus de feu
? Ouvre-moi ta porte
? Pour l'amour de Dieu
? Au jardin de mon pére
les lauriers sont fleuris
- Bonsoir, monsieur.
- Bonsoir, madame.
Combien coûte le cidre là-bas?
- Ça, cidre?
- Oui, oui.
- Cinq francs.
- Oh, c'est trop cher. Bonsoir, monsieur.
Bonsoir, madame.
? Auprés de ma blonde
? Qu'il fait bon fait bon fait bon
Enfin, ma belle.
Let go of me! How dare you, you brutes!
Let go of me.
You didn't get away this time, huh?
- She's English.
- What's she doing here?
- Stealing.
- It's a lie! Keep your dirty hands off me!
How dare you touch me!
I can buy thousands of bottles of your filthy wine.
I'll show you who I am.
Ah, I didn't recognise you. Forgive me, my lady.
My lady is right, you pig.
Qu'est-ce que vous...
(Screams)
Here, dearie, it'll do you good.
Thank you, dear.
You've all been very kind.
I didn't mean to get you into trouble.
No trouble at all.
I always wanted to kick that swine in the pants,
anyhow. I'm glad I done it.
I'm English, too.
My name's Smith - Mary Smith.
What's yours, dearie?
- Emma.
I knew a girl whose name was Emma.
Emily Burrows.
What's yours?
My name?
My name is Emma Lady Hamilton.
Oh...
That's one on me.
It serves me right. I shouldn't be so nosy.
Well, darlin',
if you don't want to tell me your name,
I'd be the last one to poke my nose
in anybody's secrets.
I remember my mother telling me Lady Hamilton
was the most beautiful woman in the world.
Have you got a mirror?
Yes.
Better you didn't, dearie.
Oh, well.
I know it.
I know that face.
For ten years it has looked back at me
from different mirrors.
It must be me.
But I always wait for the miracle,
that one time, just once more,
when it will be another face
that looks at me again.
A face I knew before.
But that face must be dead.
Go on, tell us all about it.
It doesn't matter if it's true or not.
True or not.
I don't know it myself.
It's so long ago, I don't know it anymore.
My life really began when I was 18
I was beautiful then
Coach from London!
One day I arrived in Naples
At the palace of His Excellency
the British Ambassador
How's London, Gavin?
- How's my nephew? Did he send everything?
- It's all here, Your Excellency.
Give me a hand with this chisel!
- Mr Greville sends his regards.
- Don't bother me about Mr Greville now!
- Give me a hammer and chisel.
- It's most important, sir.
Exquisite.
Come and look at this.
- Enchanting. Whose work is it?
- George Romney.
If he could paint reality, he would be a master.
Isn't that reality?
The ideal an artist dreams of.
No woman ever lived with such colouring,
such god-like simplicity.
I thought so too till I met her.
You've met her?
In London, last year. And if you're patient,
you may see her in Naples one day.
- Your Excellency.
- Oh, not now, Gavin. I'll see you presently.
But I must tell you.
Very well, if you must, but tell me quickly.
Mum? Mum? Look, it's lovely.
It's a real palace.
Oh, I do hope Sir William will like us.
Don't worry, darling. Of course he'll like you.
I'll do all the talking. Charlie told me exactly what
to answer to everything.
Why on earth didn't you tell me?
Where are they?
Sshh. Here he comes.
You must forgive me. It's disgraceful.
I'd no idea you'd come.
- How do you do, Miss er...
- Emma Hart, if it pleases Your Excellency.
- How could I forget?
- This is my mother, Your Excellency.
Welcome to Naples, madam.
This is my friend the French Ambassador.
Did you stay in Rome?
Yes, Your Excellency
and thought it very beautiful.
We saw the Colosseum by moonlight
and were deeply impressed by the Vatican.
We just missed the Pope by ten minutes.
That was a great pity, madam.
Did you come through Pisa?
Did you see the famous leaning tower?
Yes, Your Excellency,
and we thought it very beautiful.
We thought the leaning tower of Pisa
one of the most remarkable
and lovely phenomena in the whole of Europe.
A chimney went like that in Liverpool last year
at the soap works.
It leant right over the gin warehouse and
the Bishop said it was the finger of God.
Charles - Mr Greville - sent you
many kind wishes, Your Excellency.
And he hopes I will prove worthy
of your kindness
and speak good French and Italian when
he comes to take me home in October.
He is coming the first week in October.
And er... he sent his uncle... a kiss.
Well, that's the first present I've ever received
from Charles Greville.
I feel sure you must be tired after your journey,
madam.
Francis, show the ladies their rooms.
Au revoir, madam. Au revoir, Miss Hart.
- Who is she?
- Charles Greville found her.
Where can you find things like that?
Charles happened to find her
at Featherstone Castle - Sir Harry's place.
- Oh, she's a relation of Sir Harry?
- You might call her that.
She lived there for a whole hunting season
and a very gay hunting season it was, I'm told.
Oh. And where did Sir Harry find her?
Well, you remember Dr Graham's Temple of Hell
and the famous dance of the seven veils?
- She's a dancer?
- You might call her that.
She was quite a success.
The fewer the veils the greater the success.
But, alas, the police locked the place
just after the last veil fell.
The older I get,
the less I seem to know about women.
It's the penalty of your wicked youth,
Your Excellency.
Don't ask me what happened to her before.
The usual past, I suppose.
A poor little country girl wronged once
and then wronged again.
The old story.
Lower and lower, but always up and up.
And now she's the guest of an ambassador.
With a past like that.
Past?
Look at this statue.
Two hundred years in a Greek temple.
Then thrown into the mud
by some barbarian soldier.
2,000 years sinking lower and lower into the
mud, then dug up by the plough of a peasant,
changing hands every year until at last
it comes to its rightful place.
Into the hands of someone
who understands the glory of its beauty.
Because, my friend, it is still beautiful, isn't it,
despite its past?
Gavin.
I'll dine tonight with Miss Hart
Alone, at eight o'clock.
GAVlN: Yes Your Excellency
Thank you, my man.
I'll ring for you later, if I want you.
Very good, madam.
Two ambassadors, Mum, two!
Well, what did you think of me?
Wasn't I wonderful?
You were all that, darling, and more.
So far, so good.
But, please, Mum, not another word about the
soap factory. Not till I've married Charlie.
Charlie said Sir William was very fussy
about that sort of thing.
Don't worry your pretty head
about Sir William.
You'll have him eating out of your hand
within three months.
Three months? Three days?
He'll be eating out of it tonight.
And in a month,
Charlie will be here to take us home.
How pleased he'll be with me.
He will indeed, but there's no great hurry.
It's very nice here just now
and it's not costing us a farthing.
It's all very well for you, but what about me?
''Yes, Your Excellency. No, Your Excellency.
Of course, Your Excellency.''
- Oh, how I miss my Charlie.
- Yes, he's a likely, young fellow.
Burt there's no-one good enough for my Emily,
though it's her own mother who says so.
But, Mother, I wouldn't exist without Charlie.
He's done everything for me, everything.
Well, he's... made me a lady.
I know, darling, I know.
Oh! Look at that mountain
with the smoke coming out of it.
The coachman said it went off a few years ago
and killed several people.
That would never happen in Liverpool.
Oh, Mother, you're hopeless. That's a famous
volcano. People come miles to see it.
What do they call it? Charles told me 100 times.
Smoking mountain. Vesuvius, that's it, Vesuvius.
If Sir William asks you what you think
of it, just say it's lovely.
- Yes, dear.
- It's mixed up with the history of Ancient Rome.
Nero set it on fire and said the Christians did it.
Remember, Mother, it's knowing little things
like that that makes you a lady.
(String quartet plays minuet)
Whenever I have a nice piece of fish,
it always makes me think of the sea.
- The what?
- The sea Your Excellency
Oh, yes.
Charles was wonderful about things like that.
- About fish?
- Oh!
You're so funny, Your Excellency.
Every time you call me ''Your Excellency'',
it adds one year to my life.
- Sir William?
- That's getting better
Tell me, my dear.
Was my nephew so positive about coming here?
Oh, absolutely. He would have brought me here
himself, if he hadn't been detained in London.
Just a second, my dear.
As we're to live together under the same roof
I see no reason why we should not
be perfectly frank with one another
As much as I hate to spoil this beautiful picture
that you have drawn for yourseIf of my nephew,
there's one point that must be made quite clear.
Charles Greville will never come to Naples
But, Your Excellency, Uncle,
he definitely promised.
There is a wide gap between my nephew's
promises and his fulfilment of them
The promise he gave me, he will keep.
Your confidence in him is really touching.
Did he promise you marriage as well?
Why deny it? It must be written all over me.
I'm afraid I've got to destroy
those sweet dreams of yours.
My nephew never had the slightest intention
of marrying you.
Either with my consent or without it.
What did you say, Your Excellency?
I said he's not going to marry you, Emma.
But that's not possible.
Why should he send me here with my mother?
It costs a lot of money, the journey.
Perhaps he feIt you would be better off
with his uncle. A nice vacation.
But I didn't need a vacation.
No. No, there must be something else.
And what's to happen after the vacation,
if he doesn't want to marry me?
He's talked of nothing else for years.
It was his idea. I never urged him.
I was quite happy with him just as it was.
Tell me, Your Excellency,
but please tell me the truth.
Did Charles tell you about me?
Do you know about my
He did. And I imagine that was the only thing
he did not lie about.
Oh but please my dear,
I don't want to make you feel ashamed.
Ashamed? Oh, I'm not ashamed.
There's nothing to be ashamed of.
It's true there were men in my life
before Charles, I admit it.
I made mistakes, I was young, I was stupid.
I believed in men and their promises.
Charles knew about me
before he took me into the house,
before he promised to marry me.
And now I'm different, not only my clothes,
but inside.
I'm good. I know I'm good.
So why should he lie to me?
Why did he send me here?
What am I doing here?
Charles had a lot of debts. Did you know that?
Yes, quite a lot, I know.
His debts have been paid to the tune of £5,000.
Besides he has plenty of cash
to save him from new debts for a long time
Oh, I see.
see
He sold you antiques, paintings, and among
the bric-a-brac, a certain Emma Hart.
(Sobs) That wasn't fair.
That wasn't gentlemanlike.
He shouldn't have raised me up
just to throw me down again.
My dear.
Leave me alone. You're just as bad as he is.
Perhaps you haven't made
such a good bargain after all.
I'm not going to stay here.
I'm going away now. Now!
(Sobs)
Oh, don't take it to heart, my dear.
Forget Charles, forget the old memories,
forget London.
I can offer you a new life
and a far more exciting one.
Naples is a wonderful city.
You'll be a success here. You'll like it.
Perhaps not today, nor even tomorrow.
But you are young and the young heal quickly.
You will learn singing and music
under the greatest masters in Italy.
You will speak French and Italian
with our finest teachers.
Everyone of account in Europe comes to my
house. You will meet them all.
You will dine with famous soldiers,
artists and statesmen.
You can't be presented at court, of course,
but you will have a villa by the sea and a coach.
You will have your private box at the opera.
Ever since I first saw you in London,
I feIt this house of mine to be empty,
missing its greatest and most lovely ornament.
You will be that ornament, my dear.
And except for that absurd presentation at court,
you will have everything in life
that a woman could possibly dream of.
What did you say?
Nothing. Try to sleep.
Goodnight, Emma.
MOTHER: What's wrong, darling?
Oh, mum!
Dear, dear.
(Sobs) Mum, I'm so miserable.
- What's wrong?
- He never wanted to marry me.
He got £5,000 from the old man
to send me here.
He never wanted to marry me.
Don't cry, my sweet.
You're too good for any of them.
I'm going to pack now.
We'll go right back to London and you can give
that precious Mr Greville a piece of your mind.
Plenty of good men want to marry my Emily.
There, now, darling. Don't cry.
There's just as good fish in the sea
as ever came out of it.
(Emma Sobs)
Darling, precious Emily, there, now.
EMMA: And I forgot London
and the old memories.
I was young I healed quickly.
I learnt French, Italian, singing, and music.
One day I had more than I ever dreamed of.
I became his wife - Emma Lady Hamilton.
(Singing)
Sshh!
My daughter, Her Ladyship, is still asleep.
- Good morning, Contessa.
- Good morning.
My daughter, Her Ladyship, is still resting.
Perhaps you wouldn't mind waiting a little while.
- How was Her Majesty this morning?
- Her cold is troublesome. Her throat is sore.
- Has it gone out of her nose?
-No.
The best way to cure a sore throat
is to wrap a woollen sock at night, going to bed.
- Oh?
- Good morning. Good morning, Contessa.
Good morning, Your Excellency.
- Is Emma still asleep?
- She is asleep.
In my village, a husband just turns round in bed
and looks for himseIf to know.
Yes, and the Queen of Naples does not wear
woollen socks to pin around her throat.
If the Queen of Naples wore a hefty pair of
woollen socks, she wouldn't have a sore throat.
(Explosion outside)
(Explosion)
- What's happened?
- I don't know.
(Explosion)
Maybe the smoking mountain went off again.
Let's see. Come along.
(Explosions continue)
(Explosion)
How wonderful! A battleship.
You should see the Queen about this.
Salutes at this hour of the morning.
Why shouldn't they blow their cannons off?
That's what they've got them for.
Boom!
- Boom!
- Good morning, my dear.
Boom! Good morning, William.
Here, give it to me.
? Rule Britannia
Let me look, my dear.
There's a small boat coming ashore.
They will probably need me.
Excuse me, my dear.
- The mail is just in, Emma.
- I'll attend to it later.
Here's a nice fat one from London.
Oh.
(Reads) Her Excellency, Emma Lady Hamilton,
British Embassy, Naples.
Charles Greville, London.
Open it, child, open it.
I think not. Send it back
and write on it, ''Unopened. Return to sender''.
Poor Charles. He's exactly three years too late.
And as far as I'm concerned,
he simply doesn't exist.
Are you happy, my child?
Happy?
Three years ago, my only idea of happiness
was to be married to Charles Greville.
After that, I wanted revenge.
Well, I got that in a way, too.
Then I wanted to be presented at court.
And even that impossible wish was granted
to me.
I've got everything.
Everything a woman of the world
could possibly wish for.
So why shouldn't I be happy?
Of course, I'm happy, Mother.
Well, Emma, what's good enough for you
is good enough for me.
And being mother to Her Ladyship
is not to be sneezed at either.
(Laughs)
- You silly old thing.
You're lovely, Emma.
You're so beautiful, Emma.
And what about you? Look at you with
your little cap and your silver buttons.
And your beautiful skirt.
You're the beautiful one.
Your Ladyship,
could you spare me a moment, please?
Yes, Gavin. I'm in a great hurry.
It's about the dinner invitations for Sunday night.
Then, of course, His Eminence the Archbishop,
the Duchess of Argyle,
and if there's no performance
the Prima Donna of the San Carlo.
- And the two ladies - which is deaf?
- The Contessa Giovanni.
We put her on Sir William's right.
Marquess Compiani the old harpy,
and the French Ambassador -
we'll put him there between them.
Oh, he'll have a nice time.
Beg pardon, My Lady, but Sir William informs
me the French Ambassador cannot be invited.
- Why ever not?
- Sir William mentioned
Sir William mentioned... Sir William mentioned
there's a difference between the er...
William, what's this absurd business
about the French Ambassador?
l need him for the party on Sunday night.
My dear, may I introduce
the captain of the Agamemnon?
How do you do? But William, I need him.
He's amusing and he's a bachelor and I need
a single man to make my number even.
I'm sorry, my dear, but we won't be seeing
the French Ambassador for quite some time.
Why? What's the matter with him?
The captain can explain that.
- He has a message.
- We're at war with France.
War? That's torn it.
Bang goes the French Ambassador.
Oh, dear. Who can I get to sit between
these two dreary old ladies?
My dear captain, we shall be so delighted
if you will dine with us on Sunday night.
You will sit between the two most amusing
and charming ladies in Naples.
You're very kind, but I sail tonight.
Oh, then I gather you must be in a hurry.
Don't let me disturb your conference. I'm going.
Well, Captain, you were saying
that the Admiral of the Fleet wanted...
Yes, sir.
Lord Hood advised me to instruct you...
It's all right, Captain,
I have no secrets from Lady Hamilton.
I'm very sorry, Sir William. You must forgive me.
I'm not used to discussing matters of this kind
in the presence of ladies.
Oh. Is it as wicked as all that? Good gracious.
I promised to be with the Queen at 1 2.
She won't order a single new dress
until I've discussed the patterns with her.
That's a very great responsibility, my dear.
- Goodbye, William.
- Goodbye.
We've captured Toulon.
The Admiral needs 10 000 troops to hold it
It would take three weeks from England
From here, they should be in Toulon in two
days.
The treaty between England and Naples
provides full co-operation
and the Admiral expects you to secure those
troops from the King of Naples.
I'll apply for an audience with the King.
But surely in a matter as urgent as this,
we could see the King at once.
At once? I can't just walk into the Royal Palace.
Well, when will you get the audience?
Friday may be possible.
Saturday almost certain.
But we must have these troops immediately.
You must leave this in my hands.
You see, I know these people and you don't.
I'll make out the application at once.
EMMA: Yes, that's me too.
Do you like it? It's a Romney.
Circe watching her lover sail away.
Is it?
You know, I could get you those troops like that.
You were speaking rather loudly, Captain, and
the houses get so stuffy if you close the doors.
You're worried, aren't you?
You have an important mission, haven't you?
Has it ever occurred to you that women can
sometimes be of more help than men?
Not in a matter of this kind, Lady Hamilton.
How do you know?
It just happens that I shall be seeing the Queen
within the next ten minutes.
The Queen? This is an important matter of state.
All the more reason to see the Queen.
Now I'll let you into a secret, Captain.
Which everyone in Europe knows.
Except you, Captain.
The real King of Naples is the Queen.
E licenziata, hai capito?
(The children's chatter drowns her out)
Her Majesty is pleased
to be with her children this hour.
But my orders are to let My Lady in any time.
Even if the princes and princesses please
to be with their august parents.
The august family appears to be pretty big.
The marriage of the august parents
is continuously blessed.
There are 15 princes and princesses so far.
You will see.
(Pandemonium)
Lady Hamilton!
(Dog barks)
(Pandemonium drowns out conversation)
''I have the honour to be etc, etc, etc.''
And I'll sign it at once.
Phew!
Here we are, Captain. I'll have this application
to the palace in haIf an hour.
I thought it advisable to ask for only 8,000 men.
We may get as many as 5,000.
We asked for 20,000 and we got 1 0,000. There.
I'm very much indebted to Lady Hamilton
Her campaign against the Queen
was a masterpiece of strategy.
Well, there, my dear captain,
you see the real Ambassador to Naples.
At least to the Queen of Naples.
Captain, now that you have your soldiers,
there's no need for you to leave so soon.
You can go tomorrow. We'll have a wonderful
party on your ship tonight.
I'll bring the Queen and you'll get the King if
you'll allow him to conduct the ship's orchestra.
We'll sail out to Capri.
By midnight, we'll be at the Blue Grotto.
Capri by moonlight.
You've no idea how beautiful the world can be.
We'll decorate the ship with flowers. And I'll
dance. I expect you've heard of my dances.
The Dance Of The Nymph
goes beautifully with a night on a ship
I'll wear a long tunic of pale blue cashmere.
No high coiffure. Just loose hair.
Like a Greek Goddess Gavin we're to have
a party on the battleship tonight
Get out the Chinese lanterns
to send to the harbour.
And ask the chef to make big steak pies,
100 of them.
And get some rum for the sailors.
It is rum they drink, isn't it, Captain?
It will be magnificent, stupendous.
- Won't I be wonderful, William?
- You will.
I'm sorry to be ungallant, but I've just been
summoned to weigh anchor immediately.
May I present my son,
midshipman on the Agamemnon?
Such a big son.
- My step-son.
-Your wife lives in England?
Yes, sir, in Norfolk.
And this young man is your chaperone.
Precisely. He keeps a good watch on me.
- Goodbye, Sir William.
- Goodbye, Captain.
Goodbye, Lady Hamilton.
May I say,
you've done good service for your country?
It's been rather fun, hasn't it? If you're passing
Naples again, I hope you'll come and see us.
And next time, there's no need to blow off
your cannons, just knock at the door.
Goodbye.
What was your name?
Nelson.
William, did I seem very silly,
talking about the party in the moonlight?
Silly? Of course, my dear.
But delightfully silly. My Emma at her best.
I wonder.
He was so serious.
All of a sudden, I began to feel foolish.
I don't think a woman can be at her best,
playing the fool with news of war.
Don't think about it, my dear.
War is a sordid, ugly thing,
so there's no need for them to bother you.
My Lady, your dancing master's here.
- Shall I show him to the dancing room?
-No, send him away.
- But, Emma.
- I don't feel like dancing.
William, you've left certain gaps in my
education. This war, for instance.
- I know nothing about it.
- But my dear...
Every time I ask you a serious question,
you begin shuffling about.
Tell me about it. How did it happen?
- It's very dull, my dear.
- I don't care how dull it is. I want to know.
Well...
here's England.
Such a tiny little bit.
Where are we?
Here at Naples.
But why should England fight?
Because all through these centuries,
she has built up a commonwealth,
in which every little spot has its purpose
and value to the balance line of life.
And there are always men,
who for the sake of their insane ambition,
want to destroy what other people build.
And therefore, this tiny little bit,
as you call it, Emma,
has to send out its ships again and again to fight
those who want to dictate their will to others.
EMMA: Then came five years of war
We fought alone with no allies
The whole of Europe in deadly fear
of Napoleon Bonaparte
Nothing between him and the conquest
of the world but a few ships
And Nelson
MAN: His Majesty is pleased to award you
the Knighthood of the Bath
and you are promoted to Rear Admiral
of the Blue
Sir Horatio, that's wonderful.
The men will be delighted.
Oh, yes.
We'll catch Bonaparte in a week,
if we have an extra button on our coat tails.
Five years of this war and gentlemen in London
think that men can go on without water or food.
And I can fight the enemy without ammunition.
Even His Excellency the Ambassador here
sees fit to ignore our plight.
What's the matter with the lamp?
It's nearly empty, sir. No more oil on board.
Well, turn it down.
NELSON: Hardy?
- Yes, sir.
Sir Horatio from now on, sir.
Oh, not to you, Hardy.
Captain always, I hope.
Captain or Sir Horatio,
I can't stand this any longer.
What's Sir William Hamilton doing?
Why don't we sail up to Naples
and blow 'em out of their beds?
They'd give us water and meat then.
- Do you expect me to fire at a neutral port?
- Neutral?
Neutral against England?
Yes. Things were different when we were here
five years ago, weren't they?
Our braid was shining in those days.
Today they won't even let us anchor
in the harbour as though we had the plague.
They're so scared of Bonaparte,
they daren't help the people who fight him.
Starboard!
What a wonderful way to get upstairs.
How exciting.
At last I'm on a battleship.
NELSON: Trowbridge, did you get anything?
Sir, there is someone here with me.
- The Ambassador.
- No sir Lady Hamilton
Is there no light? I can't see anything.
Everything's so dark.
Where's Horatio?
Turn up the lamp Josiah
NELSON: How is Sir William? Ill, I presume?
You must please forgive me
if I seem a little abrupt.
We've been living here under great difficulties.
No food or fresh water.
No rum no tobacco
The Neapolitans have forgotten that they're our
allies and that we're fighting for their cause too.
That is why I sent Trowbridge to ask Sir William
to remind the King...
What is the matter?
Oh... Why, I'm sorry, yes.
You must please excuse these little souvenirs
of Calvi and Tenerife.
I had no idea.
They told us of your victories,
but not of the price you had paid.
Do not distress yourself, please.
Tell me your news. Did Sir William see the King?
- The King refused to see him.
- Refused to see the British Ambassador?
I ought to have said
he was too terrified to see him.
You cannot realise how Naples has changed.
Have they gone out of their senses?
What do they think I am trying to do?
Bonaparte's fleet is in Egypt.
For the first time I know where they are.
If I can smash them up,
Europe has a chance to breathe again.
And it's the first time he's been stopped.
And yet they will not give me food or water
for my ships.
When I saw that William was wasting his time,
I took the liberty of seeing the Queen.
I've never had such a time in all my life.
She's terrified of the French.
- But I got it.
- What is that?
A mandate, signed and sealed
by the Queen's own hand,
for the full watering and victualling of the British
fleet in any port in the Kingdom of Naples.
There.
Look out, Bonaparte.
By gad, we shall lick you now.
Tell the Queen I kiss her letter.
Tell her I hope to kiss her hand
when we return from our victory.
Won't you sit down? You must be tired.
Do you remember the picnic we planned at
Capri on your ship?
When I was going to dance in the moonlight
with my hair down five years ago.
Or was it five centuries?
When I rudely sailed away.
And now you're going to rudely sail away again.
How's it been with you all these years?
Alone, you know.
You've done a great many things.
How is your wife?
Oh, she's well enough, I believe.
And when are you going to meet Bonaparte?
- Soon, I hope.
- He's got haIf of Europe
Now it's Egypt.
Tomorrow it may be lndia.
We are alone, but unafraid.
SAlLOR: Haul away!
You long to leave, don't you?
Never lose an hour or waste a wind
Goodbye, Sir Horatio.
It's a bit of a mouthful, isn't it?
Yes. Goodbye, Lady Hamilton.
You've helped us for the second time.
EMMA:
He didn't lose an hour. He didn't waste a wind.
He met his great opponent
and he defeated him on the Nile
And when the battle was over
he didn't go back to his country or to his king
or to his wife
he came back
to me
(Band plays)
? A Life On The Ocean Wave
? Fanfare
- Stop. Fetch a doctor quickly.
(Band stops playing)
Fetch a doctor quickly. Send everyone away.
A doctor quickly.
(Murmuring)
What's come over you, madam?
A doctor? Who wants a doctor?
But you staggered out there and nearly fell.
I'm perfectly well.
GUARD: Shoul...der!
Your Majesty, I'm amazed.
Cosa dice?
l must speak to the King. Help me, Sir William.
Lui vuole parlare con te.
Va bene.
Aspetta qui.
Tell him I didn't come to Naples to be feted.
In other times, I should be grateful,
but today I am appalled by it.
I came here expecting to find an armed camp
and I find this tragic carnival.
This Battle of the Nile that he's celebrating
may have destroyed their fleet,
but his army's as strong as ever
and two days' from Naples.
Yet the men of Naples dance in the streets
with paper caps and toy balloons.
Maestà, Nelson dice che non è venuto
à Napoli per...
Qu'est qu'il y a, ma chère?
He says he has confidence in the English
and feels sure they will do what is necessary.
Well, tell him we're not the guardian angels of
every country too lazy to look after itself.
You've got to do something too!
At the Nile, we cleared them off the seas,
but as long as they have armies on land,
no country in Europe is free.
They want to get hold of the whole world.
If you value your freedom, stir yourselves.
Prepare and help drive them off the land!
Ma perche l'Ammiraglio è cosi nervoso?
I'm talking of Bonaparte, Your Majesty!
Bonaparte!
Either advance toward him sword in hand
or else be kicked out of your kingdom.
Lady Hamilton, may I speak to you?
You called for a doctor just now.
I'm so sorry. I didn't mean to upset you.
I thought you were ill.
Well, for heaven's sake...
..where is the doctor?
This is the third time you've helped me.
You've been here night and day. How long?
EMMA: Nine days
- What an enormous bed.
- It's my bed
There's room for six people in it.
There may be. I've never tried.
Why am in your bed?
They couldn't move you to the hospital
Of all that ghastly crowd, you were
the only one who knew that I was ill.
A nice cup of beef tea.
- That'll put some go into him.
- Who's that?
It's all right, milord. Just Emma's mother.
Emma's mother...
..do you think I could call her Emma too?
Why ask me?
You've been calling her Emma all this time.
Now, don't say anymore.
Here you are.
There.
Now I'll tell you all the news
and all the gossip too, if you're interested.
First item, the King of England is pleased
to elevate Sir Horatio Nelson to the peerage.
You are now Lord Nelson.
Second item, the King of Naples has given you
the dukedom of Bronte.
You are now a duke and a baron.
Third item, the whole of Europe sings
your praises, the victor of the Nile.
It wouldn't have been possible without you.
I'm going to tell them.
I'm going to let the whole world know.
I told you not to talk. You've got to rest.
In a week, you can get up. Then for another
week, you can have nothing but goat's milk.
Disgusting.
I shall be able to get up in a day or two..
You can get up
when you are told you can get up.
Yes, ma'am. Goat's milk for a week and
I get up when I'm told.
(Laughs) That's better.
We need you now, Lord Nelson.
In these times the whole world needs you.
And I need you more than anyone else.
As soon as you are well, the King has
commanded a gala performance of the opera
and I want to wear my new dress from London.
Gala performance?
Opera?
When they ought to be mobilising armies.
They're doomed and don't want to realise it.
You mustn't excite yourself.
Would you do me a kindness
and write a letter for me, Emma?
Of course.
To whom?
Lady Nelson.
Burnham Thorpe Norfolk England
I wonder what she looks like now.
I haven't seen her for seven years
I wonder why we sailors ever marry
Do you want that to go in?
Good heavens, no. (Laughs)
My dear wife
My dear wife...
My heartiest greetings from Naples
to you and Father.
I'm in the house of the Hamiltons
and it has taken all their care
and kindness to pull me through.
I hope some day to have the pleasure
of introducing you to Lady Hamilton
Lady Hamilton is one of the very best women
in the world...
and an honour to her sex
? La ci darem la mano
? La mi dirai di si
? Vedi, non è lontano
? Partiam, ben mio, da qui
? Vorrei e mon ver-rai
(King hums)
Ferdinando!
? Mi tremaun pocoil cor
? Felice e ver sarei
? Ma puo burlarmiancor
? Neopolitan folk song
Do you know what they're having
at the palace now?
Mushrooms from Switzerland,
pheasants from England,
wine from Spain.
120 years old and £5 a bottle.
And here sits the hero of the evening
missing it all.
Are you missing it all?
Of course not. The real and exclusive party
of the evening is here.
Besides, I know exactly
what's happening at the palace.
The Queen...
Ferdinando! Taci! Taci! Ferdinando!
And the King, the poor little King
with 15 children and the Kingdom of Naples
and never an answer to give to his queen.
And here sits the British Ambassador.
Bored and dreaming only
of his last statue from Pompeii.
And throughout the evening
there sits Lord Nelson,
exhibiting his various moods one by one.
Lord Nelson in a bad mood.
Lord Nelson in a good mood.
Lord Nelson in an exuberant mood.
(He laughs) Am I really such a dull fellow?
Only when you ask questions like that.
And now it's my turn to give you
a little presentation.
What mood is this?
One guess.
Nelson allowing himself
to be just a little bit happy?
Nelson in love.
(Raucous laughter)
(Outburst of laughter)
Of all the inns in Naples, you choose this one.
Probably the last place in Naples
where they expected to find me.
Were you at the opera tonight, my dear?
No? You should have been.
There was quite a profusion of barmaids.
Some even found their way to the royal box
(Laughter)
He's drunk.
l see you're not married, my dear. What a pity.
Married women are bestowing their favours
so cheaply these days
He's never behaved like this before.
Friends, I give you the real hero of the hour.
Sir William Hamilton.
(Laughter)
That's an excellent toast, Josiah.
May I drink it with you?
Thank you.
Sir William Hamilton.
Lady Hamilton and I are leaving. Fetch a cab.
Don't let us disturb you, lads. You're off duty.
Enjoy yourselves.
Forgive them, my dear.
They are very... very young.
I have forgiven them.
That's the way people look at these things.
They do not believe in a friendship
between a man and a woman.
Do you?
All right, later. Later.
It was magnificent! Stupendous!
Wasn't I wonderful, William?
Wasn't it a success?
A triumph.
The greatest ball ever seen in Naples.
You were stupendous.
You entertained 200 people as easily
as you enchant a solitary husband.
The King said to me, ''Milady, la sua bellezza mi
fa dimenticare tutte le pensieri della realta.''
And Hardy, good old Hardy said,
''Well, I'll be blowed, Your Ladyship.
What I mean to say is,
well, you know what I mean.''
And... Oh, goodness! I'm so tired!
What did he say?
He who?
He.
Oh, he didn't say anything.
He never says much, you know.
People were saying that he should have sat
on your right during dinner,
not on your left
What? And give the Queen the side
with the eye on it? Not likely.
He seemed very happy.
Yes, I really think he's better now.
Tonight, he seemed to forget everything.
Ships, the war, Napoleon, everything.
Could any man think of worldly cares
in the spell of Emma's magic?
He deserved his happiness this evening
After such happiness how sad to find oneself
the next morning at sea again.
And at war
What do you mean?
We're going to Pompeii tomorrow.
Lord Nelson will be on his way to Malta.
I think there must be some mistake, William.
Lord Nelson left ten minutes ago and said
he would be with us at 12 tomorrow.
The dispatch arrived while dessert
was being served.
I had it sent straight aboard his ship
He's probably reading it at this very moment
Why didn't you tell me this before, William?
But my dear I wouldn't have spoilt
your evening for anything in the world
You mean,
you wouldn't have spoiled yours for anything.
You tried to prevent me
from saying goodbye to him
You know Emma
there are three kinds of deceived husbands
in the world.
First there are those
who were born to be deceived.
Second, who do not know.
And third, who do not care.
I've been wondering for some time now,
which of the three I should be myself.
Have you forgotten the fourth kind, William?
The kind that is hard and empty
and gives nothing.
You married me because you wanted
a new ornament for your house.
Like that painting or that statue or that vase.
As far as you're concerned,
I'm just as ornamental.
And just as dead.
But, my dear,
how can you call my statues dead?
When I'm alone and rather tired, think what
it means for me to have my statues with me.
To know that they'll always be lovely,
will never grow old,
and never walk out with sailors.
What a pity you're not going to see him again.
It would have been a farewell scene
of lasting beauty.
I shall sleep beautifully tonight.
Good night, my dear.
My darling...come back.
Come back.
Emily, he's waiting for you...out on the balcony.
(Bell rings)
(Foghorn)
You shouldn't have come.
People will see you. They'll talk.
Oh, let them talk. I don't care. Do you?
Are you sorry?
I'm only sorry for all the wasted years
I've been without you.
For all the years I shall have to be without you.
You'll come back, won't you?
I wonder if I shall.
I feel I should not.
You are married and I am married.
In the magic and music and the ballroom,
these things become rather blurred.
But they stand out very clearly in the dawn.
Your life is here.
My life is...there.
We must obey the creeds and codes
that we've sworn our lives to.
kn ow t h at must n ot co m e back
And I know that nothing in this world
can keep me away.
FlRST MATE: Up oars!
Down!
Pull, oarsmen!
Together!
(Wind roars)
If I understand you correctly, sir,
our first objective is to recover Malta.
In that case, I suggest we send
the Culloden, the Lion and the Goliath,
under Ball, to blockade the island
and then take possession of it.
Aiuto!
BO'SUN: Excuse me, sir.
What is it?
We've just picked up a fishing boat
with refugees from Naples
Refugees from Naples?
Yes, sir. They say revolution has broken out.
The Government got away, but the King
and Queen are locked up in the palace.
I don't understand everything he says sir
but there must be plenty of shooting looting
and murdering in the town
That's what you've always said, sir.
Just wait until we've gone. Serves them right.
If they can't help themselves nobody else can
This is Lord Keith's orders
We've got to meet the Alexander
the Foudroyant and the Minotaur
at the point of intersection
Blackwood, go back to your ship.
Arrange with Ball to blockade Malta.
The rest of the fleet sails to Messina
Well, what course are you taking, sir?
Back to Naples.
What are you waiting for, Trowbridge?
But, sir, Lord Keith's orders...
Lord Keith's orders are addressed to me!
Mine are addressed to you.
- Yes, sir.
- Return to your ships at once
HARDY: May I speak sir?
Yes.
I'm under your order, sir. I'll do as I'm told.
I'll sail this ship anywhere
where there's water under her keel.
But I implore you,
call Blackwood and Trowbridge back,
and send the fleet where it's ordered to
And leave our allies the King and Queen
of Naples at the mercy of that rabble?
You know what that mob will do to them.
Do you want them to build that bestial guillotine
in Naples?
But in London they will say
it wasn't the Royal Family you went back for.
- Be careful what you say!
- I will say it!
They will say it was for Lady Hamilton.
Let them say it. Let them say what they wish!
l will not see those I love
and owe loyalty to left alone.
Back to Naples
I understand, sir.
In the face of such open disobedience,
I must ask your Lordships for a clear decision.
Where is Nelson now?
At Palermo, where he took the whole party
after he got them away from Naples.
As much as I dislike discussing personalities
and private matters,
I must say he does not behave in a manner
befitting a British Admiral.
Hear, hear.
I quite agree with what you're saying.
Gentlemen.
Lord Nelson has some excuse
for his disobedience.
How can there be an excuse for disobedience?
He did save the royal family of an allied nation
from certain death at the hands of the mob.
He also saved the British Ambassador
and his wife.
- What's the point of saving the husband?
- (Laughter)
Yes, you think it very funny.
The whole of England thinks it's funny.
The whole of Europe.
- But it's high time that...
- Steady, Keith. Steady.
No-one questions the seriousness of this matter.
Lord Nelson is a very gallant sailor.
But not even the greatest hero is strong enough
to defeat the prejudices
and conventions of society.
We must be tolerant of poor Nelson.
lt'd be best to bring him home at once.
Let him say farewell
to this charming little romance of his.
Let him forget the beautiful Emma.
- Oh, that's appalling.
- It's wonderful, magnificent.
- This time we have them at our mercy.
- That's the worst hand we've had.
I know, but we will bluff them. Smile, just smile.
Fortunately, they don't understand us.
- Possiamo cominciare, Signora?
- Qual è la posta?
- Il doppio.
- But we haven't a chance.
- We shall in a minute. Smile.
- The seven of diamonds.
- The ace of diamonds.
There, you see.
The queen of clubs.
- But that's mad...
- Treble the stakes! Triplichiamo la posta.
- But, darling...
- The king of spades.
The seven of diamonds.
And the ace of hearts.
E bene, signori, a mio parere.
- Molta fortunata, signora.
- Bravissimo, signora.
By gad, you're impudent. What would
you have done if the bluff had failed?
I would have fainted and upset the table.
Now let us go.
We can't go. We must give them a chance
to retrieve their losses.
Would they give you a chance? No, come along.
I'll order the carriage and we'll drive home
by the sea. The air in here is unbearable.
Arrividerci, signori. Bon soir, monsieur.
In a minute.
Emma, there's a matter of some importance
that I must speak to you about.
Yes, William.
Ten days ago,
a dispatch came from the Admiralty,
instructing Nelson in very definite terms
to report in London at once.
What is all this to do with me?
Well, if Nelson ignores this final order,
there can be only one result.
Dismissal from the Navy
and the end of his career.
ls it worth it, Emma?
His future is in your hands, you know that.
Very well. If we must go back, we must go back.
I'll tell him tonight.
When do you wish us to leave?
We are not going to leave, Emma.
My instructions from the Admiralty say
that Nelson is to return alone.
Oh, I understand.
The Admiralty is anxious to save him from me.
And what am I expected to do?
It will be convenient, my dear. The Turkish
envoy has invited you to winter in Cairo.
Tell Nelson that you love Egypt
and that you have accepted the invitation.
You can be wonderfully convincing
when you try Emma
The moment you leave for Egypt he will have
no alternative but to obey orders and return
I know I'm asking you to do a very difficult
and painful duty.
Thank you, William.
Well, we both have our duty, haven't we?
Good luck with yours, my dear.
Well, I lost everything. I feel better for it.
What is the matter, my dear?
William has just been talking to me.
Telling me of the repeated dispatches
from the Admiralty.
He also wanted me to put on
a little performance for you.
Act One. Emma Hamilton expresses a sudden
desire to see the Sphinx and the pyramids.
Act Two. Lord Nelson pleads,
Emma Hamilton remains adamant.
Act Three. Emma Hamilton departs for Egypt.
And Lord Nelson returns to London
a sadder and wiser man.
Poor William, he was so serious about it all. I'm
convinced he was only thinking of your career.
He'd been puzzling through all sorts of stories.
What hadn't occurred to him was the truth.
How silly. How utterly silly.
To think that we should need lies, you and l.
Oh, my darling.
What is the truth?
Should I have put on that comedy for you?
- It might have helped perhaps.
- Oh, no.
I cannot put it off any longer.
I must go back this time.
They want me to go alone.
Oh, of course, you must go.
And, of course, I must go to Egypt.
I don't want to be a burden to you, my darling.
My darling.
And, of course, I will enjoy seeing the pyramids
and the Sphinx and the Nile.
Your Nile.
Oh, my darling.
Why do we always meet just to say goodbye?
? At home I left a lovely maiden
? With rosy cheeks and eyes of ocean blue
? And though my heart is sad and heavy laden
? To leave a lass I love so fond and true
(Bell rings)
What are those bells?
Have you forgotten what night this is?
The last of 1799.
Eight bells for the old year
and eight for the new.
Happy New Year, darling.
apby New Yea r
The dawn of a new century.
1 800.
How strange it sounds.
What a century it's been.
Marlborough rode to war
and Washington crossed the Delaware.
Louis XVl and Marie Antoinette.
The last of the Stuarts.
Peter The Great.
Voltaire.
Clive Of lndia.
Bonaparte.
Nelson.
Now I've kissed you through two centuries.
1 800.
The beginning of a new life for me.
A life without you.
How beautiful was the old century.
When I was with you.
Emma, say that you could never leave me.
I can never leave you.
Say that you hate the blasted pyramids.
I hate the pyramids.
That you never want to see the Sphinx.
I never want to see the Sphinx.
We'll go back to London together.
I would have died if you'd left me here.
I am Lady Nelson.
Everything has been prepared
for Your Ladyship.
Your rooms have been reserved
by the Admiralty.
Thank you. Kindly show me to my rooms.
You will find our bed linen in the green trunk.
We prefer our own sheets.
- Very good, Your Ladyship.
- Breakfast precisely at 6:45.
India tea with lemon, one four-minute egg,
two slices of thinly buttered toast.
I shall instruct the head waiter, Your Ladyship.
I dislike waiters in the rooms.
Would you arrange for a chambermaid?
As you wish...
Here, here. Go and drink a health
to Lord Nelson my son.
Thank you, sir. I will and be proud to.
I am deeply honoured to have you with us
on this great occasion, sir.
You are the guest of the British Admiralty,
Mr Nelson.
Good, then charge up a glass of port
to the British Admiralty.
And let's have it right away.
Anything for you, my dear?
No, thank you. One small glass of light port
for Mr Nelson and a warming pan for his bed.
Very good, Your Ladyship.
Wonderful! Wonderful! Lap of luxury.
No morning service and no chickens to feed.
Let's have breakfast in bed with two eggs, eh?
I've arranged everything, Father.
It's unwise to break good habits even in London.
You must remember Dr Ponsonby's words
of advice.
Dr Ponsonby's advice.
Did Dr Ponsonby's son ever sink
the French fleet?
- We're going to enjoy ourselves.
(Knock on door)
Your Ladyship, Lord Spencer is here
and wishes to be received.
Very well.
Good morning, Lady Nelson.
The Admiralty appreciates
your prompt response to its request.
I hope your accommodation is comfortable.
Quite, Lord Spencer, thank you.
- Pray, be seated.
- Thank you.
I assume that the Admiralty desires
my presence
to discuss the arrangements for my husband's
reception. When does he arrive?
He's already arrived, Lady Nelson.
What?
It was Lord Nelson's special wish
that his arrival should not be made public.
Did he include his wife in the term ''public''?
I don't recall the exact phraseology of the letter.
However, the Admiralty thought it advisable to
accede to his request.
So he arrived at Great Yarmouth yesterday
I was not aware
that Great Yarmouth is a naval port.
He travelled on the mail packet from Hamburg.
lsn't that peculiar?
I should have supposed that a victorious admiral
would arrive on his flagship.
Flagship? Oh, er...
It is not customary as you know
for ladies to travel on battleships
See.
I wondered why the Admiralty had decided
not to give my husband an official reception.
Now I understand and fully agree.
The programme for Lord Nelson's stay
in London will be a simple one.
He should be able to leave for his home
in Norfolk the day after tomorrow,
even tomorrow night.
Do I understand that my husband will be forced
to resign from the Navy?
Oh, no, no, no, no, Lady Nelson.
Hardly as drastic as that.
Extended leave for the benefit of his health
will be suggested.
A matter of different words.
That's what you mean, isn't it? I'm glad.
You were quite right
to spare the people of London.
The indignity of feting a hero who treats
with contempt the most sacred rules of life.
May I say a personal word?
Try to be forgiving, Lady Nelson.
Only the weaknesses of the great are glaring.
I prefer the official view.
Goodbye, Lady Nelson.
(Cheering outside)
Did you hear it? Cheering.
Listen. He's coming! He's coming!
Excuse me, sir. May I have your permission
to hang a flag in the balcony?
Hang two flags, three flags,
everything you've got.
Come on! Come on!
Hang the coat of arms between the flags!
Most opportune, sir. We saved the coat of arms
from King George's jubilee!
Do you realise
that these are my private rooms, sir?
Forgive me, Your Ladyship.
I had no idea this would happen.
The Admiralty told me that Lord Nelson's return
would be private and without demonstration.
We never dreamed that the public would
take the matter so completely in hand.
Has the government no control
over this vulgar demonstration?
No, ma'am. The vulgar demonstration
has control over the government.
MR NELSON: Bravo for Nelson! Bravo!
I must get back to the Admiralty,
hang out all the flags we've got.
Listen, church bells.
Victory bells for my son.
Here they are!
(Cheering continues)
Mr Nelson, my name is Hamilton.
Oh, my son's good friend.
He's often told me about you in his letters.
You're to be congratulated.
You have a great son.
Lady Nelson, I am delighted to meet you.
We had the privilege of joining your husband
in his triumphant procession across Europe.
It was overwhelming and quite exhausting,
I'm afraid, for an old man.
My wife was in her element. She swallows
a triumph like a penguin swallows a herring.
Did you have a good crossing, Sir William?
Quite rough, I'm afraid. Everyone was seasick
and I was sicker than them all.
I made the mistake of trying
to ward it off with pills.
- Oh dear dear
- What's the good of trying to fight the elements?
It's far more sensible, is it not, Lady Nelson,
and so much easier to accept their victory
whether those elements be around us
or within us
I hope we shall have the pleasure
of seeing your frequently, Lady Nelson.
He's coming! Nelson! Nelson!
Bravo for Nelson!
My boy!
How proud your mother would be
if she could see you this day.
How have you been all these years, Father?
First rate. Fanny's taken great care of me.
I'm sure she has.
There is so much I have to be grateful to you for.
How are you, my dear?
I'm very well.
And how is Burnham Thorpe?
They've named a street after us.
What an honour.
(Laughs)
EMMA: Are these Lord Nelson's rooms?
Yes milady
It was magnificent, stupendous.
Wasn't it wonderful, William?
They're wild with enthusiasm.
Come to the balcony! Quickly Quickly!
(Band plays)? For He's A Jolly Good Fellow
CROWD:? For he's a jolly good fellow
? For he's a jolly good fellow
? And so say all of us
Lady Nelson...
I am Emma Hamilton.
CROWD: Hooray! Hip hip hooray!
Hip hip hooray!
Well, it's been a great day.
A wonderful day.
And next month,
it's the choirboys' picnic at Burnham Thorpe.
(Laughs)
LADY NELSON: Why do you laugh?
Are the places of country people
of so small account?
A little more wholesome I think
than the mass hysteria we've seen today
Well, call it what you like.
It was a beautiful reception.
MOTHER: You wouldn't believe the fuss
they made about him at Naples after the battle
Whoo! Such crowds. Thousands of Italians.
All smelling of different sorts of onions.
MR NELSON: Onions?
Yes, they always do. I don't know why,
it comes out more when they get excited.
There was such a crowd round the embassy
the milkman couldn't get in
So His Lordship had to go
without his macaroni pudding.
LADY NELSON: His what?
My Emma put him on macaroni pudding
to fatten him up after the battle.
Did you ever meet the King of Naples,
Mrs Nelson?
He was a one for macaroni.
He'd take pieces that length,
open his gullet and drop it in.
Proper caution, he was
He came to see Emma with the Queen one day
and he pinched my...
He pinched me.
He pinched you? The King?
Well, you see, he's a foreigner, poor King.
He got so jealous when they cheered
His Lordship because he loved it so himself.
If you shouted outside his palace,
he'd come in and out like a cuckoo clock.
Emma... Emma, who was that other king
we met on the way home?
You know,
I get so mixed up with all these monarchs.
Oh, dear, Emma. Will you excuse me, dear?
I've been up since five.
Of course, Mother, darling. Good night.
Oh, it's good to be back in England again
to hear the Bow Bells and the muffin men
and the soot falling down your chimney.
(Mother laughs)
MR NELSON: Well Sir William
how goes the world these days?
Can we hope for a little peace now?
Well, I don't know.
What was that medicine you gave my husband?
It's some stuff my mother makes.
It's very good for coughs and colds.
I think I would prefer my husband
to see a doctor.
This weather is dreadful for him.
It was so different in Italy.
The sun always seemed to shine there.
Yes, it's never very agreeable
in the Thames Valley during the winter.
It's only for a few days. Once he's back
in Norfolk, he'll be a different man.
Do you think
you will be leaving London so soon?
Certainly. There's nothing to detain us.
Directly he's made his report to the Admiralty
and taken his seat in the House of Lords,
we shall be free to go.
Why not?
Oh...of course, yes.
What are your plans, Lady Hamilton?
I suppose you'll be going abroad again shortly?
We don't really know.
Life is so very uncertain, isn't it?
I haven't found it so.
Will you excuse me, Lady Hamilton?
It's been a very exhausting day.
- Of course. Good night.
- Good night.
Emma.
We've been living in a dream.
And now we are faced with the truth,
how ugly it is.
How terribly ugly.
But we've still got the courage to face it.
What's the good of being courageous
if you're trapped?
If you know you are wrong
and there's no way out.
I'll go to her and talk to her. Tonight. At once.
And you must talk to William.
They must understand
- Divorce?
- There is no other way
No, m y ove
That might be well enough for other people,
but not for you.
You are not an ordinary man and you cannot
behave like a Mr Jones or a Mr Thompson.
I wish I were a Mr Thompson.
Now, for the first time,
I begin to understand what William meant.
What we're doing is so dreadfully wrong.
Of course, I should have realised it before.
And because it is wrong,
it cannot bring happiness.
Those streets we came along today.
They're the very same streets I walked through
when I was a kitchen maid looking for work,
but, today, they were the scene of your triumph,
the triumph of our greatest man
coming to his home.
They have made you the symbol
of all that is most precious to them.
Whatever you do
will be their guide and example.
You will not speak to your wife
and I shall not speak to William.
(Clock chimes)
I'm cold!
I'm freezing. I'm frightened!
Emma! Somebody will hear you.
Ssh, Emma!
Dear, Emma, ssh!
(Whispers) Is this better?
Lowered voices? Stolen meetings?
Darkness, suspicion, lies, more lies?
Is this what has become of it?
All that beauty
and light and glory?
Good night, my dearest love.
Good night.
(Sobs)
(Clock chimes)
I, my lords,
have, in different countries,
seen much of the miseries of war.
I am, therefore,
in my innermost soul...
..a man of peace.
Yet I would not, for the sake of any peace,
however fortunate,
consent to sacrifice
one jot of England's honour.
Hitherto
there has been nothing greater known
on the continent
than the faith
the untainted honour
the generous public sympathies
the high diplomatic influence,
the commerce,
the grandeur,
the irresistible power,
the unconquerable valour of the British nation.
(Murmurs of agreement)
He's nervous.
Look. Look at his hand. He's trembling.
It's nerve-racking for any man
to come into the House of Lords for the first time.
It will be more nerve-racking
for the poor man when he goes out.
Why?
There is that Hamilton woman.
peace or war no interest
And, don't look now, his wife.
and as the nation was pleased
with the sincere spirit of peace
It will be a thrilling moment
when he goes into the vestibule.
I can hardly wait
to see which one he goes to first.
Her?
Or her?
Here he comes.
My dear, were you comfortable up there?
Sufficiently, Horatio. Sufficiently.
- Did you hear my speech?
- For the most part.
You have a way of overemphasising,
which is rather embarrassing.
- Oh.
- It was quite interesting.
Lady Keith.
Lady Spencer.
Lady Hamilton.
WOMAN: Why, what's the matter?
GENTLEMAN: Stand back please! Give her air!
- What was that?
- It's Lady Hamilton!
- Stand back please!
Wait, Frances, please.
- Will you fetch a doctor?
- Immediately.
Make way, please
- What's happened?
- I told her not to come.
She's not been feeling well all day.
N SO N W here s the doctor?
But why should she faint?
My dear, it's natural to women of all classes.
Drive on!
(Door opens)
Well?
Frances, how could you drive away like that,
without making the slightest effort to help?
Did you expect me to take her into my carriage,
just because she selects the House of Lords
for her melodrama?
When people have been kind to me and
generous, don't ignore them when they're ill.
- Even in the House of Lords.
- Generous? Ha ha!
It is well known that what success
I may have achieved
has been largely due
to the help I have received from the Hamiltons.
- Why are you so ungrateful?
- Why are you so blind?
Don't you see what that woman is after?
It's the oldest story in the world,
the most sordid and the most contemptible.
Find a public hero and there you'll find,
as sure as fate, a woman parasite.
Don't you realise that all she wants
is to flutter about in your glory,
to use you for her own ambition and conceit?
Oh, I know, she helped you,
she encouraged you.
Why, it was part of her plan
to play upon your vanity.
She's capable of declaring you
the father of her child.
- Frances, control yourself!
- Why not?
Even that accusation stirs some men's vanities.
Silence!
Oh, yes, everyone says
she's a wonderful actress.
She is brilliant, to have hidden
her sweet secret for so long.
The other day, you remarked upon
the new fashions, all these frills and folds.
She invented them and all society followed.
Wonderful to lead society into helping her
through a predicament.
You fool! Don't you realise everything she does
is calculated and cold-blooded?
She faints in the House of Lords,
a perfect place.
Do you suppose she'd have wasted time
in fainting in her own bedroom?
You poor silly man!
Poor and silly?
Yes, that is what I am without her.
I'm a peer of England because of her.
And because of her, I'm Lady Nelson.
Lady Nelson? Ha!
What an honour!
They point after my coach, point up
at my windows, point at me in the streets.
There's a coarse joke about me in the taverns.
A foul song about me on the Limehouse barges.
Lady Nelson!
How funny!
How pitiful!
And how proud I might have been.
I'm sorry, Frances.
Sorry?
Is that all you have to give me?
Yes. That is all.
Very well.
I shall take that as your answer
and now you shall have mine.
I shall go away,
but I shall never drag the name of Nelson
through the divorce court.
As long as I live, I shall be your wife.
Goodbye.
Horatio, call her back.
I implore you, call her back.
You mustn't let her go like this.
I couldn't help hearing what you said, Horatio.
Please, Father,
try to understand.
do, m y boy, do
I know I'm a silly old man, a humble
country parson, and I don't know the world,
except the little people who come to me with
their little troubles,
but even those little people sometimes
have to fight in the depths of their soul,
the same temptations as you,
the great of the world.
And, when they have to choose
between right and wrong,
I give them the same advice
as I give to you now.
Even if it forces all three of us
to live in misery for the rest of our lives?
Even so.
That is something I cannot do, Father.
Then I shall go with her, Horatio.
What s the name off the child?
Horatia Thompson.
Her father's name?
Horatio Thompson.
- Profession?
- Sailor.
Where is he now?
At sea.
(Running footsteps)
- Emily!
- Mother, darling!
- Are you well?
- Yes. How's the baby?
I wish you could see her. She's an angel.
Not at all like a child of two months.
She's like a little princess.
I wish you could see the way she receives
her bottle and then indicates the meal is over.
- You'd adore her.
- What does she weigh now?
9lb 4oz, before her second bottle.
- The news, isn't it splendid?
- What news?
- Haven't you heard?
- I haven't been out
He's done it again. He's beaten the Danes.
It's a glorious victory!
Nelson was in the front line of battle,
ahead of the main fleet.
His commander in chief saw the enemy
outnumbered us by more than two to one.
He sent off a signal to Nelson
telling him to give up and withdraw.
Do you know what Nelson did?
When the signal was pointed out to him,
he put a telescope to his blind eye, said, ''I'm
darned if I can see it'', went on fighting and won.
There, you see, everything comes in handy,
if you know how to use it, even a blind eye!
(Both giggle)
How's William, Mother?
I have some news, too, Emma,
but not so good as yours.
All his treasures, pictures, everything, he's
waited for them to come from Naples for so long.
Now, we know for certain they all went down
in the ship that was lost in the storm.
Oh, poor William. That was his whole life.
Gavin,
that picture, there,
the Van Dyck.
It's crooked, don't you see?
I've told you about it twice already.
- Why don't you put it straight?
- Yes, Sir William.
- Here, sir?
- Yes.
That's good.
Good, Gavin.
It's good to have my pictures
around me once more
and my statues.
But they... They need more light, more room.
We must rearrange them, Gavin.
Gavin...
I'll dine with Miss Hart tonight.
Alone.
At eight o'clock.
Look after yourself.
Talk to Sir William before it's too late.
Or the house itseIf will go to his nephew
instead of to his wife.
His wife?
Why, I have never been his wife, Mother.
Let Charles have the money.
I don't want it and I don't deserve it.
But, my darling, if things stay as they are,
you won't have a penny when he dies.
You'll be poor!
I shall be rich.
I've got my child, his child.
I think that means more
than all the money in the world.
- Can I see Sir William now, Gavin?
- I don't think it's advisable, milady.
He's sleeping, very peacefully.
Gentlemen, the victor of Copenhagen!
ALL: Bravo, Nelson!
Lord Nelson, your decisive defeat of the Danes
has made it possible for the British Government
to negotiate this honourable
and, I must say, unexpected peace with France.
We all believe, with the deepest conviction,
that we shall have, at last, peace.
ALL: Hear, hear!
Lord Spencer,
gentlemen...
..you are celebrating a peace
with Napoleon Bonaparte.
''Peace'' is a very beautiful word,
as long as the impulse of peace is behind it,
but you will never make peace with Napoleon.
He doesn't mean peace, today.
He just wants to gain a little time...
..to rearm himseIf at sea
and make new alliances with Italy and Spain,
all to one purpose.
To destroy our empire!
Years ago, I said the same thing at Naples.
I begged them, entreated them, not to give way,
but they wouldn't listen to me and paid the price.
That was a little kingdom,
miles away in the Mediterranean.
But now it is England, our own land.
Napoleon can never be master of the world
until he has smashed us up
and, believe me, gentlemen,
he means to be master of the world!
You cannot make peace with dictators.
You have to destroy them, wipe them out!
Gentlemen, I implore you,
speak to the Prime Minister before it is too late!
Do not ratify this peace!
We, er, appreciate all you say.
Well, thank you, gentlemen.
I feIt it my duty to tell you of these things.
I'm not a statesman, of course.
I'm no diplomat.
I must leave it in your hands.
- Gentlemen.
- Good day, Lord Nelson.
(Heated discussion)
Going to your, er, home in Norfolk, Nelson?
I don't... I don't think so.
My wife tells me
she saw Lady Nelson at Bath, recently.
Yes. She's very well.
She gives her time to social work.
Ah. And er...shall you go to Venice?
Er... Why Venice?
Oh, something I heard the other day.
A little party to some musical festival,
Lady Hamilton and a few English friends.
Where did you hear this?
It was that little musical chap,
who came over to Covent Garden to conduct.
I heard him say something about
Lady Hamilton going back with him
Oh, well...
I daresay I've got it all mixed up.
Well, it's good to see you home again.
Why, your lordship!
Good afternoon, Mrs Cadogan.
Sit down, please.
Everything is in such a mess.
Why this sudden move
from Piccadilly to Nero's Hotel?
Well, you see, everything was so dull and dismal
since William died.
Emma couldn't stand it any longer.
see
Where is she now?
She went out quite early.
With the little foreign musical gentleman.
They're... They're driving in the park.
Oh.
May wat?
Yes please.
Look at the flowers. Aren't they pretty?
So nice for a young widow.
- Yes.
EMMA: Horatio
I'm so sorry. Have you been here long?
Oh, no.
Emma, dear. I just came in by chance.
Your mother has been telling me
why you moved from Piccadilly.
I think you're quite right.
It was so very gloomy there.
I haven't seen a great deal of you
since I've been back, Emma.
- You know what it's like. There's so much to do.
- How is the child?
I've been meaning every day this week
to go and see her.
But it's so difficult. It takes almost a whole day.
Emma, let us drive out
and see her this afternoon.
Oh, yes.
Lord Nelson, whom the whole of London knows,
calling on little Horatia Thompson.
whose father no-one has as yet seen.
My dear, what a titbit
for Lady Spencer's next dinner party.
(Knocking)
Come in.
Thank you.
My dear, I know you're very busy
and I don't want to intrude upon your affairs,
but there are things that I don't quite understand
since I came back
and to be honest I don't quite like
What things do you mean?
Three times this week I've tried to see you
and each time you've had appointments
with people whom I don't know.
We had no secrets at one time.
Even in our letters.
You surely do not ask to see all my letters.
Certainly I do not ask to see them, my dear.
If you want to hide them from me.
You're jealous!
Why do you make fun of me?
Fun? I've never been so happy in all my life.
You're splendid when you're jealous.
You must promise me to be jealous always,
please.
We were talking about some letters, weren't we?
Horatio, if there are certain letters I would
sooner keep to myself, won't you trust me?
What are those letters?
Very well.
Read them.
(She plays)
I'm sorry.
Forgive me.
- I'll see you later.
-No, Horatio, don't go.
You know what will happen
if you leave them unopened.
We shall never quite understand each other
again.
They're quite short, and to the point.
Bills, bills, and more bills.
Threats, summonses and lawsuits.
I'm up to my neck in them - drowned in them.
Why do you think I left Piccadilly?
My dear, they threw me out.
And why do you think
I haven't seen our child for two weeks?
Because I owe Mrs Gibson
15 guineas for the rent.
Do you think I like going out
with that little man from Venice?
I hate the sight of him
But I have to do it because he's promised me
a contract at his opera house.
Yes, I'm going back to work.
I've done it before and I can do it again.
I don't really mind.
You see, Horatio,
William didn't leave me a farthing.
- Why wasn't I told?
- Why should you be told?
These are my troubles, not yours.
I've never asked anyone for money
and I never shall.
Indeed?
Then are you out of your senses?
Now, you listen to me, and don't answer back!
How dare you keep those bills from me.
Aren't your worries my worries?
Everything I have is yours.
Everything!
You're going to have a home of your own.
And there is going to be no sorrow
and no trouble ever again.
Emma.
Dear Emma.
Mm, that's the best drop of rum I've tasted
since the old days.
We don't get much excuse to open a bottle
lately. You should come oftener.
It warms the cockles of your heart. (Laughs)
Captain Hardy, how nice to see you again.
Why didn't you tell us you were coming?
Well, to tell you the truth, I just happened to be
passing and thought I'd come and see you.
Will you stay to luncheon?
Oh, thank you, my lady.
Mother, darling, tell the coachman we leave
at two. I want the child here before dark.
Yes, dear, I'll tell him.
He's in the garden. You can see his work of art
in the summerhouse.
I don't want to disturb him, my lady.
I know he likes his peace and quiet.
Just because he won't see St Vincent and Keith
when they write him pompous letters?
Oh, no, Hardy, you're different.
You're an old friend. Come along.
No, to tell you the truth, Lady Hamilton,
I didn't come to see him.
I came to see you.
Me?
Yes.
There's no chance of our being overheard,
is there?
No, but what is the mystery?
Well, do you ever read the newspapers
down here?
Not unless we can help it.
We're not particularly interested
in the court news.
Nor the gossip, the scandal.
You may have missed what happened.
Bonaparte's made himseIf Emperor of France.
Yes, we saw that.
What is his next move?
His next move will be the invasion of England.
Oh, ridiculous!
So it may sound, my lady.
That's what we all thought when we first heard it.
But it's true. This peace was no good.
It'll break any day now.
This self-styled Emperor
has made an alliance with Spain.
He's raked together a new fleet
from goodness knows where.
And he's building transports and barges
as fast as he can turn them out.
From Boulogne to Brest,
every single Channel port is chock-full of them.
He's got a whole army behind him
waiting to embark.
A few weeks from now,
all he'll need is a fair wind.
And all you'll need... will be Nelson.
Yes, that's it, my lady.
- Is that all?
- That's all, my lady.
You see...
Well...
Nelson's the only man who can save us.
Now, listen to me, Hardy,
I have helped the Navy whenever I could,
but not this time, Hardy, not this time.
Let them find some other man to take command.
Keith or Parker or St Vincent himself. Not him!
Don't they understand, Hardy?
He's given so much.
His arm, his sight, his health.
He needs rest and he must have it.
For the first time in his life
he's found peace of mind and happiness.
And I'm going to see that he keeps it.
If they want me to use my influence, I will.
All my influence to persuade him
that this new war is none of his business!
That's...
all I have to say.
Of course, there's nothing to prevent you from
talking it over with him personally at luncheon.
Will you stay?
No, thank you, my lady.
I think perhaps l'd better get back.
Goodbye, Hardy.
(Carriage withdraws)
Oh, come along. I thought you were dressing.
What have you been doing?
We'll never get there if you don't look sharp.
Besides, I'm hungry.
Starving.
I don't think we'll go today, Horatio.
It will save two trips if we pick her up tomorrow,
after you've been to the Admiralty.
The Admiralty?
Hardy has been here. They sent him.
They need you, dear, badly.
This war is coming, as you always said it would.
And there's no-one else.
Did you tell Hardy I would go?
Yes.
It's a matter of course, dear, isn't it?
It'll be freezing tonight on the high roads
over the downs.
Yes,
I think I'll take the little rug I use in my study.
- Oh, yes, I know, I'll get it.
- I'll get it, Mother.
(Carriage withdraws)
He thought he wouldn't need the rug.
He'll never come back, Mother.
? Cheer up, my lads,'tis to glory we steer
? To add something new to this wonderful year
? To honour we call you as free men not slaves
? For who are so free as the sons of the waves?
? Hearts of oak are our ships
? Jolly tars are our men
? We always are ready
? Steady, boys, steady
? We'll fight and we'll conquer again and again
Mr Pasco,
I will now amuse the fleet with a signal.
I wish to say to the fleet...
..''England confides
that every man will do his duty.''
Be quick. I've one more to follow for close action.
If you will permit me to substitute
''expects'' for ''confides'',
it will be sooner completed.
That will do. Make it directly.
Those Frenchmen
have sharpshooters up in the rigging, sir.
I know. Why do you tell me?
Do you think it's wise to wear all those
decorations? They make a nice target.
- I won them in battle, didn't l?
- Yes, sir, but...
Then I shall wear them in battle.
England...
Expects...
That...
Every...
Man...
Will...
Do...
His...
Duty.
? Come cheer up, my lads,'tis to glory we sail
? To add something new to this wonderful year
? To honour we call you as free men not slaves
? For who are so free as the sons of the waves?
? Hearts of oak are our ships
? Jolly tars are our men
? We always are ready
? Steady, boys, steady
? We'll fight and we'll conquer...
We'll be on them in half an hour, sir.
Mon capitaine,
la flotte enemie est nord-ouest et bâbord.
Mon amiral,
Prèparez pour l'attaque.
(Cannonfire)
- They're getting pretty close now, sir.
-Not yet.
(Explosions)
Starboard broadside fire as you bear.
(Repeats order)
(Man shouts)
(Cannonfire continues)
Voilà l'Amiral!
Sir!
They've... done for me, at last.
You're not badly hurt, are you, sir?
My backbone... shot through.
(Explosions)
HARDY: I'll carry you to Dr Beattie.
- You stay on deck. Come to me when you can.
Cover my face... these decorations.
No time for the men to see me like this.
(Explosions continue)
Mr Beattie...
... I have no feeling... below my breast.
No lower.
I know what that means, Mr Beattie.
My spine is broken.
My lord...unhappily for our country,
nothing...can be done for you.
Poor Emma.
What will become of her?
(Shouting from above deck)
Was that cheering?
They're cheering in all our ships, my lord.
The French line has broken.
Why doesn't Hardy come?
- He must be killed.
- He's on deck, sir. He can't leave.
(Shouting)
(Moans)
(Gasps)
They're cheering again.
The French flagship has surrendered, sir.
(Croakily ) Good.
Why don't they bring Hardy to me?
He sends a message, sir.
We're against the Redoubtable.
When we have beaten her, he will come.
(Nelson gasps)
- How goes it, Hardy?
- Fourteen of them are ours, sir.
Not enough.
Twenty. Twenty.
(Gasps) Don't throw me overboard, Hardy.
No, sir.
You know what to do.
Let my dear Lady Hamilton have my hair...
..and all things belonging to me.
You mustn't die, sir. You mustn't die!
(Softly ) It's all over now, Hardy.
All over now.
(Whispers)
Sir!
Sir! It's eighteen now sir
Eighteen - a great victory.
Thank God.
I have done my duty.
Kiss me...Hardy.
I am the resurrection and the life,
sayeth the Lord.
He that believeth in me
though he were dead, yet shall he live;
And whosoever liveth and believeth in me
shall never die.
(Continues sermon)
It's all right, Anna, I'll draw them myself.
Thank you.
My lady.
- Do you come from Portsmouth, Hardy?
-No, Spithead, Lady Hamilton.
I came on the St George, she's our fastest ship.
Captain Blackwood went ahead to London
with the news.
What is the news, Hardy?
It was a great victory.
It was the greatest we've ever known.
That's wonderful.
It was nine days ago...
we engaged them off Cape Trafalgar
the combined fleets of France and Spain
They've been destroyed
The oceans are free once more
and England is safe from invasion
The first cannon was fired a little after twelve
Within one hour five French
ships-of-the-line had struck their flags
His plan was magnificent
He swung our fleet from line of battle
into two spearheads,
that broke the enemy line
into three separate parts.
Then...
about one-thirty
I was walking with him on the upper deck
The fighting was at its height
The French flagship the Redoubtable
came through the smoke
and we fought alongside one another
he was so
confident.
We'd just...turned to go...back to the...
(Sobs)
By sunset
everything was over
But
he he lived to know
he'd won England's greatest victory
His His last thoughts were with you my lady
That you should be cared for
(Sobs softly )
(Door slams)
- And then?
- Then what?
What happened after?
There is no then.
There is no after.