[music playing]
[horns sounding]
NARRATOR: In the
pleasant summer of 1914,
the American community
was [inaudible],
was finding it
easier and happier
than ever before in its history.
[trolley stopping]
A Washington cream pie.
Washington cream pie?
You like it too, [inaudible]?
NARRATOR: In America'sbrave little world of 1914,
a self-contained and contented
people would look back
with satisfaction
on nearly a century
and a half of unparalleledprogress and prosperity.
American industry
lead the world,
and was rapidly
increasing its lead.
To contribute to and share inthe wealth of a growing nation,
immigrants from every
part of the world
were still flocking
to US shores,
bringing up their childrenin the American community as
new first generation Americans.
[children chattering]
[bell ringing]
Most communities
of any size in 1914
could boast of their
own daily newspaper,
whose editor championed
their causes,
helped fight their battles.
But Americans of 1914 werelittle interested in news
outside their own communityand their own nation.
The country was still debatingafter two years the merits
of the New Freedom,slogan of Woodrow Wilson,
the first Democrat
to occupy the White
House since Grover Cleveland.
The Panama Canal, in whichthe whole nation took pride,
was scheduled finally to
be opened in mid August.
And the man most responsiblefor the canal, ex-president
Theodore Roosevelt, was
still a powerful figure
on the US political scene.
The regular Army of
the United States
totaled just under 100,000men in the summer of 1914,
and many a US citizen feltthat even this number was
excessive for a force
that had little to do
but chase Mexican bandits.
Heavier than aircraft
were undergoing tests
by a few young andfar-sighted army officers,
who hoped eventually to
put the new invention to
some useful military purpose.
Fast achieving popularitywas the Hesitation
Canter, a startling newoutgrowth of the Turkey trot.
In 1914, young
citizens of America
were looking forward with highhope for the future of a land
which was still a new world.
It was a settled
and ordered world,
in which youth,
keen and confident,
saw limitless opportunity.
There were new standards andnew ideals, new entertain
and new pleasures.
Well, just as the
train came to a trestle,
she got to the window
and jumped out.
Well?
Well, that's the way it
ended until next week.
Isn't that just like them?
NARRATOR: An earnest people,living in a land grown
powerful and great, wereonly beginning to realize how
truly great their nation was.
[train whistle]
Until the arrival of thepaper train on the morning
of June 1914, Europe
and Europe's troubles
seemed very far away.
Say, Harry, is an Archduke likea prince, or is he like a king?
Search me.
[train whistle]
[bells]
NARRATOR: In the days
that quickly followed
the first declaration ofwar, as country after country
mobilized and marched, the
news that mattered most
was the news of Europe andits spreading battle fronts.
It was America's foreign-bornwho first felt the impact
of the war in Europe.
And they tried as best
they could to explain
it to their American friends.
To them, war was a
sad, familiar Old
World story, the age-old uponthe lands from which they came.
Anna, [inaudible], look.
Right here in the paper.
[galloping]
[door bell]
A registered letter
for you, Mrs. Kovacs.
Looks like something
from the old country.
You can sign for it.
It'd be odd to sign for this.
You don't want me to bringit back again, do you?
Sign right here.
Thank you.
Goodbye.
[train whistle]
Hello, Anna.
What are you doing here?
Joe, the postman
brought it this morning.
What does it say, Joe?
It's for the army.
We'll talk it over
when we get home, Mama.
[buoyant music]
Any from Austria?
I don't know
where they're from,
the "Pathe Weekly" is on now.
[music playing]
[non-english speech]
You got Army papers
too, huh, John?
Yeah, come today.
What's your take?
Not for me.
That's Old Country business.
I'm staying in America
with the wife and kids.
What you going to do?
If you don't go now, you'llnever get back to Old Country.
I go Monday, maybe.
Joe.
Now, Mama, in times
like this, a man's got
to do what he thinks is right.
[speaking german]
When do you go, Joe?
I take the train for
New York this afternoon.
Did you ask them
about the money?
Well, Anna, they said
it's hard to get money
through from the
Old Country now.
What are we going to live on?
Oh, Papa.
I'm sorry.
Come, we go.
NARRATOR: With the invasionof neutral Belgium,
Americans awoke to the fulland terrible implications
of a modern war.
A taxi cab army,
rushed from Paris,
brought the miracle
of the Marne.
Britain's contemptibles,as the Kaiser called them,
were desperately holding
the Flanders' front.
American military men knewthat Germany had devoted all
her energies for 20 years tobuilding up the greatest war
machine the world had everseen, armies that were now
systematically destroyingin their advance
the towns, the cities,
and the homes of
a simple, peace-loving people.
And there were signs in
the American community
that the nation was aroused.
Razor all right, Congressman?
Mm-mm.
John, I'm not
going to find it so
easy to be neutral in thought.
JOHN: Mm-mm.
NARRATOR: Already,
the war in Europe
was finding its way into theeveryday lives of Americans.
Americans of every age.
H2O.
Twice, please Anna.
Say, I'm sorry to hear thatyou're quitting school.
Do you have to?
What else can I do?
I've got to help Mother.
I don't understand
Pop doing what he did.
Well, I suppose you can't blameanybody for being patriotic.
But he didn't have
to go over there.
It wasn't his war.
The war will be over ina couple of months anyway.
That's what my
father says, and he
used to be in the German army.
I suppose he thinks theGermans are going to win.
They win every day, don't they?
If your old man
likes Germany so much,
he'd better go back there.
That goes for you go too.
Never mind him, Freddy.
Don't let that
guy get your goat.
The army advanced
along the whole front
again today, in some placesnearly five kilometers.
You're not eating
much tonight, Fred.
What's the matter?
Nothing Mama, I'm
just not hungry.
Anna Kovacs has
had to quit school.
Her father's been called
by the Austrian army,
and now she has to work.
So?
Dad, it's getting
so that all of you
and everybody else talk aboutis this war all the time.
Today, I said that you hadbeen in the German army,
and that you thought theGermans would win in two months.
I didn't mean anything.
It almost started a
free-for-all, Father.
That's too bad, Frederick.
Perhaps I should
be more careful.
It is very wrong for any ofus to get personally agitated
about the wars of far away.
We are in American.
President Wilson said,
this is a war with which
we have nothing to do.
That is how we all
must try to feel.
NARRATOR: Under the personalcommand of Kaiser Wilhelm II,
the armies of imperialGermany seemed invincible
in the summer of 1914.
And Americans began to realizethat belief in a just cause
was not enough against
superior manpower
and superior armaments.
The bravery of the Belgians,fighting on To hold the channel
ports, further heightenedAmerica's desire
to help these stricken people.
Most Americans feel that
the invasion of Belgium
was the most barbarous
act ever committed
by a civilized nation.
[applause]
We are not here to
discuss the rights
and wrongs of the European war.
We are here to help its innocentvictims, little children,
helpless and starving.
The Committee for the Reliefof Belgium under the able
chairmanship of Herbert Hoover,can feed a Belgian child
for a month on a $5 bill.
It is up to us to see thathe gets those $5 bills.
Yes, and $10s, and
$20s, and $50s.
NARRATOR: A generous
people had assumed
its first responsibility
of the war,
with the help of a young miningengineer named Herbert Hoover.
Within three months, he
had organized a fleet
of 35 vessels, carrying
more than a million
worth of food a week to Belgium.
As the war entered
its first winter,
American contributions werekeeping alive 10 million
homeless, starving
people, helpless wards
of the one nation of the
world still able to feed
and care for them.
Aren't these
Professor Carter's?
Why, of course they are.
Do you suppose he'sreally bought a new suit?
We can't send these old
things to the Belgians
with St. Luke's name on them.
And those poor Belgian women.
--[sighing] I can't
bear to think of them.
Well, I just can't
understand it.
Why, Dora.
We all know German people.
Some of us have German friends.
Look at the Bensingers.
They're as nice as
anybody could be.
NARRATOR: --with Europe's war.
America was a neutralnation, but neutral nations
on the high seas were beingopenly and flagrantly violated
by Germany.
What a way for a civilizednation to fight a war.
Why shouldn't they
sink English ships?
So why don't the
submarines give
warning, so the crews
will have a chance
to get into life boats.
The Germans have got to sinkships if they're carrying
munitions for the Allies.
And suppose they have
Americans on them?
They shouldn't be there.
The German government
has warned them.
[audio out] be there.
Huh.
Don't make me--
NARRATOR: But far more
fateful [audio out]
questions of international lawwas the submarines' steadily
mounting toll of human lives.
[music playing]
Men like Theodore
Roosevelt were now
demanding forceful
action to uphold
the nation's traditional
freedom of the seas.
But few Americans wouldbelieve that their rights
were seriously threatened.
[typing]
Clarence.
And they sunk the "Lusitania."
What?
Tell circulation we
have an extra coming on.
How many Americans aboard?
228.
96-point banner.
Play up the American angle.
The Germans had run a warningto "Lusitania" passengers.
What do you mean?
An ad in "The New York Times."
In "The Times?"
Have you got a copy?
I didn't think they'd
dare to sink her.
The warning of
the German embassy
had attracted little notice.
It was unthinkable that Germanywould sink the "Lusitania."
Her sailing had been set
for a Saturday for noon.
On her passenger list were someof the proudest names of two
continents, for the
"Lusitania" was queen
of the great [inaudible] fleet.
It was to be a gay
and festive voyage.
Nearly 2,000 souls were aboard.
1,200 never reached shore.
No single disaster
in half a century
had stirred Americanemotions more profoundly.
If Wilson stands for this,he'll stand for anything.
Stand for what?
Stand for murder.
Murder of 114 Americans.
[inaudible].
MAN: An American
citizen has the right
to travel anywhere he wants to.
We oughta lick the Kaisernow and have it over with.
You're gonna have a
hard time [audio out].
They don't care how many
Americans get killed.
And what do they say
about the "Lusitania."
Well, in Montana, they thinkif a man goes out in the street
when there's shooting
going on, it's
his own fault if he gets hit.
[band playing]
[church bells]
NARRATOR: Anger and indignation,deep and mounting, swept
every community in the land.
Throughout the nation on
the following Sabbath,
there were memorial
services for the men,
the women, and the childrenwho were the "Lusitania's"
martyred dead.
[galloping]
Well, boys, what's
on your mind?
We came to find out
what you're going
to do about the "Lusitania."
To tell the truth, I hadn'tthought of doing anything.
John, you're our Congressman.
You know how they're feeling.
Don't you think you oughtto go talk with President
Wilson about this thing?
Well, now boys, you don'twalk in on the President
just that way.
He's already said
he would Germany
to strict accountability.
John, we've been hearingabout strict accountability
for a long time.
It seems to mean that
when a German U-boat
kills some more Americans,the President just
sends another note.
What do you want to do?
You ought to go to Wilson,and tell him he's got to act,
and act quick.
All right.
I can go to Wilson.
Are you boys willing
to go to war?
That's not the point John,and you know it isn't.
The point is you
want to do something,
but you don't want to do theonly thing the Germans would
understand, war.
this country isn't
ready to fight a war,
even if it wanted to.
Just suppose I do
go to the President?
Suppose he says, all right, ifyou want a war, you'll get it.
Do you want your boy
to go to war, Ed?
Will you fight?
I know how you feel.
I feel the same way.
But it's war or nothing.
And I still think it
ought to be nothing.
NARRATOR:US opinion was
still deeply divided.
To demands for action,
Woodrow Wilton answered,
there is such a
thing as a nation
being too proud to fight.
It was a bitterly
disputed phrase.
But other US citizens
were going to war.
Across the border, thousands ofyou Americans of military age
were joining famed Canadianregiments-- the Black Watch
and Princess Pats-- to fightalongside Canadians in a cause
they believed to be just.
[patriotic music]
Bought and sent overseasby the contributions of US
communities, driven by Americanswho paid their own expenses,
nearly 100 ambulances
by the end of 1915
were on the
battlefields of France.
[plane engine]
Bearing the name of a Frenchsoldier who had helped America
to win her independence,
the Lafayette Escadrille
was an elite corps
of US volunteers.
[engine]
[explosion]
In the American community,emotion for the Allied cause
was running high.
And in a town as
important as this,
with the mainline railroad, thereservoir, the college and all,
they'd be sure to
have at least one spy.
Honestly, Dora.
Do you really believe ElizabethBensinger's husband is a spy?
Where there's
smoke, there's fire.
Hello, everybody.
WOMEN: Hello.
Hello.
Hello, Mrs. Averill.
Hello, Elizabeth.
How are you?
I'm fine.
Elizabeth?
Yes?
May I speak to you and
Hilda a moment please?
Why, certainly.
Hilda?
I thought I ought to tellyou that since we are working
on bandages for
the Allies, we all
feel that perhaps you andHilda could make yourselves
more useful somewhere else.
I'm not quite sure that Iunderstand what you mean, Dora.
With feeling as it is aboutthe Germans, I'm very sorry.
But I'm sure you will avoidunpleasantness if you go.
Come, Hilda.
[patriotic music]
NARRATOR: In every
US community by 1915,
the lines were
slowly being drawn
between peace at any priceand intervention in the war.
[crowd chattering]
When I hear these
fools shouting
about being too proud tofight, it makes my blood boil.
Don't they know that
the Allies are fighting
to save our own civilization?
I'm glad you feel
that way, Dad.
Because I want to jointhe Lafayette Escadrille.
What?
I want to join the LafayetteEscadrille and go to France.
Well, Walter, that's
a fine sentiment.
But I'm afraid it
isn't very practical.
You're hardly old enough
for a thing like that.
Of course I am, Dad.
They'll take you at 18.
But Walter, what
about your college?
Dad, how can I keep
my mind on studies
with a war going on
that's going to affect
the whole future of the world?
You won't much voice in thefuture of the world, Walter,
if you go over there
and don't come back.
I'll have to take
a chance on that.
A lot of other people have.
[patriotic music]
Why did you have totalk to me first, Walter?
Well, it--
Because my father's German?
Walter, I love my father.
I'd do anything in theworld rather than hurt him,
or let anybody hurt him.
I know he wants the Germansto win the war, but I don't.
What do you want, Hilda?
I want you to go toFrance, if you want to go.
I'd be proud of you, Walter.
[train bells]
So long, boy.
Take care of yourself.
You've been great, Dad.
I know how you feel about it.
That's all right, Son.
Goodbye, Mom.
I'll write you every week.
Don't you worry.
Hilda.
You
[train bells]
[dramatic music]
[explosion]
NARRATOR: 600,000causalities at [inaudible].
A million dead and
wounded on the Sommes.
And on the minds of men, therelentless pressure of war,
dragging on into a third summer.
[gunfire]
At Jutland, in the
summer of 1916,
the British Navy to
cover in the greatest
sea battle of all time.
[patriotic music]
And for the first
time, Americans
realized how great
was their dependence
on the might of the Royal Navy.
The whole thing boils
down to this, John.
If we had a big army navy,we wouldn't have to worry
about getting into war.
I'm afraid there are someof my fellow congressmen
who will agree with, Jack.
Well, they're wrong.
And if congressmen won't dosomething about preparedness,
we'll have to do it ourselves.
Say, Dan, I want you to putsomething in your paper for me.
What about?
You know PlattsburghTraining Camp Teddy Roosevelt
and General Woodruff started?
I'm going to have one here.
What for?
There's a war
going on in Europe.
You know as well as I do that ifFrance and England are licked,
we're next.
You've been a soldier
too long, Jack.
Nobody's coming over
here to fight us.
Maybe not.
But suppose we have to goover there to fight them?
You know that's
not going to happen.
[trumpets]
NARRATOR: By 1916, WoodrowWilton now a candidate
for reelection, could no longerignore the growing demand
for national defense, andhe marched at the head
of a Preparedness Parade.
Republican candidate was SupremeCourt Justice Charles Evans
Hughes, advocate of a strong andforthright US foreign policy.
[chattering and cheering]
That is the real
issue, the only
real issue in this campaign.
The President has
kept us out of war.
[applause]
He has sent notes to thewarring nations of Europe.
That's all he has
done, is send notes.
Yes, the President
has sent notes.
But he has not sent one singleAmerican boy to his death
on the battlefields.
[applause]
[parade music]
11:10 PM.
Madison, Wisconsin.
Charles Evans Hughes has tiedWisconsin by large plurality.
[cheering]
11:15 PM.
The Associated Press
reports that with five
states still
unreported, Hughes is
leading Wilson by a now margin.
[cheering]
[bell ringing]
He's to a real President
of the United States,
Charles Evans Hughes. [SINGING]Here's to Charlie Hughes,
drink down, drink down.
Here's to Charlie Hughes,drink her down, drink her down.
Here's to Charlie Hughes, he'sin Woodrow Wilson's shoes.
Drink her down, drink her down,drink her down, down, down.
NARRATOR: With the campaignslogan "Kept Us Out of War,"
Woodrow Wilton was re-elected.
[cheering]
[explosions]
The war in Europe had longsince become a merciless process
of attrition.
To break the stalemate, Britainhad introduced the tank.
Germany was using liquid fire.
The war went on,
into another winter,
bringing death to some
5,000 men each day.
[action music]
[zooming]
War had already touched theAmerican community in many ways
by the summer of 1916.
[ragtime music]
The Lafayette Escadrilleis all Americans, isn't it?
Yes, sir.
Now, what would happen
to you if the United
States should go into the war.
Well, I understand
we'll be commissioned
in the US Army flying corps.
Hello, Hal.
Hello, Mr. Meredith.
It's good to see you.
It's good to see you back againall in one piece, isn't it?
Sure is.
Certainly is.
[ragtime music]
Hiya, Hal.
Hello, Betsy.
How are you?
Swell.
Boy, I guess the
last thing you ever
thought when you graduatedwas that you'd be
an aviator in the French army.
Say how old do you have
to be to go to France?
[ragtime music]
Hello, Anna.
How's the party?
All right.
What's the trouble, Anna?
Mother got a
cablegram this morning.
My father was killed.
Anna.
Do you think WalterAverill will be able to get
back to America on his leave?
I don't know.
He's a sub-lieutenant
now, and they
may not be able to spare him.
[trumpeting]
Colonel.
Hut.
[inaudible]
Left shoulder.
Right shoulder.
[inaudible]
Quiet in the rank.
You men are at attention.
And while I'm on thesubject, you might as well
get it through your heads
right now but you're
not out here for a vacation.
You're here to learn
to do a job, the job
of defending your country.
Maybe it won't be very longbefore you have to do that job,
and do it right.
[inaudible]
Dismissed.
Hello, Dad.
Hello, Ralph.
Hello, Mom.
Why, Ralph, you must
be tired to death.
No, I'm fine.
This is fun.
Do they give you plenty to eat?
Sure.
All I can hold.
Don't worry, Mom.
Oh, Ralph, I can't help it.
I hate to see you
in that uniform.
I hate it all.
Aw, Mom.
Dad, you like it, don't you?
You look fine, Ralph.
Just fine.
[cannon]
[trumpeting]
In Europe on a dozen
separate battle fronts
by the winter of 1916,
4 million men had met
death in ways new and dreadful.
And Germany had introducedthe most terrible
of all the First World War's newweapons-- poison gas, chlorine
and [inaudible] to choke
the lungs and throat,
mustard to burn
the eyes and skin.
[dramatic music]
The use of poison gas seemedhorrible and barbarous
than any other single actionof the German high command.
And Americans were fast
reaching a decision.
[cheering]
And has also received
the [inaudible]
for bravery in action.
Can you imagine that
guy, Hal Fisher?
With his name all
over the paper?
Boy, I guess I was born
just a little too late.
Don't worry.
We're going to get
our chance yet.
Did I tell you I'm gettinginto the Naval Reserve?
Naval Reserve.
You oughta be in
the National Guard.
I'll bet we go over, thefirst week, we're in the war.
[patriotic music]
[cheering]
Anna, I think I'm going tosign up in the Marine Corps.
Well, I want to do something.
We're going to be in this war.
Fred, what will
your father say?
I don't know, but
I'm going to do it.
[cheering]
NARRATOR: By now, pacifist songswere finding a little favor.
[music playing]
SINGER: Hello, my dear.
I heard a mother murmur
through her tears.
I didn't raise my
boy to be a soldier.
I brought him up to
be my pride and joy.
Waiter.
What's the trouble, sir?
How much is this?
Why can't you make up
your mind whether you're
Germans or Americans?
Come on, let's get out of here.
SINGER: It's time to put
the sword and gun away.
There'd be no war today ifmothers all would say I didn't
raise my boy to be a soldier.
[applause]
[dramatic music]
[explosion]
NARRATOR: Fires and explosionsof mysterious origin
had plagued the nation'sindustrial regions for two
years, and Americans
were now beginning
to realize that these disasterswere not all accidents.
Thank you.
How do you, sir?
How do you do,
Professor Bensinger?
Am I disturbing you?
Not at all.
Is there something
I can do for you?
If you could give
me a few minutes.
Certainly.
[inaudible] the German embassy.
Yes?
Professor Bensinger,
it is imperative
we stop the shipment
of American munitions
to France and England.
As a German who is a respectedmember of this community,
your influence can
help the fatherland.
Herr [inaudible], my
home is now in America.
I have a wife and twochildren who are Americans.
If only for their sake,
I cannot take sides.
The war in Europe
is a terrible thing.
Actually, I wish I
could do something
to help the fatherland.
But I must be clear
to you, I cannot.
You know I must report
your answer to Germany,
Professor Bensinger?
NARRATOR: Many Americanswere beginning to suspect
that the German ambassador,
Johann von Bernstroff
was directing planned sabotageon a nationwide scale.
[explosion]
An explosion of munitions onBlack Tom Island, New Jersey
have rocked an area of 70 miles.
Another explosion at
Kingsland, New Jersey
destroyed in a few minutesmillions of dollars
worth of shells and ammunition.
Time and time again came
evidence and sabeteurs,
well-organized
and financed, were
attempting the
systematic destruction
of US munition plants.
The violence of war hadtouched the nation's shores.
And America's traditional
sense of security
was shaken to the core.
By 1917, Americans were
facing the inevitable.
I think most Americans feelabout the way I do, John.
You know I've never
believed the propaganda.
I've never been frightenedby spies, and I've hated war.
But the time has
come when we've got
to fight for the decent,civilized things in life.
It's just that I hate to thinkthat I'll ever have to vote
to put this country into war.
NARRATOR: More and more, the warin Europe coming into the homes
of the American community.
Mind the office for
awhile, will you, Eddie?
I've gotta deliver a
message across town.
Can't I deliver it for you?
I think I'd better
deliver this one myself.
[typing]
Gee, Walter Averill.
We'll run this one, George.
[choral music]
The death of Walter Averillseems to have brought
the war in Europe very close.
Perhaps this war is
no concern of ours.
Perhaps we should be in it.
There are sincere thinkingmen and women on both sides.
And we are under terrifyingpressure on this question.
From England and
France and Germany
come all kinds of reports.
Most of them are half truths.
Some of them are lies.
But Walter Averill didn'tgo to France for lies.
He didn't go because
of the lurid tales
about the Hun and [inaudible].
I think Walter
believed in his heart
the same as I believe
in mine that there is
a basic democratic principleand a primitive might
makes right instinct.
And today, these
two are fighting
to see which will survive.
I think that's the fight forwhich young Walter Averill was
willing to give up his life.
NARRATOR: Like an openchallenge to the United States
in the first weeks of 1917 cameGermany's declaration that she
was resuming
unrestricted warfare
against the vessels
of all nations,
belligerent and neutral.
Now the German
government tells us
that she will let us
send just one ship
a week across the Atlantic.
We are told when it must leave,when it must arrive, and where.
We are told to
paint stripes on it.
That it must fly a flag
of red and white checks
like a farmer's table cloth.
I think I can truthfully saythat no man in this house
has advocated caution
more consistently,
has more consistently
championed the cause
of neutrality and peace.
Now, it seems that the effortsof all of us may be in vain.
If they are to be in
vain, then I say this.
Let us thank God that
we are on the side
of justice and the right.
NARRATOR: [inaudible] came USAmbassador James W. Gerard,
and his disturbing rumorsthat Germans were attempting
to promote an attack
through Mexico
against the United States.
[band music]
The nation was tense
with expectation.
But on the cold March
day of Woodrow Wilson's
second inaugural, the
nation's men of state,
as well as all the solemnthousands who crowded
into Washington, feltthat they were witnessing
the close of one era
in American history,
the beginning of another.
[band playing]
By March, the US flag
had been all but driven
from the Atlantic
by German submarine.
For America, freedom of theseas had ceased to exist.
As the first important
act of his second term,
Woodrow Wilson signed
an executive order
which armed all US merchantships with naval guns.
It was another compromise,called by Woodrow
Wilson armed neutrality.
Congressman [inaudible]?
Good evening.
This is Western Union.
I have a telegram for
you from Washington
signed Carter, Sergeant at arms.
The message reads, three
more American ships,
having been torpedoed,
the President
has advanced the date of aspecial session of Congress
through April 2.
That's signed Carter,
Sergeant at Arms.
NARRATOR: Armed
neutrality had failed.
The American peoplelooked to the White House.
For three years, Woodrow Wiltonhad compromised with Germany.
And each new compromisehad brought new indignity.
Now, his people wanted war.
On the evening of April2, 1917, the entire nation
awaited Woodrow
Wilson's fateful answer.
[trumpets]
The answer came.
Calling upon the nationto mobilize its resources
and its manpower, WoodrowWilton declared that America had
no quarrel with
the German people,
sought no dominion,
and no conquest.
But the Imperial
German government
had subjected the rights andthe ideals of the United States
to such violation as no nationof free men could endure.
It's a great speech so far.
Here's the end of it now.
[typing]
For democracy, for
the right of those
who submit to authority to havea voice in their government.
For the rights andliberties of small nations.
For a universal dominionof right by such a concert
of free peoples as
shall bring peace
and safety to all nations,and make the world
itself at last free.
To such a task, we can dedicateour lives and our fortune
with the pride of those whoknow that the day has come when
America is privileged to spendher blood for the principles
which gave her
birth, and happiness,
and the peace which
she has treasured.
God helping her,
she can do no other.
OK, George.
Three column box
on the front page.
Run it over.
Head it "The President's WarMessage," with a main head,
"Wilson Calls For War."
[bells]
[whooshing noises]
[band music]
Aye, aye, sir.
Date of birth?
February 10, 1899.
Place of birth?
Miles City, Montana.
[cheering]
Boys, I'm not going tomake a speech here today.
You're leaving home to begin
the long trek to France.
No words of mine can tell youwhat you're going to fight for.
You all know.
The only thing I can sayis we're all proud of you.
Good bye, and good luck.
[military commands]
[patriotic music]
[cheering]
[train whistle]
NARRATOR: With serious
purpose, the nation
dug in for the biggest
job it had ever tackled.
Starting with a regulararmy of 130,000 and 70,000
half-trained,
ill-equipped reserves,
the United States
undertook a mobilization
of manpower and resourceswithout precedent
in any age or any time.
To equip America's soldierswas US industry's first job.
Production began on 14 millionuniforms, 27 million pairs
of shoes, 3 and 1/2 millionrifles and bayonets, a quarter
of a million machine guns.
[band music]
In the nation's war
effort, every citizen
was to take a part.
Ed, how about
putting me to work
as one of your four minute men.
You young fellows havemore than you can handle.
And I'd like to help
in this war too.
Well, Dr. Hatfield,
it's pretty strenuous.
Four or five speeches a day.
That doesn't worry me a bit.
I've been preaching
sermons since you
were a boy in knee pants.
All right.
When can you start?
Start now.
[patriotic music]
NARRATOR: Through liberty loans,the American people raised
the huge sum of $24 billion.
[cheering]
Within three months afterthe declaration of war
came the draft, the firstmilitary conscription since
the war between the states.
24 million men of militaryage registered for war service
and waited for their
numbers to come up.
In the 19 months of war,
there were to be three
drawings of the draft lottery.
Is that you, stranger?
Yup.
I had a hunch my
number was due up.
Look, there's another one.
NARRATOR: By the spring
of 1918, a nation
that for half a centuryhad not fought a major war
had called nearly 3 millionof its citizens to the colors.
[parade music]
Another 3 million men wereat work in US war industries.
The biggest job was
steel, and more steel.
Steel for big shell.
More steel for the big guns.
With its experience in supplyingFrench and British armies,
American industry
in the first year
produced 1 million
tons of munition.
Meanwhile, in France, Frenchand British manpower continued
to hold off the
powerful war machine,
for their new ally 3,000 milesaway was unprepared, and could
not send the trained
men so desperately
needed to stop the greatGerman drive of late 1917.
It was not until early 1918that America's first million
were equipped and in training.
Still ahead were weeks of
body-hardening marches,
long, precious weeks oftraining for trench warfare,
for going over the top.
Crews for convoys
and submarine patrol.
Crews for transports.
Transferred to the Army were theNavy's regiments of US Marines,
soldier/sailors who were
to take their places
on the battlefields of France.
MAN: Private Bensinger,report to commanding officer
immediately.
[inaudible], up front.
Inspection, halt. [inaudible].
Private Bensinger, sir.
Yes, at ease.
You know, I suppose
that your father's
interned as an enemy alien.
Yes, sir.
I'm sorry, but I have totell you that it will not
be possible for you to gooverseas with the regiment
under the circumstances.
Yes, sir.
That's all, I'm afraid.
Aye, aye, sir.
[singing]
Good bye, Ma.
Good bye, Pa.
Goodbye, mule, with
your old hee-haw.
I may not know what
the war's about,
but I bet, by grass,
I'll soon find out.
And oh, my sweetheart,
don't you fear.
I'll bring you a
king for a souvenir.
I'll get you a Turk
and Kaiser too.
And that's about all
one fellow can do.
Fellows getting
everything you wanted?
Well, almost.
That's fine.
Nothings to good for our boys.
[singing]
Can I have a package
of Sweet Caps please?
Why, certainly, Eddie.
Did you know my outfit wasleaving tonight, Mrs. Averill?
I suppose you're awfully glad.
You bet.
Well, hello there.
Hello, dear.
Evening, Ruth.
I'll be with you
in just a minute
[singing]
Mr. Lawton?
Yes, my boy?
Could you do me
a special favor?
Doing favors is a
Congressman's main job.
Well, do you supposeyou could have me ordered
over to France in a hurry?
I'm afraid if I don't get
over there pretty soon,
there won't be any
war left to fight.
--[laughing] I wouldn't worrytoo much about that, my boy.
Good night, Mrs. Averill.
Goodbye, Eddie.
Good luck.
Thank you.
[singing]
[patriotic music]
NARRATOR: Under the commandof Admiral William Sims,
since the declaration
of war, US destroyers
had been helping to rid theseas of the German U-boat,
with the aid of a new Britishweapon, the depth bomb.
[patriotic music]
[explosion]
For a year, US dreadnaughtshad been with the British fleet
at Scapa Flow.
Now, the efforts of a unitedAmerica were producing results.
1 million, trained
and equipped, were
ready to join their Allies.
[cheering]
In May 1918 began thegreatest overseas movement
of troops in all history.
It was the citizen army of theworld's greatest democracy,
to fight in a foreignland for American ideals.
For those ideals,
one man in every 20
was destined to
give up his life.
[music playing]
[chattering]
To the war-weary
people of Europe,
these fresh and determinedmen were like saviors.
They had come none to soon.
[dramatic music]
In the spring of 1918,Germany had launched her last
and greatest offensive.
The first contingent
of Americans
met their baptism of fire in theheaviest fighting of the war.
[explosions]
Carrying on at home,
men, women, and children
were doing their bit,united toward a common goal.
Look, Miss [inaudible].
15 radishes.
Have gone over the top?
NARRATOR: In one single mammotheffort to help feed the Allied
armies, to keep aliveEurope's 30 million refugees,
the American peopleresolved that no sacrifice
could be too great, for
food would win the war.
To keep the endless convoysmoving with their cargoes
of food and materials of war,to replace the thousands of tons
of shipping destroyed
by German submarines,
American ship
builders were engaged
in the greatest constructionprogram of all time.
By the summer of 1918,
more than a ship a day
was going down the waves.
Ships of steal, wooden ships,even ships made of concrete.
To France in 1918 wentmany a US political figure,
great and small.
What is the type of
your artillery support?
[non-english speech]
We have in support bothheavy artillery and 75's.
Thank you.
NARRATOR: On French soil
in the ranks of the AEF,
2 million strong, were
many young Americans
destined to be among theirnation's future leaders.
And to the front
lines went Franklin
Delano Roosevelt, then
the young assistance
secretary of the Navy.
Courageous to the point ofrecklessness, American forces
by the fall of 1918 had sufferednearly 300,000 casualties,
50,000 killed in action.
Eddie?
Here's a friend of yours.
It's Sean Lawton
from back home, Eddie.
Mr. Lawton?
How did you ever find outwhere I was, Mr. Lawton.
Oh, that wasn't so hard.
Gee, I never expected
to see anybody
from back home way over here.
NARRATOR: There were
to be more casualties.
But in the Argonne
on September 29,
Americans had broken
Hindenburg Line,
last strong-hold of Germanforces on French soil.
Through the first
week of November,
there were repeated rumorsof German capitulation.
A false report reachedAmerica that an armistice
had been signed.
But the war went on.
[explosions]
Then, on November 11, 1918--
Hey!
MEN: Yay!
[cheering]
Hooray!
The war's over.
[cheering]
NARRATOR: It had come withbreathtaking suddenness.
No event in all recorded historyhad swept the minds and hearts
of men throughout theworld, with so deep and wild
a fervour of thanksgiving.
[singing]
[applause]
[cheering]
[non-english]
Vive la France!
Vive le President Wilson.
[cheering]
[patriotic music]
NARRATOR: It had taken fourlong years, from the combined
efforts of most of the
nations of the world,
to destroy the great Germanwar machine which had
threatened their civilization.
[music - "the first noel"]
The American community
in the winter of 1918
was preparing to
celebrate a new year.
Americans faced their futurewith the confidence of a people
who had accepted the
gravest responsibility
their age could offer.
They had fought for andpreserved the way of life which
was their American heritage.
In a few minutes
now, it'll be 1919.
Dan, how about a toast?
You know, I have
never forgotten,
and I suppose I
never will forget,
the President's
words when he told
us why we were going to war.
I would say, to the things wefought for and won-- democracy,
the rights of those whosubmit to authority to have
a voice in their own government,
the rights and liberties
of small nations,
a peace that will
bring safety to allpeoples, and make the world
itself at last free.
[trumpets]
[explosions]
NARRATOR: Guiding
the Germany of 1940
and its war machine
is a blueprint
for world conquest, a book whichevery good Nazi knows by heart.
Its title? "Mein Kampf."
Its author?
Adolf Hitler.
"Democracy is a monstrosity,born of filth and fire.
While democracy talks, we act.
Borders are made by man,and can be changed by man.
Germany will be the
world power or nothing.
Almighty God,
bless our battles."
First step to conquest
in the Nazi scheme
is to demoralize the enemy bypropaganda, to inspire fear,
and to breed terror.
At Bermuda, Britishcontraband control officers
had intercepted tons ofNazi propaganda, destined
to make the Americas
fear the might
of Germany's great war machine.
Most famous piece of confiscatedNazi propaganda is an English
language version of themotion picture [non-english],
"Baptism of Fire,"
showing the horror
and detailing the techniqueof the Blitzkrieg.
Hitler used this
film to soften up
resistance in the
European nations
he was about to destroy.
[trumpets]
The appointed hour is at hand.
The attack is geared
for lightening swiftness
and irresistible power.
Total war is a sciencewhich Germany has mastered.
The operation is directed fromthe Fuehrer's private railway
carriage, for the Fuehrerhimself is the final source
of all decisions and commands.
The orders go out to the variousdivisions and commanders,
assuring perfectcoordination of the attack.
The first units tocontact the enemy of those
of the German air force.
The years of sacrifice todevelop this great air force
have not been in vain.
For thousands of planes willcarry the attack to every part
of the enemy territory.
[plane engines]
Stuka planes, protected
by German engineers,
dive thousands of feet
upon their targets.
[plane engines]
A Stuka pilot dives upon
a railroad junction.
To bomb the target, he aims hismachine directly down upon it.
[explosion]
The task of the air
force in total war
is to attack enemy airfields anddisperse enemy concentrations
of troops and material, todisrupt enemy communications
far behind the lines, andto destroy the enemy's
vital industrial centers.
[explosions]
Against aircraft, suchantiquated weapons as armor
trains are utterly useless.
Because mastery of the air isvital to the lightning attack,
airports, multi-million
and military,
are among our first objectives.
But in a few days, theinferior air force of the enemy
has been completely destroyed,and the German air force rules
supreme.
To halt the advance
of our forces,
the enemy has blown
up his bridges.
But detachments of engineers,assisted by Reich labor
servicemen restore without delayany roads or bridges rendered
impassable by the enemy.
And our troops continuetheir advance unhindered.
[galloping]
The lightning attack demands theacceleration of all movements.
If bridges are
scarce, German forces,
even heavy mechanized units,have ways of crossing rivers
without them.
[engines]
Meanwhile, parachute troopsare dropped behind the lines.
These men are able to capturestrategic telephone, telegraph,
and wireless stations, andcause great panic and confusion,
particularly among civilians.
[plane engine]
Ranging far ahead of the mainbody of the army, [inaudible]
divisions, small, mechanized,highly mobile units
that penetrated to
enemy cities far
behind the main battle front.
[explosions]
If the surprised enemy garrisoncannot be overcome with hand
grenades and light
artillery, their hiding
place is sprayed with gasoline.
[gunfire]
The infantry follows themechanized divisions to destroy
the main armies of the enemy.
Hardened by long training,
the German soldier has
incredible physical endurance.
Sometimes, he must advance 30or 35 miles a day, with no rest
and little sleep for
more than a week.
The capital city
of the enemy nation
is reached within a few days.
When the enemy does notadopt the reasonable course
of unconditional surrender,
this capital must,
unfortunately, be destroyed.
[engine]
Nations which make
war upon Germany
must be prepared to face theconsequences of their acts.
The enemy at last has noalternative but surrender.
Because of his
senseless resistance,
the terms will now
be less lenient.
There is no possibility
of compromise
with the victorious German army.
Vast quantities of war materialsof all kinds of been captured,
more than enough to
replace what has been
lost for the German forces.
[orchestral music]
Within the city, German
soldiers are greeted
by loyal friends and admirers.
And every country,Germany has such friends.
[applause]
Those who have been of serviceto Germany behind enemy lines
are given an
opportunity to identify
persons who have persecutedthem before the German conquest.
Such persons will be shot.
As a result of their mad desireto wage war upon Germany,
hundreds of thousands of theenemy's most able-bodied men
have temporarily
lost their freedom.
They will be formed
into labor battalions
and sent to Germany to
help with the harvests,
and otherwise, to take theplace of German fighters
on other fronts.
Under German supervision,many of these men
will do useful work for thefirst time in their lives.
The enemy is no more.
Before the power of German armsand the terror of propaganda,
nine once-free nationshave already fallen under
the domination of Adolf Hitter.
And upon German conquest,Hitler has set no limits.
The slogan of his war
machine-- today, we
are masters of Europe.
Tomorrow, we shall
rule the world.
[speaking german]
Again, today, as in the
years of 1917 and '18,
the American people arepreparing to meet the challenge
of might makes right.
Overwhelmingly, we as a
nation, we are convinced
that military and naval victoryfor the gods of force of hate,
would endanger theinstitutions of democracy
in the Western world.
Once more, the
future of the nation,
the future of the Americanpeople, is at stake.
I call for effort, courage,sacrifice, [inaudible],
granting the love of freedom,All of these are possible.
And the love freedom isstill fierce, still steady,
in the nation today.
[applause]
[patriotic music]
Our way of life
is in competition
with Hitler's way of life.
And I promise to
out-distance him
in any contest he may choose.
And I promise you
that when we beat him,
we will beat him on our ownterms, and in the American way.
[applause]
NARRATOR: Today under leadersunited in their determination
to meet force withsuperior force, Americans
themselves once more standunited against the powers
of aggression.
And as Americans measure
their nation's strength,
they remember that there havebeen other times of crisis
when the people of Americahave taken up arms.
The founders of America
fought for freedom
and established theirrepublic by force of arms.
Other generations of Americanshave fought to preserve it,
and Americans today rememberthat their nation's courage
has been tested under fire
within the memory of men
now living.
MAN: Happy New Year!
[cheering]
NARRATOR: For in their
brave little world,
Americans of a
generation ago met
crisis, and emerged fromit citizens of the greatest
nation on Earth.
Now, an old man, I'd
like to make a toast.
Through the generations
yet to come, in peace,
may they cherish that which weare handing on down to them.
In crisis, may
they unite and know
as we have known the joy
and strength of uniting.
In war, if it should
ever come again,
may they hold the rampartsof our democracy and freedom
until kingdom come.
[MUSIC - "THE STAR SPANGLED BANNER"]
CHORUS: --the
rockets' red glare,
the bombs bursting in air,gave proof through the night
that our flag was still there.
Oh, say, does that star-spangledbanner yet wave o'er the land
of the free, and the
home of the brave.