My name is Anne Blair.
My father was Dr. Julian Blair.
This was my father's house.
In Barsham Harbor,
on nights like this...
...when lightning rips the night apart...
...why do people close the shutters
that face towards my father's house?
And lock their doors and whisper?
Why are they afraid?
No one goes near my father's house.
No one dares.
I don't know where my father is.
I only know that for one
brief terrible moment...
...he tore open the door
to whatever lives beyond the grave.
Seven years ago, my father was
head of the science department...
...at Midland University...
...a few hundred miles
from Barsham Harbor.
My father was famous.
They were proud of him
at the university.
That night, five great scientists
came to my father's laboratory...
...to see something no one
on earth had ever seen before.
Finally ready to startle us, Dr. Blair?
l don't blame you for being skeptical,
Professor Kent...
...but l assure you that
all this is vitally necessary...
...for the demonstration
l've invited you here to witness.
You will be the first people...
...with the exception of my wife
and my assistant, Dr. Sayles...
...to see the proof
that the human brain...
...gives off an impulse
that can be recorded.
l think we'd better close
those blinds, Saunders.
Please watch the chart, gentlemen.
Dr. Sayles' brain is sending out the
waves you see recorded on that chart.
And whether he speaks or is silent...
...or even if he tried to hide what he was
thinking with meaningless words...
...his true thoughts would
still be recorded on that chart.
-How did you reach that conclusion?
-Well...
...you will notice a repeated pattern
in the variant waves, an exact rhythm...
...as though it were a carrier wave...
...on which the true thoughts
were being transmitted.
l think we better stop now.
-You feel any ill effects?
-Not at all, Dr. Saunders.
So that's a portrait
of the mind of Dr. Sayles.
-Yes, Dr. Hart.
-A poor thing, but mine own.
-Seems incredible.
-Can you make a graph like that...
-...for any living brain?
-Oh, yes.
And each brain has
its own wavelength...
...and they're as unlike as fingerprints.
Excuse me.
l couldn't help it.
She said it was important.
-Helen!
-Don't blame Karl.
-You're not angry, are you?
-Of course not.
Come on in.
You know everybody here.
-Hello, Richard.
-Hello, Mrs. Blair.
-Good evening.
-How are you?
l hope you'll forgive me for interrupting,
but l know my husband so well.
When he gets started in the lab...
...he forgets about time
and people and everything.
You have forgotten, dear,
haven't you?
Anne is coming home this evening.
Anne is our daughter, and she's
been visiting friends in New York.
Today's her 20th birthday.
l remembered that.
-lf we don't hurry, we'll be late.
-Helen, wait a minute.
We've still got time.
l was showing them
the recording with Richard.
Now l'd like to show them
your graph for comparison.
-But it's so late, darling.
-Oh, please, dear, it won't take a minute.
l'm not really Julian's wife.
l'm guinea pig number one
for his experiments.
And l guess l still like it
after all these years.
l envy you, doctor.
-A wonderful wife for a scientist.
-For any man.
Thanks.
-Are you sure your hair isn't wet?
-No, no.
-Sure?
-Sure.
You reset the graph, please, Richard.
See how different the wavelengths are?
Why should this record
be so much stronger?
l don't know, but every demonstration
that l've made so far...
...clearly shows the wave impulse
of woman, the so-called weaker sex...
...is much stronger and is
much more regular than man's.
Evidently, there's a greater natural power
in the brain of woman.
-Any woman.
-Haven't l always told you that, Julian?
-Has Mrs. Blair's graph ever varied?
-The individual wavelength never varies.
Well, l believe what l can see.
Now tell me where you go from there.
Well, eventually, conceivably,
we may be able to record and read...
...the thoughts of every human brain
without a word being spoken.
You actually believe that someday
you can push a button here...
...and read what
l'm thinking in Chicago?
-You'll be able to read my thoughts too.
-lmpossible.
They called radio impossible,
but all this that you see...
...is only the first step towards
what we can achieve.
lt may take years, perhaps a lifetime.
But if science can unlock
the human mind...
...can uncover the secrets
of every human brain...
...well, that's a job worth doing,
Professor Kent.
That's the first understatement
l've heard you make.
l'd like to show them
the laboratory notes, Richard.
-l'll get them.
-Richard, get his coat.
-We've got to go.
-That's right.
l'll have to leave you
with Dr. Sayles.
-You see, l'm helpless.
-Sorry, gentlemen.
Good night.
-Do hurry, Julian.
-l'm sure we've got plenty of time, dear.
Richard, l forgot to turn off
those switches.
l'll take care of that.
-We'll see you at the house later.
-All right.
Come along, Julian.
Hurry up.
You know...
...l think l even convinced Professor
Kent, and that's a major triumph.
Darling, don't be a scientist
anymore tonight.
You're asking an awful lot, but l'll try.
Say, aren't we going the wrong way
for the station?
You've forgotten again, haven't you?
l told you l was ordering
a birthday cake for Anne's party...
-...with her name on it, remember?
-Oh, yes.
-l don't see how you put up with me.
-lt's because you're you.
l don't see anywhere to park, do you?
Run out and get the cake,
and l'll drive around and pick you up.
And hurry, dear. lt's almost train time.
-Come for the birthday cake?
-Yes, Mr. Booth.
Well, it's all ready for you.
-Okay, doc?
-You're an artist.
Well, l try to be,
especially for nice folks.
Bet you and Mrs. Blair are happy
to have the young lady back.
-lndeed we are.
-l'll carry it out for you.
-l wanna say hello to Mrs. Blair anyhow.
-Thank you very much.
Helen.
I lost my mother that night.
And when she went away...
...I seemed to lose my father too.
He loved her so much.
I did all I could
to take my mother's place.
He didn't seem to know I was there.
He was lost.
Alone.
There wasn't anything
I could say to him.
There wasn't anything I could do.
l'll get the car.
No, Richard.
You take Anne home.
l want to walk for a while and think.
He went back to his laboratory
that night.
Alone.
He couldn't bear being in our house...
...where everything reminded him
of my mother.
Helen.
Anne...
...for a moment, l thought that....
Father, what's the matter?
Anne, dear...
...your mother is not dead, not really.
She's come back to me.
No, dear...
...l haven't lost my mind.
She's here, here in this room.
She still lives.
Look.
l can only tell you again...
...that when l turned on those motors...
...it was simply because
l had to be doing something.
l wasn't trying to reach my wife.
l had no reason on earth
to believe that l could reach her.
But she tried to reach me.
There is the proof of something
the world has always wanted to believe.
The proof of life after death.
Richard. You of all people,
you've worked with me.
You know how we believe
that mind could talk to mind.
Well, now l know that there is a way
for the dead to talk to the living.
My wife has passed through
a change that we call death.
But the impulse that spoke
from her living brain...
...that you saw me record
on that chart, did not die.
lf Helen could send me that message,
and she did send it...
...then there must be a way
to establish controlled and scientific...
...communication between
the living and the so-called dead.
Do you really believe what you say?
Do you think l would invent
a story like that about my wife?
How do you propose to go about
establishing this communication?
Radio began with a first,
faint, transmitted impulse...
...which no one knew
how to control or harness.
Yet science found a way
to send sound and speech...
...and living images
clear around the world.
Well, l believe that the human brain,
the brain that invented radio...
...is itself the most perfect sending
and receiving mechanism on earth.
And l know that power
does not end with the grave.
Don't you see?
We hold in our hand a key
that may unlock the door...
...between us and those
whom we call dead.
lf we can set humanity free from fear...
...if we can show people that those
we love are not lost to us...
...if we can wipe out the horror...
...that superstition conjures
up out of fear of darkness--
Julian.
l have too much respect
for you to scoff at your hopes...
...to doubt your utter sincerity.
But what if you do find a way to pierce
the veil between us and them?
And let the world of the dead
back in upon the living?
We don't know what evil
may be lurking behind that veil...
...waiting to get through.
What if you let loose on humanity...
...something much more terrible
than any fear that haunts us now?
-But why should that happen?
-l know one thing, Julian.
There are things human being
have no right to know.
There speaks fear, even from you.
Call it fear if you want to. l tell you,
you must not go on with this.
Must not? ls there a wall beyond
which science may not go?
-This is not science.
-Please don't argue.
Anne.
Don't argue with him,
because he's not himself.
That's what's in your mind, isn't it?
You won't believe me.
You won't help me.
Poor, frightened little people.
Well, l don't need you.
l don't need any of you.
Dad, won't you come
home now and rest?
Then tomorrow,
maybe you'll feel better.
Tomorrow.
No, Anne.
l'm not some helpless child
to be taken home for his own good.
Get out. Get out.
All of you.
Do you hear me, Anne?
Go home.
Thank you, gentlemen.
Thank you for your great faith in me.
What do you want?
l just wanna tell you
you're right, doc. l know.
-What are you talking about?
-l know we can talk to the dead.
l talk to my mama all the time.
She died two years ago,
but l can still talk to her.
-How?
-Ever hear of Mrs. Blanche Walters?
She's a spirit medium.
Her control brings the voice to you
from the beyond.
l'm afraid mediums
are no good to me, Karl.
You better go now,
l've got work to do.
But, doc...
...it wouldn't hurt to see what
Mrs. Walters can do, would it?
No.
That night, my father took another step
toward tragedy.
Poor Karl wasn't to blame.
Perhaps no one was to blame.
I don't know.
But that night, my father
met Mrs. Walters...
...and then for him...
...there was no turning back.
There is one here
who seeks his mother...
...who asks his mother
to speak to him.
His name is C....
K....
Karl.
Karl seeks his mother.
ls Karl here?
Here.
Here l am.
Karl.
Your mother is calling you.
Your mother is...
...with us.
Talk to me.
-l see you.
-Karl.
Karl, my son.
-l hear you.
-Karl.
Don't be unhappy.
lt's very beautiful here.
l am at peace.
There is no pain, no sickness,
no sorrow.
l am watching over you, Karl.
We will meet again...
...soon.
-Come back!
-No.
No, l can't.
They've gone. l can't find them.
Turn on the lights.
-Mrs. Walters, are you all right?
-l'll get some water.
l'm afraid l can go no further tonight.
You will forgive me, now, won't you?
l'm so tired.
-lt was wonderful, Mrs. Walters.
-An inspiration.
We'll see you next Tuesday.
Your hats and coats are in the hallway.
-You coming, doc?
-l'm going to talk to Mrs. Walters.
l congratulate you.
l've seen a lot of mediums at work...
...but l think yours is one of the
smoothest performances l've ever seen.
You're not the first unbeliever l've met.
But other men of science have turned
to the occult for surcease from sorrow.
Sir Oliver Lodge was a believer.
-So was Sir Arthur Conan Doyle.
-l know, Mrs. Walters.
But l am quite sure that l can duplicate
every trick you've done here tonight.
l hate to disillusion you, Karl...
...but there's your mother's ghost.
And the voice...
...came from...
...here.
There's just one thing more--
Get out of here, both of you.
Get out.
After you've explained
one trick that's new to me.
How do you handle
the wiring for that table?
What wiring?
l experienced a severe shock during
the séance, a dangerously high voltage.
lt might prove fatal to some
of your more elderly clients.
Are you crazy? l've never used
electricity in a séance in my life.
ls that the truth?
Why should l lie to you now?
What if that's true?
lf that impulse...
...is really generated by your own brain...
...and your nervous system
without your knowledge, then....
lf that's possible.
Mrs. Walters, l'd like you to come
to my laboratory now.
l'd like to make a test.
-Why?
-lt may be that you're closer...
...to a real communication
with the dead than you ever realized.
l'm not in this business
for my health, Dr. Blair.
lf you can help me in my work,
you'll be well-paid.
l'll get my coat.
I waited for my father at home
that night.
I didn't know what to do.
I didn't know where he was.
And all the time, he was locked
up there in his laboratory...
...with Karl and Mrs. Walters.
All he could think of was
how to reach my mother...
...how to talk to her.
He thought Mrs. Walters
might be able to help him.
He wasn't sure,
but he had to find out.
And that...
...that was the beginning.
l think you'd better
take off that ring.
Stand back, Karl.
Are you afraid?
Now watch those lights.
Your brain and nervous system
are producing an electrical current.
An incredibly high voltage.
Dr. Blair, l think it's time you
told me what this is all about.
This is science, Mrs. Walters.
There's nothing of the occult about it.
lf you can produce an electrical
voltage as powerful as that...
...the next step is to see if
you can absorb as much or more.
And if l can?
Then you may serve
the same purpose...
...as the ground and aerials serve
in radio sending and receiving.
But l can't be sure
until l make a further test.
Karl, you can help me, if you will.
You can take that off now.
Let's move this out here, Karl.
Far enough. Over here,
if you please, Mrs. Walters.
Stand back, Karl.
All ready?
Karl!
l'm all right.
Do you realize that 2000 volts would
electrocute the ordinary human being...
...but 1 0,000 passed through your body
a moment ago without harming you?
l believe l'm on the right track.
Let me show you something.
That wave, that impulse was recorded
by my wife's brain before she died.
That was recorded after
she was dead and buried.
That proves that that brain impulse
still lives somewhere.
What has that got to do with me?
l believe that if l could change
the hookup on that recording machine...
...so that instead of recording
your brain waves...
...l could utilize the energy output
and receiving field...
...of an abnormally sensitized
human being, like you, for instance.
l could bring in that impulse so strongly
that l could record it constantly...
...and perhaps learn
to read its message.
Eventually, l may bring back
my wife's actual voice...
...and show the world
how to talk to those who have...
...passed beyond the grave.
lf you can do what you're trying
to do, you'll own the world.
You know that, don't you?
You sit down and rest for a while.
Then we'll see.
My father didn't come home.
I didn't know what to do.
Finally, I couldn't stand waiting,
wondering.
I had to find him.
I called Richard Sayles.
-Karl, do you want to help?
-Sure, doc.
Then get a chair and put
it next to Mrs. Walters. Hurry.
l'm going to add Karl to the circuit.
lt may add to the receiving strength
of the machines...
...just like adding radio tubes to a set.
ln a little bit, Karl.
That's right.
Now sit down.
lt's all right, Karl.
lt's not going to hurt you.
Helen.
Helen!
Karl.
Help me.
-Who is that?
-l don't know.
We'd better not let anybody
see him the way he is now.
No.
l'll take care of him.
Go see who it is.
Dad, we've come to get you.
Do you know what time it is?
Of course.
Dad, come home.
l thought l asked you
not to bother me.
Doctor, l don't like
to say this to you, but...
...well, people are talking about you.
And there's to be a report
given at the university board...
...that...
-...well, that you....
-That l'm losing my mind.
Thank you for telling me.
Now will you leave me alone?
-Dad, please.
-Good night.
Look at Karl.
Karl. Karl.
l'm afraid electric shock has injured
his nerve centers, perhaps permanently.
The impulse had begun
to come through. lt was Helen...
...and now Karl, like this.
The world can get along without him,
and nobody has to know about this.
We can't hide him.
He has to have care.
lf anyone sees him the way he is,
the law will step in and stop you for good.
l know.
Have you got enough money
to leave this town and take Karl?
-What?
-We've got to get away from here.
Where you can go on working
and no one will know.
Yes.
The next morning,
my father sent me away to New York.
He resigned at the university.
He arranged to sell our house.
He said he was going away
that same day.
He wouldn't tell me where.
He said he'd write to me later
if he could.
He was like a stranger.
Someone I'd--
I'd never known.
And yet, he hadn't stopped loving me.
I know he hadn't.
Goodbye, Anne.
Goodbye.
I didn't see my father again
for two years.
Every three months,
he sent me a check.
He never wrote me a letter.
I wrote to him,
but he never answered.
He bought a strange house at Barsham
Harbor on the New England coast.
There, he went on with his work.
On and on and on.
People in Barsham Harbor
didn't understand my father.
They began to talk about him.
Slowly, they began to fear him
and then to hate him...
...without really knowing why.
Poison of hate
spread through the village.
No one would even speak to him...
...although he had never
hurt any of them.
You must remember that.
My father never hurt a living person
in Barsham Harbor.
Never.
-Why, Sheriff Ed.
-Evening, Mrs. Marcy.
What on earth you doing way out here?
Come on inside.
l asked you what you're doing
way out here.
-Oh, business, Mrs. Marcy.
-Sheriff business?
ln a way.
Your husband around anywhere?
Seth Marcy ain't set foot
on these premises...
...the two years l been working here,
and swears he never will.
Seth don't like Dr. Blair.
From what l hear,
he's not the only one that don't.
-You better call Dr. Blair.
-l wouldn't dare go near him.
-Why not?
-He's working in his laboratory.
l got strict orders
never to go near that place.
This is important.
Wouldn't matter if the world
was ending tomorrow.
She wouldn't let you bother him.
-She?
-Mrs. Walters.
You seen her?
l've heard of her.
Have you noticed anything
peculiar going on around here?
l make it my business not to notice
what ain't my business.
How do you get along with that ape
that follows the doc around?
Karl?
He's harmless.
He's like a big, ugly dog.
All you have to do is raise
your voice to him, and he minds.
Hey...
...why haven't you got electric lights?
Mrs. Walters says they'd interfere
with the reception.
-Reception of what?
-l don't know.
He's inventing some kind of radio,
l guess.
You. Stand still.
Ed Willis, you put that gun away.
Karl, you stop.
Karl, you hear me?
Just like l told you.
Karl minds when he's spoken to.
What was that noise?
Some kind of static, l suppose,
from the laboratory.
l got used to it long ago.
-What do you want?
-l'd like to talk to Dr. Blair.
That's impossible.
l don't think so.
Doc, do you want to come down here,
or shall l come up?
Maybe l should explain
that l'm sheriff of this county.
The name's Willis.
Ed Willis.
-l don't care who you are.
-How about it, doc?
You don't have to talk to him.
Might make things a lot better
all around if he did.
Why?
An old settler named Sam Jennings...
...was buried in the family vault
day before yesterday.
Well?
His body disappeared last night.
Why tell us about that?
Mostly because it's happened before.
Four times before.
Five bodies missing in the two years
since you people came to this town.
And it never happened
before you came to town.
Now, it's my job to find out
who stole those bodies.
We don't know anything about it.
Ordinarily, l don't pay attention
to what people say.
l figure they've gotta
talk about something.
But when a whole town
begins to talk about...
...a connection between
the missing bodies...
...and whatever it is
that goes on in this house...
...well, l figure it's time
l found out what is going on.
This is not the first time l've been
the victim of people who talk...
...about things they're
too ignorant to understand.
l'm engaged in experimental work.
All right.
What kind of experiments?
That's none of your business.
l think it is, under the circumstances.
Dr. Blair...
...l want you to take me
to your laboratory.
Show me just what it is
you are doing...
...tell me what it's all about.
Then l can go back to town
and tell the folks.
Tell them you're okay.
And l'll make them quit talking
before the talk goes too far.
Now, that's fair enough, isn't it?
lt'd be impossible to explain to you
what l'm doing, even if l wanted to.
l believe l have the right to go on with my
work without being put on trial by fools.
This is my house.
l've committed no crime. Karl.
You will take this gentleman to the gate
and see that he leaves. That's all.
Good night.
That's all for tonight.
-Good night, Dr. Blair.
-Good night, Mrs. Marcy.
That man will be back.
l'll take care of him when he comes.
You'd better get some rest.
No, l think l'm going to work
a little later tonight.
Good night.
Oh, it's you, Sheriff Ed.
-You scared me out of me year's growth.
-Sorry.
l didn't turn on the headlights, in case
anybody was watching. Come on.
Come on, get in.
l'll drive you home.
You certainly caused
plenty of excitement tonight.
How on earth could you
practically accuse poor Dr. Blair...
...of stealing bodies?
Well, somebody stole them.
What's in that laboratory of his?
l never been in it.
The door's always kept locked.
-Could you get in?
-And get caught and lose my job?
l never was inquisitive,
and l see no reason to be now...
...just to satisfy your curiosity.
Look, Mrs. Marcy. l'm not saying there's
anything really wrong in that house.
But a lot of folks are thinking there is
unless l can tell them differently.
You know, folks can talk just so long,
and then there's an explosion.
And a lot of people get hurt.
l don't want any mob trouble
in our town.
Maybe you could help
to keep that from happening.
Will you try?
l never made a promise yet
and didn't keep it.
So l ain't gonna promise you a thing...
...but l'll see.
Karl...
...l forgot to lock the laboratory.
Take care of it for me, will you?
Let me out! Let me out!
Let me out!
Dr. Blair. Dr. Blair!
Dr. Blair! Dr. Blair! Dr. Blair!
Who's in there?
Where are the keys?
Stand back.
ls she dead?
Yes.
-How'd she get in here?
-l forgot to lock the door.
Now l am a criminal,
a murderer.
When she doesn't come home tonight,
her husband will start looking for her.
-Then how? What?
-There's only one thing we can do.
They're here.
-Who?
-Seth Marcy and the sheriff.
You'll have to talk to them.
They won't leave unless you do.
l've taken care of the footprints.
You'd better not keep the sheriff waiting
too long, or he might come up here.
-Where's my wife?
-Easy, Seth.
-l can't tell you anything about her.
-She left here hours ago.
You're lying.
She's here in this house somewhere.
l'd like to help you,
but l can't.
How do l know she's not here?
What would she be doing here
at this time of night?
You have time to help them look for her,
haven't you, Dr. Blair?
Yes, l'll get my hat and coat.
Look where?
She always went home
the same way, didn't she?
The path leads right along
the edge of the cliff at one place.
l know it does.
Come on, Seth.
lt was dark when Mrs. Marcy
left the house.
We asked her if she wanted a lantern,
but she said she didn't need one.
She walked that path day or night,
rain or shine, for two years.
She wouldn't have walked over here.
What did you do to her?
l didn't do anything to her.
l'm....
-l'm terribly sorry.
-Seth.
May l go home, please?
Yes, you might as well.
l'd be glad to help to pay
for the funeral expenses...
...in case you find--
Good night.
They've killed her.
Seth!
Now, l know how you feel...
...but l can't stand for you
starting any trouble.
You've got absolutely nothing to go on...
...nothing but loose talk
and superstition...
...and the fact that you
never did like Dr. Blair.
Now, you go around
talking too much and....
Well, l might just have
to put a stop to it.
Go on home now, Seth.
Well, are they satisfied?
Why did you follow us?
We could honestly have said
her death was accidental.
Now we've lied.
-We're as guilty as if we'd planned this.
-Stop talking like that.
Come on.
We can't stay here now.
Richard and I reached Barsham Harbor
very late that night.
The sheriff told us what he thought
had happened to Mrs. Marcy...
...and hinted much more than he said.
He told us Seth Marcy was telling
everyone my father had killed his wife.
The sheriff told us so much
we could hardly believe him.
My father had become
a very strange man.
While we were on our way
to his house...
...he was working
in that ghastly place.
Karl, go over to the other wall
and fix your safety belt.
Stand back, please.
The sooner you take charge
in there, the better.
Helen.
Look out, let me.
-You better stay down here, Anne.
-No.
Let me out. No.
l can't stand it.
Julian.
Helen.
Stop. l can't stand it.
Julian.
Helen.
No, let me out.
Mrs. Walters.
Karl, don't open that door.
Anne.
Oh, Dad.
l sent for her.
Told her she'd better come here
and take care of you.
Dad, why didn't you
answer my letters?
-Well, you never wrote me.
-But l did.
l saw a letter at the post office myself.
That's how l knew
where to get in touch with her.
But Mrs. Walters always--
l should have realized long ago.
You've done me a favor,
a great favor.
There'll be no more trouble
in this house...
-...now that my daughter is here.
-l'll be in touch later, sheriff.
All right.
Good night.
You'll find a lamp
downstairs in the kitchen.
You'll be wanting something
to eat, won't you?
l'll come talk to you later.
-But, doctor, why--?
-l'll be down in a few minutes, Richard.
l've got something to do.
lt won't take me very long.
All right, Dad.
You'll have to help me, Karl.
Yes, she's dead.
l thought you'd never get here.
Seth's got them worked up to where
they're talking about lynching him.
Not tonight, Seth.
Now go back home where you belong.
-You ain't stopping us, Ed.
-l will. lf l have to use this.
-Now, l'm warning you.
-Attaboy, Joe.
Hold him. Come on, men.
-You can't stop them now.
-Come on.
No, Karl.
Come in, Richard.
Doctor, are these...?
Now you know why l couldn't
bring the sheriff in here.
l never meant to kill anybody, Richard.
And as soon as the work is finished,
l'm going to give myself up.
Richard, we must go on
with the work. We are both scientists.
You and Anne can help me.
Do you think l'd let Anne
have anything to do with this?
Helen spoke to me tonight.
l actually heard her voice.
l found out something
l should've known...
...something l should've realized
a long time ago.
Every time Helen's tried to speak
to me since she died...
...Anne has been somewhere near.
-What are you trying to tell me?
-Anne is the key.
Don't you understand, Richard?
The impulse that belongs to Anne
is almost identical with her mother's.
Their minds are in tune.
Tonight...
...for the first time,
l heard Helen's voice.
And now with Anne to help me,
perhaps l can talk to her.
Do you think l'd let you put Anne in that?
Richard, she'll be perfectly safe.
-l won't let you touch her.
-Oh, Richard.
Don't try to stop me now.
Trust me. Help me.
Richard.
l'm going to take Anne
out of this place.
Maybe l can keep her
from knowing about this.
Richard, Anne cannot leave.
Anne cannot leave.
Karl! Don't touch him.
He isn't badly hurt.
You better take him to my room.
And that's all!
Anne, dear,
l'm not going to hurt you.
ln a few moments, we may hear
your mother's voice.
We're very close to your mother now,
dear. l feel sure of it.
l've got to use more amplification than
l've ever used before, but don't be afraid.
You'll feel something pulling at you,
dragging you towards the table...
...but l won't let that force hurt you.
lf there's any danger,
you can trust me to turn it off.
Julian.
Helen!
Helen.
He's upstairs in his laboratory.
Get out of the way, you.
-Come on, boys!
-Get him!
Helen.
Anne!
Anne. Anne!
Anne, are you hurt?
Anne!
They say my father's spirit
must still live in that house.
I don't know.
When he seemed to be so close
to what he sought...
...something reached out for him.
A warning that human beings
must not try to reach beyond death.
I don't know.
No one will ever know.
And yet, perhaps the time will come
when the door to infinity will open.
Perhaps.