Subtitles: Luís Filipe Bernardes
- Miss Cabot, please.
- Oh, hello, Mr. Hoffman.
Hello.
- Miss Cabot, your husband is here.
- Tell him to come in.
It's a streamline marriage.
- Go right in, Mr. Hoffman.
- Thanks.
- Bully.
- Hello, darling.
What have you done to Prissy?
She's crying.
She's upset about my leaving.
Did you get the tickets?
Yes. Outside suite, bath in private,
strictly delight.
Oh, you don't really mind, do you?
I can't help it if I'm American
and a little gaudy.
It may be my one and only,
and I want to do it up brown.
Hang this up in the corner,
darling, will you?
I'm filing away the accumulation of my
long and buried career as an art critic.
Why not toss it all in the waste basket?
No, someday, somebody might
want to write a book...
...called "The Life and Times of
Carol Cabot, Art Critic".
Competent little woman.
Oh, did you get the things for Ricky?
Erich.
You didn't buy him that sailor rig.
I did both. The suit you liked too.
Oh, you spoil him dreadfully.
He shouldn't have so many things.
Who bought him the camera,
a kid of seven?
Well, after all the stuff you got him,
I didn't want him to think
his mother was a heel.
Oh, I haven't told you!
J.B.'s going to pay my salary
all the time we're gone...
...and I'm going to send him some
articles from Berlin.
Isn't that marvelous?
But Coco, I thought this was
to be a vacation.
- I can hardly wait to see Dresden.
- Munich is nicer.
Wait till you taste Dielbach beer.
Dusseldorf. Lovely word, Dusseldorf.
Sounds like something made out of pastry.
There's a little place in the Bavarian Alps
on the side of a mountain,
where I used to go skiing.
It looks like a doll's town.
Oh, darling, let's go there.
I want to see everything.
In the summer there are flowers,
tiny flowers all over the mountain.
You can lie in them and look
right down into the town.
From way across the valley you can hear
the little bells on the goats.
And just lie there in the sun.
Sometimes it's very hot, but every time
a cloud passes, it's...
- ...like a cool hand.
- This isn't fair.
I've still got work to do.
Couch but no privacy.
- Yes?
- Dr. Gerhardt to see you.
- Dr. Gerhardt, here?
- Yes.
Send him in, please.
That's funny, what does he
want with me?
To wish you bon voyage.
He loses his heart to all
his obstetrical cases.
I've never seen him outside
his office at the hospital.
- Do I intrude?
- Of course not, come in, Doctor.
How are you, Hugo?
It's been months.
You must forgive me,
I've been busy, very.
Mrs. Hoffman.
And how is little Ricky?
Oh, in a dither about going.
Acts exactly as if he had rabies.
The whole world has the rabies.
Pier 86, that is to Bremen, no?
- Yes, sailing at noon.
- You prefer German boats?
Well, we wanted to take the Queen Mary,
but she doesn't go to Germany.
This visit, it is unusual, I know.
But I wished to speak to you where there
were not so many people like at the boat.
Well, sit down, please.
- You look wiltered.
- Thank you.
All the way here I sweated...
but not because it is hot.
I come to ask you a favor.
One moment I'm afraid that
you will say no.
And the next, that if you say yes,
perhaps it is wrong of me to ask.
Whatever it is, it's yes,
you know that, Hugo.
I've just learned that my brother
is in Dachau.
- Have you ever heard of that place?
- It's a concentration camp, isn't it?
My brother was sent to Dachau
six months ago.
I didn't even know you had a brother.
I do not often speak of him.
When I do it sounds like boasting.
In Berlin he had a very great position.
There are some who called him
the first philosopher in all Europe.
Ernst Gerhardt!
I never connected you.
Natürlich. I'm just another
doctor in Yorkville.
No matter.
I'm not in a concentration camp.
Last week I have a letter
from Switzerland from an old friend.
He was in the same class
with Ernst at school.
It says Ernst was arrested
six months ago.
But why, what had he done?
The letter does not say.
But I can guess.
Ernst was not a man to keep quiet
about things he believed to be wrong.
He may have been released by now.
You do not get out of Dachau so easily.
My friend says it is possible
to get out...
...only if you have money to bribe.
That's how he got free himself.
Please, don't think I come for money.
Five hundred American dollars
I can manage.
And in Dachau that is a fortune.
But I do not know any way
to get it to him.
Since his arrest, his wife and son
have moved.
And I have no longer any friends
in Germany...
...after twenty years in America.
We'll take it to him.
- We'll be glad to.
- Of course we will, Hugo.
You are very generous, my friends.
It may not be easy.
A concentration camp is not like
an American prison.
Oh, I bet they're not half as bad
as they say they are.
I hope you are right.
Anyway, I'm an American,
they won't stop me.
That is why I turn to you.
Are you yet naturalized?
Oh, I can get my second papers any time.
I have been meaning to.
He's waiting for someone to give him a lift
down to the Battery. He abhores subways.
I told him he ought to hitchhike.
- How long will you stay in Germany?
- I have three months' leave.
I have to be back in six months
or come in on the quota again,
but I won't take that chance.
Don't worry, we'll have
plenty of time.
I just have to settle some business
with my father.
I know what you say you will do
you will do, somehow.
Tomorrow at the boat I will bring
you the money.
I have to sell some things.
Liebe Freunde.
Your hat.
Danke.
He's really worried about his brother.
Wet. He was crying.
I can't blame him. He believes
everything he reads in the papers.
Well, after all there are concentration
camps and things like that.
It isn't all just fiction.
No, but you've got to take a lot
of these things with a grain of salt.
If the newspapers didn't exaggerate
a little bit now and then,
they'd never sell any papers.
When I told the newspaperman this morning
that I was going to Germany on my vacation...
he looked at me as if I were
out of my mind.
Well, if there is any doubt in your mind,
darling, I could go alone.
I could wind up the business
with my father in four weeks...
...and then we can go to Bermuda.
Sorry, mister, no soap.
Oh, don't mind him, he just
works here.
Heil Hitler!
I don't see why me must
go through all that nonsense.
- Why did he do that?
- Their way of saying hello and goodbye.
- Why?
- Hush, dear.
Frau Olga!
Mommy, did you see?
He bit her hand!
- Wo ist die Zollkontrolle, bitte?
- Bist du Deutsche?
- Ya, natürlich.
- Geradeaus, bitte. Heil Hitler.
- He knew I was German.
- Your accent, of course.
It's funny, I don't feel a bit
as if I really belonged here.
- I feel like a tourist.
- You'd better.
I'd hate to be a little knickknack you picked
up abroad somewhere, especially with this.
Bahnkarte, bitte.
Can you reach in my pocket,
I don't want to wake Ricky.
- Which pocket?
- No, let the little one sleep.
- Where do you go?
- Berlin.
Then you will give me
the tickets later, ja?
- Of course, and thank you.
- Bitte seher, Heil Hitler.
How can anyone say the Germans
have been brutalized?
Propaganda. Listen to this.
It was announced that because
of the labor shortage...
and the extreme, er... advisability,
urgency is closer, I guess,
...of gathering the harvest, several thousand
farm workers are being brought from Ostmark.
That's what they call Austria
now that it's part of the Reich.
I told you there wasn't any
unemployment here.
More jobs than men.
Seems to good to believe.
You can't get around it.
These boys are doing a big job.
The government is going to put out
radio sets for only 35 marks.
How much is that?
Oh, er, Reichmarks are worth more than
tourist marks, about 40 cents, I think.
Er, twelve plus two... $14 apiece.
And our little one at home
cost twenty-five.
And these are much better,
according to Goebbels.
There are already 9,5 million
radio sets in Germany,
more than in all the rest of Europe.
I read somewhere they were making
a small car cheaper than the Ford.
Yes, the Volkswagen, much cheaper.
Only about $400.
How do they do it?
Well, if the government says
you have to make it at that price,
the industry has to make it,
that's all.
You have to hand it to them. Industrially,
they're way ahead of the rest of Europe.
In some ways even of America.
They should worry about unions
over here.
And the government even fixes it so
you pay on installments all in advance.
By the time the car is delivered,
it's all paid for.
- Is it any good?
- Well, they haven't produced any yet.
Why are we slowing up?
Waiting for the signal, I guess.
What are the guards for?
Do you suppose those are prisoners?
Oh, no.
No, not prisoners.
Those are the workers from Ostmark
you read about in the newspaper.
Our German brothers.
We have to guard them,
because they're stupid.
They would run away from a country
where there is no unemployment.
Only soldiers in labor camps.
Where you can buy a radio
for 35 marks, which you call 40 cents.
But it is the same as a dollar
to a German.
Of course you cannot tune in Moscow,
or Paris, or London.
But only a traitor wants to hear what our
newspapers don't tell us for our own good.
Those poor, stupid Austrians would rather
be home with their families.
But they can't have ration cards,
or stand in line to buy bread.
They have to work here in a country where
you can buy an automobile for only $400,
which will be delivered someday...
maybe.
Heil Hitler!
He's crazy going around saying things
like that to strangers.
He could get into a lot of trouble.
I guess we have that simpatico look.
Well, if anybody else starts
anything like that, duck!
We've got to be careful, darling.
Keep our ears and traps shut.
Stick to our own business.
- We don't want to get mixed up in all this.
- Don't worry, mister,
I just came along for the ride.
Erich!
Bitte...
Erich Hoffman!
Erkennst du mich nicht?
Könnte ich nicht dir erkennen.
Ich bin Frieda, Frieda Heinkel.
Gunthers frau.
Bitten Sie noch, wir waren Kind
zusammen in diesselben Schule.
Mein mädchen Name war
Frieda Stuhl.
Ah, natürlich!
Carol, this is Gunther Heinkel's wife.
She was my best friend.
We went to school together.
My wife hasn't er... Oh.
Meine Frau spricht nicht Deutsch.
- Nein?
- It's stupid of me, I know, but...
Erich already spoke English
when I met him.
Well then, I speak English.
I can practice.
- How do you do?
- You are very pretty.
- Thank you. So are you.
Me? Oh, I never think how I look.
We have so much work to do.
Here we do not have time for masseuses,
and dressmakers and cosmetics
like in America.
You don't need it, you're
naturally lovely.
I'm afraid I come out of a jar.
Ja? Oh, I have tried them all.
Mud baths, permanent waves,
paint, lipstick, all those silly things.
But that was before, when there
was nothing better to do.
Before what?
Before... before machtübernahme.
Oh, I don't know how to say it.
Oh, um... literally it means, er...
the taking over of power.
- By the women, you mean?
- By the Party, natürlich.
Well, my father was supposed
to meet me here.
No, I came in his place.
At his age, you understand,
he doesn't like riding in the tramcar.
Tramcar? Why, he has his
own automobile.
We cannot waste petrol
for private cars.
Oh, well, let's get out of here.
They'll take care of the luggage.
The streetcar will be fine.
It'll be fun.
Where's Ricky?
Oh, there he is.
- You have a child?
- That's what we call him...
...but it's more like having
a grasshopper.
He's blond.
He has never seen any of these
soldiers before.
- Ricky, this is Mrs. Heinkel.
- Are they going to war?
There isn't any war to go to.
Pretty soon you'll be big enough
to join the Jungvolk.
Some day perhaps, you'll be
a Party leader.
I wanna be a Lone Ranger.
- Was isten das?
- A character on the radio at home.
Don't you know the Lone Ranger?
"Hi-Yo Silver!"
Ja...
Today no meat, tomorrow no butter,
the next day no sugar.
1938 becomes like 1918.
- Not so, Otto?
- Bitte?
- Well, you speak English.
- Nein, Herr Direktor.
- But you understand.
- A little.
You spoke it well twenty years ago.
Ah, twenty years...
zwanzig Jahre, das ist eine
lange Zeit.
Yes...
He says such a long time.
Ya, that's true.
A century, not so?
I'm living beyond my years.
Sixty isn't old.
A man's age is no longer
measured by his years.
Ya, the old Germany disappears.
The Germany I understood
understood me.
The new Germany is for the young
people, so I'm old, not so?
For six months I do not leave
this house.
That's why I asked you
to come here, Erich.
You must stay here and manage
the factory.
Or we must sell.
I cannot breathe this Berlin
air any longer.
There is a little village on the Rhine...
above Cologne,
a very little village,
and all the people who live there
are old like the vineyards.
The young have gone away.
You see only faces gnarled
like the vines.
I will go there.
There I can live in peace...
...until I die.
Of course I think you're
making a mistake.
Oh, no, no, Erich, you don't understand
yet what this Berlin is,
this Berlin does to my health!
All the doctors say the same.
It's a bad time to sell with our
foreign market going to pieces.
You don't think I want to leave
after thirty years.
But I must, not so?
Does old man Friehof still live
next door?
Ludwig, yes, he's still here.
Every Saturday night, for as long
as I can remember,
Mr. Friehof played chess with Father.
And lost, he always loses.
Not any more. He doesn't come
here since months.
Mother used to say if he ever won,
we'd never see him again.
His son was arrested. The older one.
- The one who wore glasses?
- Ya, he was always reading.
And remembering, which is worse.
- That was the doorbell.
- Bitte?
Die glöcke es klingelt!
- Da, gehen Sie, bitte.
- Ja, natürlich.
Es tut mir Leid, Herr Direktor.
Ich hatte es nicht gehört
The Friehof boy, he meant
to make a joke.
He said, der Führer once promised
not to take Austria,
and now he'll promise not
to take Czechoslovakia,
and soon he would promise not
to take the world.
He always diddled with his chin.
Yes, but it was my misfortune...
...that he said it while he was here
at dinner with his father.
- Someone reported it to the police.
- Who else was here?
Only myself.
And... Otto, of course.
Frau Heinkel, Herr Direktor.
Ja, komm herein.
There has just been an announcement
in the radio.
Dr. Goebbels is going to go
on the air tonight.
Right away, any minute.
Später. Wir gehen ins Wohnzimmer.
Wouldn't you rather finish dinner?
Erich and I will have plenty of chances
to listen to Goebbels.
In Germany, we all listen when
der Herr Doktor speaks.
It is forbidden not to.
No, Frieda?
When our leaders speak,
we are glad to listen.
Doktor Goebbels ist ein
großartiger Redner.
What's he saying?
He's raising Cain with
the Bolsheviks.
Shhh!
Silence, bitte!
That's how the war of the future
is going to be fought.
Looks like something you see
at the circus.
The world may laugh at us just now,
but someday they won't laugh.
That's the Condor Legion, back from
fighting in Spain.
- Gives you a boot, doesn't it?
- In the stomach.
Imagine what it does to me,
a German.
- Like it?
- Love it.
Me too.
You especially.
This is the Germany I've dreamed of.
What do you say we stay
over here?
Don't go back at all.
Erich, you're not serious.
We'll do much better running
the factory than trying to sell it.
- I haven't had a decent offer yet.
- But we can't!
Why not? Technically I'm still a German
citizen and you're my wife.
Erich, please.
But Ricky likes it here now
that he's started in school.
- Let's not argue about it.
- But, darling, you just said you loved it.
I do, here, tonight, but...
It isn't like home, never could be.
- It happens to be my home.
- Does not.
New York's your home, our home.
You've always said so.
Yes, I know, that's the way I felt,
but now everything has changed.
Germany's alive, exciting.
The Horst Wessell song says,
"Make way, make way, here come
the Brown Battalions."
Let's not kid ouselves.
Those boys are going somewhere.
If you don't mind, I'll take
the detour.
Joke all you like.
But at least Berlin isn't out
of the world anymore.
Here is where history is
being made, right here.
And that's where I want to be.
Oh, Erich, Adis Abeba, Port Said or even
across the East River in Red Hook, but...
...not here, please.
But what's got you so down
on Germany all of a sudden?
I'm not, really I'm not, but...
Ah, here you are.
I didn't think you'd be hiding
out here like a love affair.
It's such a big place.
I looked everywhere.
- Do I disturb?
- No, of course not.
I wasn't sure you were coming.
You didn't say definitely.
I only said yes.
Did you tell her?
- Why, no, not yet.
- Tell me what?
The money you brought from America
for Ernst Gerhardt.
- You must not try to deliver it to him.
- You told her?
Why, I thought she might help.
There is no need to lie.
Of course he told me.
He was worried if it is right.
He wanted my opinion.
I told him it is impossible.
Natürlich!
Natürlich! How could you?
Hugo particularly asked us
not to talk about it.
He had no right to ask that.
- Ernst Gerhardt is a traitor!
- But we promised.
What did she say?
You wouldn't smuggle money into
Sing Sing for a murderer, would you?
- This is different.
- Yes!
This is noch schlimmer.
Even worse.
But lots of people send money to their
friends in concentration camps all the time.
- What's wrong about it?
- It can get us all into trouble.
- You want to sell the factory, don't you?
- Be sensible, darling.
Ernst Gerhardt is an enemy of Germany.
Who helps him is an enemy also.
- He was just a philisopher.
- He was against the government.
- He said we shouldn't have burned the books.
- And that Hitler is the same as Stalin.
Think of others beside yourself.
Of Erich. He's German.
Think of Ricky.
You wouldn't want to do anything
that would jeopardize him, would you?
Nonsense. You're just trying
to scare me.
But I don't care what you say.
I'm not going to be frightened.
I keep my promises.
Anyway, it's none of your business.
I'm going home.
Lass sie gehen.
Mommy!
- Mommy!
- Coming, Ricky!
- Darling.
- Mommy, Mommy!
I dreamed... I dreamed something awful!
Oh, a nightmare. I was afraid
you were sick.
- It was an awful dream.
- What was it, darling, what did you dream?
- I forget.
- Is he all right?
Oh, just a bad dream. But he's
all right now, aren't you, Ricky?
I want to sleep with you. Please, Mommy,
let me sleep in your bed.
- Don't be a cry baby.
- Oh, he's frightened.
- Poor little Ricky.
- That only encourages it.
- Sei ruhig. Schlafiets.
- Ja, Vater.
Don't forget, darling, the Lone Ranger
isn't afraid of dreams.
Now you go to sleep like
a good boy, won't you?
Yes, Mommy.
Too bad you aren't always
so concerned about Ricky.
You want to begin that again
about Gerhardt?
My wife is not going to make
a fool of herself...
...and get us all into trouble,
that's final.
Why didn't you tell me Frieda
was coming?
Can't she let you out of her sight
even for a couple of hours?
What have you got against
Frieda anyway?
There once was a Nordic named Frieda,
always quoting the words of the leader.
She wasn't born people say
in the usual way,
the Führer simply decreed her.
Where did you get that?
Out of my head, dear,
I'm clever that way.
Why don't you admit it?
You're jealous.
Oh, doesn't that make you
smug and lovely?
Because of her looks, I mean.
Because hers don't come out of a jar.
- As you said!
- Did you think I meant that?
If you didn't mean it,
why did you say it?
To flatter her, silly, I wanted her
to like me, but...
right away she makes cracks and starts
saying things to you in German...
...so I can't understand.
We've never said a single word in German
you could have any objections to.
- Now, isn't that a comfort.
- Would you prefer we had?
I'd prefer not to have my husband...
...reassure me he hasn't been making love
to another woman right in front of my eyes.
Good grief, what do you want?
Methinks the fellow doth
protest too much.
I give up.
Darling, let's not fight.
So silly.
As if we didn't love each other.
I hate to be mad. It always does
something to me inside.
I'm sorry if I was mean, but...
You were so bossy, and I can't
stand being bossed.
Please, won't you try to understand
my viewpoint and...
I'll try to understand yours.
Listen, Herr Hoffman, the lady's
talking to you.
Crying?
What do you think, gargling?
I'm sorry, Coco.
- Let's get better.
- It's about time.
The boss, who do you mean, Nick?
He's in London.
I'm running the show now.
Sure, where have you been for the past
six months, don't you read the papers?
I'm special correspondent in Berlin,
that's me.
I've even started to write my first book.
Okay, boy, I'll see you.
My friends don't take me very
seriously yet, but don't worry.
The nazis will do anything for a big
American news agency.
They want to be sure and include us
out of the next war.
Kenneth Delane speaking.
No, I didn't understand it that way.
The embassy is acting unofficially.
It hasn't issued any formal order for
Americans to get out of the country.
It merely suggests that if they haven't
any urgent business here,
it'd be very smart to go.
That's right.
What is it now?
Oh, no, no thanks.
Not this afternoon.
The little man with the moustache
has ruined my putting stroke.
Some other time, boy, huh?
Say, cut off all these phones,
will you, honey?
Yeah, I'm right in the middle
of a very important conference.
Now!
Would you mind telling me
where you got that hat?
That's the first time I've ever been
called a conference.
Don't mind if I seem to be staring
at you because I'm just...
Just staring at you.
Gosh, it's been months, and months,
and months...
...since I've seen a smart-looking
American woman.
Oh, I'm not really smart, just
sort of Lexington Avenue.
Oh, no, my homing instinct
is unerring.
You are the breath, the glamor, the lovely
odor of Fifth and 42nd on a late afternoon.
Oh, dear, I thought I was at least
Madison and the 50s at shopping time.
- You must have been away a long time.
- Yeah, a century.
Five years, in fact. Three in London
and two here.
Say, tell me. Do they still sell hamburgers
and ice-cream sodas in America?
- Hm-hmm.
- Yeah? Do you like them?
- Mad about them.
- We are going to get along.
Well, what with the world coming
apart at the seams...
...it's pleasant sometimes to ponder the
relative merits of hamburgers and sodas.
Is there really going to be a war?
Well, Schicky...
That's Hitler. Schicklegruber
was his father's name.
Schicky's due to throw another convulsion
at the Nazi Congress in Nuremberg.
And that may be a signal for the German Army
to march into the Sudetenland.
If that happens, the Czechs will fight.
My advice to you is not to wait and see.
I can't leave until my husband
sells the factory.
Oh, your husband. I forgot,
he's German, isn't he?
And now as to your question.
No, there won't be the slightest trouble
about delivering that money...
to your friend in the concentration camp...
...because that is one way the nazis have
of getting their hands on the loot,
foreign currency, that is.
- You mean they take it away from him?
- You keep some of the money yourself.
Let the people he bribes know
that they'll get the rest...
...as soon as he's safely
out of the country.
That's the way it's done.
- What's his name?
- Ernst Gerhardt.
Gerhardt. Oh, Professor Gerhardt
of Berlin University.
Uh-huh.
I filed a story on him just
a couple of weeks ago.
Story?
- Was he a very close friend of yours?
- We know his brother in New York, why?
Hm... he's dead.
- Dead?
- Hm-hmm.
The commanding officer of the
Schutzstaffel Headquarters...
...told me that Ernst Gerhardt died
in Dachau of acute appendicitis.
Poor Hugo.
Was it in the papers? I'm sure
my husband would have seen it.
Well, in the New York papers,
not here.
That's funny, I thought he was famous.
My lady of the ivory tower.
Honestly, I'd forgotten such
people existed.
Don't you read the papers?
What's the use of reading a lot of stuff
when you don't know what to believe?
Hm, my devoted public.
What are you going to do
with the money now?
Take it back to the doctor, I guess.
Professor Gerhardt's family might
find it very useful.
I haven't the faintest idea
where they live.
Oh, I think we can fix that.
Hello, get me Colonel Deckhart, please.
The Schutzstaffel and the Gestapo work
hand in hand, it's amazing what they know.
Hello, Herr Deckhart? This is Delane,
American correspondent, remember?
Yeah, I'm fine, fine, thanks.
Say, I'm just called up to get the address
of the widow of Ernst Gerhardt,
who you said died in Dachau
of appendicitis.
Not over the phone, well...
don't you recognize my voice?
Can't you check by ringing me back
here at the office?
Donald Duck.
Yeah.
Yes, I... I understand all about that,
Herr Deckhart,
but I don't think that you
appreciate the fact...
...that I have an American
gentleman in my office.
Yeah, a great industrialist.
I was just boasting to him about
the efficiency of your organization.
As a matter of fact,
I just made him a bet...
that you could give me the address
of anybody I named...
...within one minute after I
picked up the phone.
Oh, thanks, thanks very much.
Never fails to work.
There's nothing like landing on with a shovel
when you're dealing with the Heinies.
Look what Schicklegruber did with it.
Convinced them that they ought to rule
the world because they're blond Arians.
He forgets he's a little
on the dark side himself.
Ja!
Danke schön.
Waisenstrasse, 23.
Thanks.
Very much, thank you.
Come on, I'll drive you down there.
Oh, you're much too busy.
- Do you know how to speak German?
- Yes, danke schön.
Oh, no, that's not enough.
I can't let a beautiful woman
wander the streets of Berlin...
...when she doesn't even know
how to say no.
All right, I give up.
I like having it laid on
with a shovel too.
Can't you make them
get out of the way?
It doesn't do to irritate Storm
Troopers on the loose.
Well what's going on?
Nicht weinen. Nicht weinen, kleinen.
I don't get it.
It's the Brown-shirt blitzkrieg against
old people and kids.
Jews?
No, in this instance they're Czechs.
There's quite a few of them
live down in this quarter.
You see that garbage truck?
The bully boys bring their own filth,
dump it, then make the Czechs
clean it up.
It's a charming little passtime.
Why don't the police stop it?
Only one man can stop this
sort of thing.
He invented it.
They let him go.
He said he wanted to change
his clothes.
He told him the suit he had on
was the only good one he had...
...and if he got it dirty, he'd lose his job,
so they told him to go and change.
You'd think they'd be afraid
he'd get away.
Oh, no, he knows that they'd only
get him in the long run.
It would make it worse for him.
Ich bin ein amerikanischer Journalist
What's so funny?
Stop talking to him.
Don't look so glum.
I just told him that you said
the Czechs are barbarians...
...and ate with their fingers anyway.
- You didn't!
- Smile, little lady, and keep on smiling.
Verlasse die armen Leute
Schweine! Tschechisch!
Ja.
I'll never forget it, never.
Perhaps I should have got you
out of there sooner,
but I wanted you to see
with your own eyes.
I gather you're one of those people who
pride themselves on being fair to the nazis.
No, I just try to discount propaganda.
That just means that you've swallowed
Doktor Goebbels hook line and sinker.
That's Gobblegobble's favorite trick,
making people discount facts.
Zu viel um den valuta.
My English is so little,
gnädige frau.
But my heart thanks you.
I'm sure Hugo would want you to come
to America where he can take care of you.
I may be able to get you a visa.
No, I stay.
But Joachim will go, he will be happy.
- Is that your son?
- Yes, my son.
Joachim Gerhardt was one
of the top surgeons here.
- Was?
- Yes.
Naturally, he loses his position
at the hospital...
and his practice too...
...when it is known his father
is in Dachau.
Why can't you both come to America?
If that's not enough money,
I'm sure that...
It is not the money.
I cannot leave Ernst.
He is dead, of course.
But for 40 years
we were never separated.
Soon we will be together again
in German earth.
Some day beautiful things will grow
in Germany again.
And we will be a part of them.
I understand.
I'll tell Hugo.
I'm afraid I'll have to be getting
back to the office.
You will not stay and see Joachim?
He is for a walk. He will not be long.
I wish we could, but I must
be getting back too.
No one knows where I am.
You are sweet, my dear,
to come and see me.
- And brave.
- Just stubborn, I'm afraid.
Oh, what lovely work.
Do you do it?
No, Joachim makes it.
You are surprised because
he is a man?
- It's so delicate.
- His hands are used to delicate work.
He does it to keep his fingers from
becoming stiff and clumsy...
...so that he can operate
properly again someday.
It's really very beautiful work.
Well, auf wiedersehen, liebe Frau.
- Auf wiedersehen.
The Schutzstaffel, what do they
say about Ernst?
How he dies.
They told me he died of
acute appendicitis.
So.
Mein Mann hatte eine
Blinddarmoperation gehäpt...
...vor zwanzig Jahren.
- Auf wiedersehen.
- Auf wiedersehen, my friends.
What did she say?
Oh, it's more propaganda, my dear.
She says her husband had his
appendix out twenty years ago.
What do you expect, soft music?
This is a revolution. Certainly a few
people get pushed around.
The nazis were doing it for fun!
If you could have seen them.
It's nothing to what the Czechs have
been doing to the Sudeten Germans.
Anyway, you can't build a new world
without a few people running wild.
It wasn't just mob violence,
I could understand that.
But they went about it in such
a methodical, disciplined way.
It was horrible!
That's their new world.
Why don't you look at the good side,
what they are accomplishing?
These! You know what they
are made of?
- They look like flannel.
- Wood fiber.
Well, I've seen dresses made
out of glass at home.
In our factory we are using grease
made of lumber by-product!
You have seen buna.
It's better than rubber.
And now they've even found a way
of turning whale oil into butter.
Eww, I'm glad I'm reducing.
Look at the roads and factories
they've built. Laugh them off!
Not to mention all the nice, shiny
airplanes, tanks and guns.
Always that pacifist pat.
She's got you talking just
like Schicklegruber.
- Like what?
- Schicklegruber.
Where did you pick that up?
It was his father's name.
Don't you love it?
- Not so loud, will you?
- Nobody can hear us.
It's all very fine your sounding off.
But I haven't got an American passport.
It's not very funny to me.
Oh, darling let's get out of this firetrap.
I want to go home.
How much longer do we have
to stay here?
Give me some time. I've had
one offer already.
An offer? How much?
- Two hundred thousand marcs.
- Oh, darling, that's wonderful.
- Then we can go right away.
- If I take it.
If you take it?
Erich!
It's silly to take the first proposition.
If Markheim is interested,
others will be.
Maybe I can get another fifty
thousand marks.
What do you care about another
fifty thousand?
Your father will have enough
without it.
I'm afraid you're scarcely the one
to judge, my dear.
Oh, darling, you know I'm crazy
about your father.
I wouldn't have said that if he
hadn't said that all he needs...
...is ten thousand marks a year.
Four hundred thousand is enough
for forty years.
I have to think of Ricky,
it will be his someday.
Ricky will never get it. You know you can't
take money out of Germany.
I'm just as anxious to get it
settled as you are.
But I have to do it my way.
Oh, darling. Can't we at least
go away for a few days?
Just the three of us.
You said you'd take us
to Munich, and Dresden, and...
...that little town in the mountains.
Well... you and Ricky can go if you like,
but I can't go away now.
Right when things are popping.
Aren't you going to wait for me?
I have to go out to dinner.
I told you.
- Oh, yes, the Party officials.
- Yes.
A word in the right place may
make all the difference...
...in getting the government's
okay on the sale.
- Is Frieda going to be there?
- Naturally.
Without her I'd never
have been able to meet them.
Any objections?
By the way, I wouldn't go around saying
Schicklegruber if I were you.
It happens to be against the law
to make fun of the Führer.
What can he do? Sue me for libel?
Besides other things,
it's grounds for divorce.
Good night, Coco.
Good night.
- Yes, ja?
- It's Carol, Father.
Ah, come here, lieblich.
- What troubles you?
- Nothing, I... I just can't sleep.
For several days you don't
look so good.
- Are you ill?
- So hot and still.
It's as if everything, the whole world
were holding its breath.
It does.
How can anyone breathe until
we know is it war?
Erich says no.
I hope yes.
You want war?
It is one way, perhaps the only way,
to make an end of these lunatics...
...who spread fear and hatred
over the world.
Listen.
Soldiers.
What goes on?
Where are they all going?
To the border.
Always to another border.
Father, didn't you say the Friehofs
lived next door?
Yes, why?
Somebody's hurt.
I'm going down to see.
No, don't go, you'd better not!
- Oh, Vater.
- Shh!
Stille, stille, sie können dich hören.
Can I help?
Oh, don't be frightened, Herr Friehof.
I'm Erich Hoffman's wife.
The American, yes, I have seen you.
Please, you do not see anything,
you know nothing, go away!
- But he's hurt.
- Yes, this is my son.
He escaped tonight from the police
while they take him to Dachau.
They will be here soon to look for him.
Now go, quick, or they find you too.
- What are you going to do with him?
- I will hide him in the bushes.
He's too week to go farther tonight.
- He loses much blood.
- Lift him, hurry.
Polizei!
Im garten, schnell!
- Was ist los?
- Zu in garten
Mein Vater versteckt meinen Bruder
im Gebüsch, schnell!
- Who's that?
- My other son.
He betrays his own mother.
Quick, run!
- No, it's too late.
- No, no, run, run...
I'm sorry this makes trouble for you.
But God bless you.
They can't do anything to me!
I'm an American.
I want to see a lawyer.
But this is not America, Frau Hoffman.
I'm a friend of Kenneth Delane,
the American newspaper correspondent.
You are the wife of a German
citizen, Frau Hoffman.
But I don't know anything, I tell you.
I've never seen either of them before.
Hm?
You help to hide a man
you do not know?
Certainly, he was hurt.
And of course he does not mention
that others escaped with him.
Or say where they went.
- He never spoke a word.
- Hm.
He didn't! I don't know anything,
really I don't.
Anyway, why ask me,
why not ask them?
Oh, thank you!
That is very intelligent!
But I'm afraid it doesn't serve.
The boy died during the night
of his wounds.
And his father had an
unfortunate accident... in his cell.
So you see, gnädige frau.
Excuse, please.
So.
Herr Delane is outside.
On other business.
Ja!
Yavol.
Hallo!
Ja... Herr Deckhart.
He doesn't appear to know you.
- Ja...
- Kenneth, it's Carol!
Quick, help me!
Hallo.
Hallo?
He's gone.
That was very foolish of you.
He did not hear you at all.
- Heil Hitler!
What do you mean you were just
going to let her go?
You told me over the phone you didn't
know anything about her!
- I'm so sorry.
- Yeah.
Doktor Goebbels is going to hear
about this from me.
Yes, of course, that's understood.
- Come on, Carol you're free.
- Good old U.S. marines.
They didn't hurt you, did they?
- Mind if I hang on?
- No, grab a hold.
Erich!
Oh, darling!
- Is everything okay?
- Officially it was a mistake.
Free! Free as the air!
- Okay, let's not make a scene here.
- Aren't you glad to see me?
Of course, but it won't do
either of us any good...
...to have people know we have been
in trouble with them.
- Is that why you stayed out here?
- Naturally.
Naturally? Well, nothing like being
honest, I always say.
Don't mind if I seem a little gregarious,
it's the herding instinct.
Mass demonstrations in the streets
of Prague tonight...
...are protesting against acceptance
of the Hitler terms.
The Czech cabinet has resigned.
The new cabinet, headed by the
one-eyed hero, General Syrovy,
is expected to resist.
Monsieur Chamberlain prend l'avion
pour Godesburg...
...pour conférer avec Monsieur Hitler.
The Czechs have completely mobilized.
Hier huite hommes ont été tués...
...et des autres blaissés
dans le pays Sudètes.
In a note handed to Lord Halifax,
General Syrovy rejected the
German demands.
Speaking for the American people
in a personal plea for peace.
And now for the news in English.
The leader speaks tonight to the whole
world at the Berlin Sports Palace.
Hitler! Hitler!
Erich!
- Erich!
- Frieda!
They're going to the Kohlgarten for beer.
They want us to go.
Oh, I've had about all I can take
for one night, but you go if you want to.
Don't be a dope, you'll never see
another night like this!
I hope you're right!
The yelling!
My head feels as though
a riveter had moved in.
You hear what she says.
You come, she doesn't want to.
Okay, don't wait up for me.
Hiya, lady! Want a lift?
Hurry it up!
I had to be on the phone with
the Paris office right now.
Manhattan transfer, everybody out.
We've been married eight years.
And suddenly he seems a stranger.
Standing there with his hand up
like a mechanical doll screaming.
I've seen men go mad at football
games but nothing like that.
He looked as if he were going to pop.
Yeah, it's convulsions of the ego.
But I don't understand it.
They catch it from Schicky.
Erich's not the hysterical type.
In New York he was always
sweet and gentle.
He's never been like this,
it doesn't make sense.
In America we go in for other kinds
of quacks, thank heaven.
Sometimes they are pretty silly,
we worship...
...glamour girls, and healers
and quarterbacks.
But we can still laugh at ourselves.
These poor boys over here lost their
sense of humor, if they ever had any.
And any nation that doesn't know
how to laugh is dangerous.
What I can't get through my head
is why these people listen to Hitler.
When they know in the end it'll
only mean bloodshed and chaos.
Well, Schicky sold them a gold brick.
Probably the greatest gold brick that's
ever been sold to any peoples...
...in the whole history of time.
He's actually made them believe that...
...the only culture in the world
is the nazi culture,
that the only form of life
worth living is the nazi form.
He's a master magician.
Fanatical, egomaniacal, with the greatest
appetite for power...
...ever seen on this earth
since the days of... Genghis Khan.
Attila the Hun.
He won't be satisfied until
he makes an effort...
...to wipe the democracies right
off the map.
And I don't mean just England
and France either. Yeah, I know, I know.
A lot of us Americans laugh it off when
we hear things like this but not me.
I've seen too much.
I've seen the war machine
he's constructed.
And nobody can tell me he has
the slightest intention...
...of letting that machine go to rust.
In the long run of course
he won't win, but...
before he's through...
Schicky's going to spill an awful
lot of blood.
If I could only get Erich back
to New York...
He'd get over all this.
I'm sure he would.
Wouldn't he?
He would too.
- Well, can't you say anything?
- Yeah. Good night.
Hadn't you better take
your socks off?
Huh?
I didn't see you were awake.
I wasn't even going to speak to you,
but since you only got tight.
Who's tight?
I've been lying awake worried
about you since two o'clock.
The beer halls have been
closed for hours.
So what?
Where were you all this time?
Erich?
I saw you coming across the lawn
from Frieda's just now.
You and Otto.
I wasn't spying.
I got up to take a look at Ricky and just
happened to look out his window.
All right, I was at Frieda's,
what does that prove?
Don't you think it's a little late
to be coming home...
...from a woman's house carrying
your shoes?
Particularly a woman who's been
on the prowl for you for weeks?
Erich, darling, I don't care
about Frieda. Not really.
Those things just happen to people,
I understand that.
Let's forget about it and I promise
never to mention it again.
But Erich, won't you please take
Ricky and me away somewhere?
Dresden, the mountains, anywhere,
until we can go back home.
Won't you please, Erich?
All right, since you asked for it,
you might as well know now.
I'm not going back to America.
I've decided to stay here
and run the factory.
- For how long?
- Permanently.
You expect me to live here
the rest of my life?
Well, if you don't like it here,
I don't want to make you stay.
Meaning you want me to go away
and leave you here alone?
I want us both to be happy.
But you were happy in New York.
You always said you were.
We had lovely times together,
we can again.
That wasn't me in America,
not really me.
I found that out.
Just hearing Hitler tonight?
What are you, a holy roller?
Can any cheap demagogue make you
roll over and froth at the mouth?
I made up my mind a week ago.
- I joined the Party then.
- The nazis?
- What other party is there?
- Frieda made you do it.
Oh, Erich, how could you?
Did you have to give her your mind,
your will, everything?
- She had nothing to do with it.
- It works while you sleep, like medicine.
Skip it!
You aren't in love with her, are you?
She's a German and so am I.
- You want to marry her?
- Naturally.
Then I... I suppose you want
a divorce.
I guess that's the only solution.
She can't do that to me.
Oh, Erich, this isn't you,
she's just got you all mixed up.
I won't give you a divorce.
Very well, I'll divorce you.
On what grounds? You couldn't.
You ridiculed the Führer. Otto heard you
that night, he was in the hall.
He told Frieda, he'll corroborate
my testimony.
Very well, if that's what
you really want.
Go ahead and get your divorce.
I'll leave for New York this morning.
I'm sorry.
Do me one favor, will you?
Don't say anything to Ricky. Just...
just say you have to stay here on business.
I'll explain it to him some time later.
You can trust me to be fair.
Ricky's staying here with me.
Don't be silly, Erich, a child always
goes with his mother!
Not that I'd mind for a few months
at a time when he's a little older.
He belongs here.
He's a German under the law!
He is not! He's an American!
You can't make a nazi out of Ricky,
I won't let you!
He belongs to me! Any civilized court
anywhere in the world would...
What do you know about courts?
Do you think any nazi judge will let you
take a Party member's child away?
I know what I'm talking about.
I've consulted lawyers.
Lawyers? You planned all this?
- Where do you think you're going?
- To consult a few people myself.
At this hour?
I can't stand being in the same room
with you another minute.
I don't even want to breathe
the same air you breathe.
Heil Heel!
Well, there's only one thing to do.
You and Ricky have got to get
out of Germany today.
This afternoon. Without Erich's
knowing anything about it.
But how possibly?
First get Ricky out of the house
on some excuse. Take him for a walk.
I'll meet you in the park near
your home with my car.
And don't bring anything with you, see,
just your passport.
You're travelling on a separate
passport, aren't you?
- Yes.
- Well, that's perfect now.
Leave the rest to me.
Just give me a couple of hours.
Let's see, it's 9:15.
Meet me at 11:30, just inside
the park entrance.
I'll have your train, plane tickets,
your boat reservations,
some luggage and clothes.
Enough to get you to Paris anyhow.
And before Erich wakes up
to what's happening,
you'll be clean across the border.
You don't mind flying, do you?
I'd crawl on my hands and knees
to get Ricky out of here.
I don't know how to thank you.
Don't try.
Oh, incidentally, er...
I expect to be in New York by January.
I'm, er... I'm gonna take charge
of a special cable desk...
...they're setting up in case of war.
- Will you like that?
- Oh...
New York will look awfully good
to me right now.
Say, I forgot.
You'll need some cash, won't you?
How about 200?
That'll keep you going until you get in touch
with your friends in New York, won't it?
- Oh, you're very generous.
- Well, it has been a pleasure.
What I really mean is, you're swell.
Thanks.
- Where are we going, Mommy?
- For a walk, dear, just for a walk.
Why?
- Hold still, darling, Mommy's in a hurry.
- Why?
- Don't ask so many questions.
- There.
- Carol!
Yes?
- Where are you taking Ricky?
- To the park just for a little while.
But I want him to go downtown with me.
As soon as Frieda and I finish
talking with Father.
Do you begrudge my last
few minutes with him?
You said you are not leaving
until tonight.
- I'll have him back by four.
- No, I want him now.
Go on upstairs until I call you.
- Mommy.
- Erich, please.
- Geh schon!
- Ja, Vater.
Father wants to see you.
Ja...
Ja.
Thank you that you come.
Sit down, lieblich.
Erich tells me you leave
Berlin tonight.
Yes, I... we... it seemed best.
I understand.
I heard everything.
We are not ashamed of our love.
Ja.
- You don't take Ricky with you?
- He's staying with me.
That is your wish?
No, no, of course it isn't.
But Erich says I can't have him.
You try to take a child away
from his own mother?
You cannot.
A child belongs to the state now.
- Belongs first to his mother.
- That isn't the law.
It is the law of nature!
To hang by our tail from the trees
was once a natural law.
The world changes whether you
old men like it or not.
Yes, I am old, that is true.
But I am not yet dead.
And so long as I live, I do not
permit you to do this, Erich.
I don't want to discuss it.
Do you not injure enough of us?
Must you destroy your own son?
Destroy? It will make a man of him,
a real man!
Instead of a sponge.
Erich, ten years you are away.
You are still my son.
Still you hear my voice, no?
Is there not deep inside...
...any feeling of the small boy
I used to know?
He cannot be dead, only sleeping,
nicht wahr?
That warm-hearted,
intelligent boy that used to sit
on the arm of my chair...
...while I read to him from Schiller,
Goethe and Thomas Mann.
Always the same sentimental dreck.
When people talk of the old Germany,
it's always about books,
and music, and painting.
Life was gemütlich then.
What did it matter that we'd been
surrounded by enemies,
robbed of our living space?
Everything was gemütlich.
Let the Fatherland die
so long as it dies charmingly.
Please, Erich, my son, take
this woman if you insist.
Follow your leader!
Your antichrist who steals from us
everything that makes life worthwhile.
But do not chain your own
child in this jungle.
Making of him an animal
like all the others.
Allow him to go to America so he can
grow up to be a human being,
not a beast knowing only to tear others
apart in the name of survival!
No.
Was ist deine Antwort, mein Sohn?
Nein!
I told you I've made up my mind.
It's final.
So.
Ach so.
Wait, please.
- One more thing.
- I must hurry. Be quick.
You are not in such a hurry you would not
do well to listen to what I have to say.
Power, force.
That is all you respect.
You make me use it, Erich.
If you do not allow Ricky
to leave tonight...
...for America with his mother,
tomorrow I go to the nazis...
and tell them that your mother...
...was a Jewess.
Proof, yes. I give it to them.
Your mother came from Belgium,
as you know.
We were married there.
The record still exists.
They show she was a full Jewess.
The night the Reichstag burned,
I went to Brussels...
I could guess what was going
to happen here.
It was easy to pay for fake documents
saying she was an Arian.
But the original records are
still there...
...for anyone to see.
Was kann ich tun?
Du bist ein Jude.
Nein. I can't be.
I'd know it. I'd feel it.
Frieda!
Liebling.
You will suffer much, my son.
But from it you will learn what
you would have done to others.
Poor Erich.
I wish I could help you, but...
I'm all dead inside.
I can't even feel sorry for you.
Oh, Erich, can't you see, that's what
this sort of thing does to people.
All this hating and grabbing
what you want.
It kills everything worthwhile.
All feeling.
Love.
Jude.
Don't forget. I'm looking forward
to seeing you in New York.
- I'm afraid that won't be possible.
- What do you mean?
The Home Office has changed my orders.
I'm to stay here now.
- For how long?
- For the duration.
Oh.
You can do me a great big favor, though.
- What?
- You know that little drugstore...
...in the corner of er... 50th and Madison?
Drop in there sometime.
Order a hamburger and a chocolate
ice-cream soda.
And when you do, you think
of me, will you?
- I will.
- Goodbye.
- Bye-bye, Ricky.
- Bye.
Goodbye.
Subtitles: Luís Filipe Bernardes