This is Britain,
where we believe in freedom.
For over 800 years, we have
kept our shores safe from invaders.
And for 800 years,
we have opposed every dictator
who arose and tried to enslave Europe.
For this is Britain,
where we believe in freedom.
We also believe in peace -
peace to develop our inheritance.
This was the Britain we inherited
from the Industrial Revolution.
And this is the sort of Britain we have been
trying to build during the years of peace.
A new Britain in which every one of us
might have a home of which he was proud.
A gigantic task we undertook, to rehouse
the urban population in well-built,
well-lighted, well-ventilated flats,
to replace the tumbledown slums of the past.
In new settlements of neat houses
with gardens -
pleasant to look at,
delightful to live in, easy to work.
We had no use for war.
We had no designs on others.
Our only enemies
were the common enemies of mankind -
poverty, bad conditions,
the rigours of the northern
climate, disease.
And we had them on the run.
It seemed to be the
beginning of a new age.
And is it to stop because one man chooses to
try and force his outworn ideas on Europe?
A Britain of new factories
as well as new homes,
where people can work
in healthy surroundings.
A Britain of new schools, where our sons
and daughters are equipped for life,
and taught to be good citizens of
their country and of the world.
In which the importance of physical health
and clean living are taught.
In the old days at school, they used to
tell you "mens sana in corpore sano".
It used to be mumbled to boys
who didn't know what it meant
by old men who
didn't mean what it said.
Nowadays, we say you can't enjoy life
or pull your weight if you're ill.
The consequence is,
we all try to keep well and
everybody's better off all round.
Even schoolteachers
have become human.
They realised that children
had a right to be happy,
that the youthful mind
was a delicate instrument
to be trained for the
future good of all.
Is this to stop because one man
wishes to dominate the world?
A Britain of new hospitals,
where disease can be prevented
as well as cured.
Where the old atmosphere of gloom
and ignorance has vanished.
Even very little people
can enjoy their cure.
Nowadays, it's quite a pleasant adventure
to be listened to with a stethoscope.
And here's somebody
taking the waters.
A Britain of new infant schools
and welfare centres,
where busy mothers
can leave their children while they work.
Where the children themselves learn
to become busy mothers - no, fathers.
This ridiculous modern
craze for washing.
A new Britain, where leisure and pleasant
surroundings in which to enjoy leisure
plays an increasingly important part
in everyday life.
For we believe that when
the day's work is done,
or when bank holidays come round,
life is meant to be enjoyed by all.
We were trying to make it possible
for everybody to have the means
to enjoy it in their own way.
Holidays with pay for all,
when those in towns
can get away to the coast
and refresh themselves
in sunshine and sea air.
Or at weekends can get out into the
country, play games, go swimming.
We think this is a life worth living.
Are we to lose it because one man
seeks to destroy civilisation?
Better conditions have brought an enormous
improvement in our national physique.
Our enemies sneer at us.
They say we are effete and decadent.
A characteristically unfortunate lie,
as they will find to their cost.
Though we have our champions,
we don't claim to lead the
world in athletic records.
We think it more important that
people should get enjoyment
from their favourite exercise -
rowing, running, jumping.
Or in Scotland, throwing heavy things about
in a way only Scotsmen can understand.
Apart from tossing the caber,
there is nothing unusual in all this.
We have long made up our minds
to use our bodies for games and sports,
not for building up vast armies
with which to terrorise
and subdue our weaker neighbours.
We like to win matches, not wars.
Although, if we must have wars,
we can win those too.
But unfortunately,
the new spirit was not universal.
While we played, or swam,
or cycled or walked...
others preferred to march.
While our young men
fought friendly battles,
they marched in
grim regimented hordes,
stirred by false ideals,
inspired by the blatant
trumpet of power.
They were soaked in the creed of force
with its black and sinister emblem,
while we practised good fellowship.
# Waltz
They spent their days
in mechanical stepping,
before a leader
whom they worshipped as a god.
He gave them the choice of guns or butter,
and he made them choose the guns.
Still the youth of Britain
preferred the arts of peace.
Still it was our public choice
to watch football or go racing.
Still the chief use for
our horses was exercise,
not to carry cavalry.
Still we believed that
the best government
was that which allowed the
maximum freedom to the individual.
The Nazi system crushes the individual.
Are these men,
or is this dipping day on the sheep farm?
What is your idea of a holiday?
This?
Or this?
Would you rather hear
this going on...
I've got a horse'.
..or this?
The most wonderful race of the year...
..in den gar nichts nutzen,
denn sie können ja kaufen.
The sport of kings
has tied you in a knot.
Foxglove!
..wenn ihr Geld haben,
da hechte man uns!
4-1 to win, 8-1...
..dann könnten wir heute kaufen...
..Feuer ausplündern sollen...
Bet with the man with the whiskers.
..sind wir auch,
dass wir kaufen können...
The best money can buy. Lovely food.
Accommodation!
What is your idea of a ruler?
A man who must be protected
by armed guards like this?
Or a man who need not fear
to walk freely, like this?
# Oh, how happy I should be
# Under the...
# If I...
# On my...
The funny part about this song is,
the more you do it, the harder it gets.
# If I...
# On my...
# On my knee...
# Oh, how happy I should be
# Under the...
When Hitler came to power,
he publicly stated his position.
In his speech of June 1st, 1933,
he referred to the past war
in the following terms:
"Another outbreak of
such a crisis of madness
would necessarily involve the destruction
of society and the public order."
...verblieben and Wachen zu zerstören.
Wenn die anliegenden Nationen eben so
rechtlos das Gleiche tun.
He gave his word that
he would uphold the Locarno Treaty.
Yeton March 7th, 1934,
he broke the Locarno Treaty.
He sent the German Army
into the Rhineland.
All Europe was deeply stirred.
But Hitler hastened
to set fears atrest.
In his honourable
open fashion, he said,
"We shall strive for an understanding
between European peoples.
We have no territorial demands
to make in Europe."
As his own people listened to him,
was there the seed of doubt?
Europe was reassured.
What of the Austrian chancellor?
..und seine Ehre zu wahren wusste.
Goodbye.
Hitler had no territorial
demands to make.
Notin Austria?
And Hitler gave the answer
in his honourable open fashion,
on May 21, 1935.
"Germany neither intends nor wishes to
interfere in the internal
affairs of Austria,
or to conclude an Anschluss."
A year later, Hitler signed
an agreement with Austria
guaranteeing the complete sovereignty
of the Viennese government.
Chancellor Schussnig
followed Dr Dollfuss.
But Hitler summoned him to
Berchtesgaden to be threatened.
The system of
power politics was working.
On March 12th, 1938,
thus went Austria.
With Austria gone,
Czechoslovakia was in the wolf-like jaws
of the new boundaries of Germany.
The tactics that had crushed Austria
were used again.
Hitler declared that by 1st October
he must have the territory occupied by
the Sudeten Germans in Czechoslovakia.
Thus went Sudetenland.
# Horst Wessel Song
It went all the more easily because
on 27th September, 1938, he had said:
"If this problem is solved,
there will be no further territorial
demands in Europe by Germany.
We do not want any Czechs."
The Munich Agreement was signed.
The Sudetenland went back to Germany,
and Hitler guaranteed the integrity
of the rest of Czechoslovakia.
Buton March 15th, 1939,
he broke his word again,
and annexed Bohemia and Moravia.
Thus went Czechoslovakia.
Who was next?
Next was Memel.
The German press cried out
that Memel was free.
They call it freedom.
By this time,
the world had ceased to believe
any of Hitler's honourable
open declarations.
For the real Hitler, turn to the
revealing pages of his book, Mein Kampf.
Read the story of his true ambition
in this, the Nazi gospel.
Page 754 tells you:
That is why Poland has been smashed.
And on page 742,
read why any power but Germany
should be smashed:
Hitler says he loves peace.
Buton page 315, he tells you
what kind of peace he loves:
So history repeats itself.
As in 1914, the world has no choice.
We remember the famous words
of Bethmann Hollweg.
The step taken by the British Government
is terrible to a degree.
Great Britain is going to make war
against a kindred nation
who desired nothing better
than to be friends with her.
Just for a word,
just for a... a scrap of paper.
Britain awoke.
It was clear that war
could not be avoided by negotiation.
Britain must be strong.
Hitler's real ambition lay naked
in the cold light of truth.
The German leader aimed at dominating
the whole of Europe,
and Britain must defend her freedom
once again.
Britain's navy in 1939 was still the
greatest navy the world had ever known.
The proud tradition of the army
is that it always wins the last battle.
And the introduction of compulsory service
added enormous reserves of manpower
to the efficient regulars of peacetime.
# The British Grenadiers
600 years of tradition
from Crécy to Compiègne
have covered the British
soldier with glory.
Add to that modern mechanisation.
British industry is second to none.
And in building up its new equipment
from anti-aircraft guns to tanks,
miracles have been accomplished
which amazed the world's military experts.
Our famous cavalry regiments employed
their qualities of dash and hard riding
in driving mobile forts
at ever-increasing speed.
Artillery was motor-drawn.
And infantry was no longer trained
merely to work on foot.
Speed in moving,
tremendous striking power.
And power where the deadly machine gun
largely took the place of the rifle.
And with the Regulars and the Militia
worked the Territorials -
a voluntary army of young men who gave
their leisure to their country's defence.
Young men who became a vital factor
in the gigantic war machine.
Then the youngest service
of them all.
In the war of 1914-1918,
the Royal Air Force grew
from a small experimental force
to become undisputed
masters of the sky.
Each following year,
the Hendon pageant of the Royal Air Force
demonstrated breathtaking skill
and parade-ground precision
in this new element of war.
So rapidly have we advanced,
that these pictures, taken two years ago
at the last Hendon air display,
are already out of date.
But what a story they tell of skill
and relentless striking power.
These people are becoming air-minded.
Yes, but not war-minded.
Hello, Schulenberg.
How do you like the show?
Marvellous.
- Wunderbar.
- What?
- Oh.
Germany might scoff.
These pictures are still
the old pictures,
but since that time the
Air Force has expanded
into the magnificent
service that it is today,
once again second to none.
Ready for anything,
no matter how difficult and dangerous.
Britain founded her
greatness on the sea.
The spirit of those great names of old
lives once more in those who dare
the uncharted heights of heaven -
Nelson, Drake, Frobisher, Raleigh.
The dauntless courage
that made them famous
is born anew
in these young captains of the clouds.
Swell. Gee, it's worth coming all the way
from little old Montreal to join these boys.
Here's your husband.
He ought to feel like a million dollars.
- Pleased, darling?
- So-so. Not bad.
Some of those new buses
are quite good.
- Schulenberg says it's wunderbar.
- Do you believe him?
Shouldn't wunder.
All honour to these pilots
and their crews.
And honour too to the ground staff.
For to their knowledge and
experience and devotion to duty,
the flying men trust their lives.
Every part of every machine
must be tuned to concert pitch,
and ready to bear the strain of battle
at six miles a minute.
They must never make a mistake.
Nor must the craftsmen
who make the machines.
We learned early in our history
to study our weapons as well as our men.
Crécy and Agincourt were won,
partly because the English archers
were the best in the world,
but partly also
because they carried the best bows.
So today into our fighters go the soundest
materials, the most careful workmanship.
In the construction of aircraft,
there are two policies.
You may decide to build
the best possible machine,
a machine to last its natural life
apart from the risk of war,
or you may calculate
what is the average life
of a machine in wartime
and build only to that.
The advantage of the second method
is that you economise,
both in materials and in labour.
"The aircraft," you say,
"is only likely to last for so many
flying hours before being shot down.
So why waste time and money
and good material and craftsmanship
to make it any better
than it probably need be?"
"Probably" - that is the test word.
"Probably" is not good enough
for our Air Ministry,
who have turned down
that specious policy and argument.
British pilots and crews shall
have only the finest aircraft
that our factories can produce.
The British Royal Air Force
shall never be let down by its aircraft.
As with the fighters,
so with the bombers.
Here you see the famous Wellingtons,
the type that wentouton the Kiel raid.
Designed on the remarkable
geodetic principle of construction,
they carry a formidable weight of bombs
for an immense distance at high speed.
They are manned by a crew of five -
pilot, navigator, wireless officer,
gunner and bomb aimer.
A corridor runs the
entire length of the aircraft.
The pilot is able to maintain contact
with the whole crew.
Great tasks have already been
carried out by these aircraft,
and there are more to come.
From aircraft to anti-aircraft guns.
The modern bomber cannot be compared
with that of 20 years ago.
But nor can the modern AA gun.
Guided by the modern searchlight,
by the new detectors and rangefinders,
their fire is truly formidable.
Shall we be short of material? No.
We have natural resources within our empire
that can scarcely be exhausted,
no matter how long the struggle.
The furnaces in our foundries will not die,
nor the lathes in the shops stop turning,
until there is no more need
for these weapons of defence.
At the beginning of the last war,
guns were starved of ammunition.
We have not made that mistake again.
Bombs - so many already in storage that
manufacture could almost be suspended.
Bombs - not for defenceless towns,
not to break the morale of
the civilian population,
but for military
and naval objectives,
to let frightfulness have
a taste of frightfulness.
Factory upon factory
feed the insatiable machine guns.
This is the strength of the nation -
bullets, guns, shells.
Bullets, guns, shells.
And production is expanding,
with a momentum that day by day increases,
until it reaches vast proportions
hitherto undreamed of.
For a long time now, Germany has been
producing war materials on a wartime scale.
Her administration has been intoxicated
by power of armaments.
Her national energy has been concentrated
on turning out the dreadful engines of war.
Such a programme over a period of peacetime
years could only show one result.
That long, dreary,
selfish road trodden by her rulers
could only lead her people
to bankruptcy and want.
But even in peacetime,
in the year that followed
the disillusionment
of Munich,
Britain was catching up.
Britain was overhauling
the Nazi production machine.
And Britain is now working up
towards a new peak.
We are fresh.
We come into this race that
was made necessary fit and confident.
Production has not yet grown stale
and begun to tire.
If it should be a long war,
if that forecast of a three-year
struggle should really come true,
it is not hard to calculate
which side will endure.
We have at our disposal resources
that far outstrip the German.
The wheels of their industry are
slowing down, ours are starting up.
On top of that,
we know that our cause is just.
Every man and woman
knows why we are fighting.
We have not been misled
by false promises.
We have not been tricked into a world
catastrophe by deceit and vanity...
and lies.
Not for us the terrible awakening that must
come sooner or later to the German people.
We hoped that reason might prevail.
But the fate that had overwhelmed Austria
and Czechoslovakia enveloped Poland too.
For two days we waited in suspense,
while the Prime Minister
made one last effort for peace.
He gave Germany until
11 o'clock on Sunday,
September 3rd,
to withdraw troops from Poland,
21 years after the end
of that "war to end war".
And then he spoke to the nation.
Up to the very last,
it would have been quite
possible to have arranged
a peaceful and honourable settlement
between Germany and Poland.
But Hitler would not have it.
He had evidently made up his mind
to attack Poland whatever happened.
We have a clear conscience.
We have done all that any country could do
to establish peace.
But a situation in which no word given
by Germany's ruler could be trusted,
and no people or country could feel
itself safe, had become intolerable.
At such a moment as this,
the assurances of support
which we have received from the Empire
are a source of profound
encouragement to us.
Now may God bless you all.
And may he defend the Right.
For it is evil things
that we shall be fighting against-
brute force, bad faith, injustice,
oppression and persecution.
And against them,
I am certain that the Right will prevail.
# National Anthem
What was that?
Are we at war?
The Prime Minister just broadcast.
Hm.
What did he say yesterday?
"To satisfy one man's vain,
senseless ambition."
He did his best to stop it,
if ever a man did.
- Yes.
- Now we're in it.
Well, I'm glad.
At least we know where we are.
What are you doing here, darling?
We're on our way to a new station.
We've only got one second.
Darling... are we ready?
Do you mean are we prepared?
We've never been better prepared.
Darling.
Good luck.
- Darling...
- Yes?
Let's get married when I get back.
Yes.
God bless you, my dear.
Come on, Bobby. We've got to go.
Goodbye, June.
Darling...
God bless you, darling.
- Goodbye.
- Bye.
Well...
- Air raid!
- Already?
First-aid post. Get your things quick.
I'll get the car.
So it began.
That first air raid was
a false alarm, but...
so it began.
All the filthy inhumanity of war.
Yes, whether we liked it
or not, it was war.
An unbelievable catastrophe
had visited this peaceful countryside.
But we were prepared.
Behind each bushy hedgerow,
a battleship of the skies stood ready.
Massive, forbidding,
deadly.
The symbol of modern power.
Waiting for the word to go.
And while pilots passed the time
waiting for orders to avenge
the outrage of the Athenia,
orders were on the way.
Bomber Command.
Yes, sir? Air Ministry here, sir.
Yes?
Check your time, will you?
Yes, that's right.
Zero hour, 19 hours.
Very good, sir.
No.1 group?
Operate zero hour, 1900.
No.2 group?
Zero hour, 1900.
Hanbury? You will commence Raid Table
No.1 at zero. Zero hour, 1900.
Great Milton? You will commence Raid Table
No.3 at zero plus ten. Zero hour, 1900.
Zero hour, 1900.
Right. Thanks.
- You heard that?
- Yes, sir.
- You've got all the information?
- Yes.
I expect you'd like
A-Flight for Raid No.1.
Yes.
And I suppose you'd like
your B-Flight for Raid No.2.
- Yes, sir.
- All right. Carry on.
Baron, can I have your pilots and
crews here in quarter of an hour?
- Right.
- Thank you.
Out of their lofty hangars came the
flights selected for a hazardous job.
Sky battleships armed and equipped
with all that military science
and technical skill could devise.
Messengers of havoc, yet it had not been
our will that sent them forth.
Inexhaustible supplies of petrol
the lifeblood of modern war.
Fewer cars and buses
on the home front.
More planes on the war front.
Millions of gallons of alcohol.
And not a hiccup in a tankful.
Fore and aft,
they carry machine guns.
Guns that spit out a double stream of
bullets, swifter than thought itself.
Next to go in is the complicated apparatus
for bomb-aiming.
For bombing now
is exact and mathematical.
Speed of flight,
strength of wind, altitude.
A hundred factors must be taken into account
before the pressure of a thumb
lets loose these tons
of roaring chaos.
With the utmost care and precision
they load up their cargo of destruction.
No mistakes - they don't want
any dropping out too soon.
Nor do we.
But even on a job
that carries a 50-50 chance of death,
these wonderful boys start out
with a light heart and a joke.
And pilots and crews
go in to receive their orders.
- All the people here?
- Yes.
- How many aircraft?
- A full six.
Right. Well, you're in luck.
No propaganda leaflets this time.
It's the real thing.
We've received information
that the German pocket battleships are
making towards the mouth of the Kiel Canal.
By the time you get there
they should be just inside.
Your job is to secure direct hits
on the battleships.
Six copies of your route
and weather forecast.
You cross the coast at Sheringham.
Fighter Command will be informed.
Change your course to 110 degrees.
From there on you can
expect air resistance.
Now your final course is 145 degrees
for those on target one.
121 degrees for those on target two.
You'll see here where
you're likely to encounter gunfire.
The red pins indicate
heavy anti-aircraft.
The black pins 2.7.
About ten miles from
your target is a hospital.
It's a large white building.
You can't possibly mistake it.
But you must get those battleships.
OK.
As you'll be over your objective in
daylight, I want cameras taken, of course.
Exact data of what we achieve
is particularly important.
Now... anything else?
There's just one thing.
I take it there's no balloon barrage there.
- Not if you stick to your route.
- Good.
Well... that's the lot.
- Good luck.
- Thank you.
- Good luck, boys.
- Thanks.
- What about our party tonight?
- What about tomorrow?
OK, make it tomorrow.
Captains of aircraft?
Your routes and forecasts.
Get your maps marked out.
You heard what was said.
We need direct hits.
The type of attack will
depend on local conditions,
but it will be low-level bombing.
I'll let you know in the air.
Stick to me if you can,
but if anybody gets lost...
he must make his way home independently
and dump his bombs in the sea.
Now, we'll be heavily loaded
so individual takeoffs, of course.
All happy about your machines?
- Yes.
- Good.
Carry on.
Engines throb and leap to life.
They start out for Kiel.
Raid No.1 airborne, sir.
Group Operations?
Raid No.1 airborne. Zero plus 32.
Fighter Command?
Our first raids have taken off.
Here are some details
for your plotting table.
Raid Table No.1.
Raid No.1 started at zero plus one.
Raid No.2, zero plus three.
They're heading east on
a great adventure.
The bow gunner ready
in the forward turret.
The navigator amidships busy at
his charts, plotting the course.
And in the tail, another gunner.
A solitary sentinel, protecting the ship
from attack from the rear.
But its a long time
before there's any excitement yet.
Except for the wireless operator.
See if you can pick up Mr Middleton.
It's vibrating a bit in the tail, sir.
May I rest up for a bit?
Wait a minute.
- Hello?
- Sir?
- What's our latest position?
- Half a mo.
About another hour at our present speed
before we change the course.
All right, Saunders.
Bill, take over for a minute, will you?
Anything doing?
Nothing from our side, sir.
Wireless silence was ordered.
Seems to be some activity from
German station AZ2 but it's all in code.
Saunders?
Back in the tail, half an hour.
They've been on their course now
for an hour of steady flying.
The sight of a ship below is a
welcome break in the monotony of sea.
Destroyer ahead, sir.
- Ours or theirs?
- Ours, I think.
Boring through the sky.
Getting close now.
Time to take up battle stations.
The pilot goes back to his controls.
Navigator now constantly
at his elbow.
Changing course in about five minutes.
Let me know.
Time for the rear gunner
to go back to the tail.
Bomb aimer leaves the forward gun.
Wireless operator goes forward.
No need for wireless now.
And he steps over the bomb aimer -
who crouches down getting
his sights lined up -
and he makes his way
to the gun turret.
Alter course to 110 degrees.
Going down to 100 feet
for the run-in to the coast.
Going in low to avoid the arches?
A bit of excitement down there.
- See that? The ship's crew's bathing.
- Can't have expected us.
There she is. Signal for line astern.
Right. Here we go.
Right.
Steady.
Bombs dropped.
Get him?
Good show. Now for home.
What's the course?
Step on it.
You have Messerschmitts on your tail.
The German pursuit planes
were shaken off.
The flight of bombers returned home.
They had dropped their bombs,
not upon unfortified towns,
buton a heavily-protected naval base.
A legitimate target of modern warfare.
An objective bristling with anti-aircraft
guns and guarded with fighters.
They came back to
their home aerodrome.
But not all came back.
But they had achieved
what they set out to do,
and they drew first blood of the war
that was none of their making.
It was an epic of the skies.
Carried out with brilliant dash
and matchless courage.
Although you watched a reconstruction
of that raid upon the Kiel Canal
the men you now see stepping out of these
bombers are the officers and men of the RAF,
who carried out that heroic raid.
These are the men who flew the planes and
dropped the bombs on Hitler's battleships.
We have seen how Britain can strike
when she chooses.
But we do not expect
to read of such exploits every day.
What is of constantinterestis to learn
how we can protect our own country
from undesirable visitors.
What is the organisation that exists
to counter and eventually to conquer
German bombing attacks?
Vast machines, fighters, interceptors,
pursuit planes, and of course, personnel.
There is no lack of men
for the machines.
Men who will prove themselves
worthy successors to the Great War aces.
Leefe-Robinson, and Ball and Bishop.
And leaders who have the confidence
of the rank and file.
And men of experience.
And a new form of defence
never before tried in warfare -
the balloon barrage.
A chain of blimps that
trail invisible steel wires.
Death to the invader.
The object of the balloon barrage
is to force enemy planes to a height
at which they can become a better target
for anti-aircraft fire.
Or an easier victim
for defending fighters.
Not only that,
accurate bombing becomes impossible.
Anti-aircraft guns.
The range and volume and rapidity of fire
of the latest guns are official secrets.
Closely guarded.
It is sufficient to know
they fling upward a hail
of metal that changes
the sky into an inferno.
Searchlights pierce the darkest corners
of the heavens.
Scientific equipment works out the height
and speed of approaching planes.
While at every point on our coast,
watchers are always on the lookout.
So, come to Berlin.
Let's be in at the start
as an order for a bombing raid
is rapped out by the
German Chief of Air Staff.
The Chief of the Nazi Bomber Group
hands on precise instructions
to a German bomber station.
Wenden Sie sich südwärts nach.
And the commanding officer of the
bomber station addresses his officers.
A striking contrast to the friendly
atmosphere that is Britain's way.
Haben Sie etwas?
Zu Befehl, Herr Oberst.
Danke, meine Herren. Heil Hitler!
Heil Hitler!
The necessary activity on the aerodrome
may be kept undercover.
But Britain too has undercover methods
of getting advance information.
- Har ni on tandstickor?
- What's that?
A match.
Oh, yes.
Activity at Pirate Squadron AZ2.
AZ2.
Code group - X74 479.
X74 479.
Right.
Air Ministry? Yes, sir.
- Here you are, for the old man.
- Right.
- Hello?
- Chief of Air Staff speaking.
I've just received information that
an enemy attack is expected tonight.
Raise your barrage.
Very good.
Somewhere in Britain,
its existence and communications
completely protected from the enemy,
is an organisation known
as Fighter Command.
It is in direct communication with the
Air Ministry and all defence units.
In supreme control
is the Air Officer Commanding-in-Chief.
He is the brain.
The whole of the rest of the organisation
are his nerves, his limbs, his fingers.
A large staff of telephonists
remains on duty night and day,
to receive reports as they come in
from every post in the country.
Observer posts
and all other sources of information.
Each individual section
of the Fighter Command
is in a separate soundproof compartment,
behind glass.
And spread in front of them all
on this huge table
is a map of the eastern half of Britain,
the North Sea and the German coast.
A message comes through
to the Air Officer C-in-C.
Chief of Air Staff, sir.
Yes?
I've just received information
an enemy attack is expected tonight.
- Tonight's the night.
- Get me No.1...
Yes, we're all ready.
- Your observer standing by?
- Just checking up, sir.
To think that for years I've been
wanting a darkroom for developing,
and now that every room
in the house is dark,
I'm stuck in the bushes
listening to the birds.
Listening for them, you mean.
Hello. Yes, sir.
Standing by.
They expect them tonight.
Observer's post.
Numbers 115 to 127 in readiness.
- All observers standing by, sir.
- ARP.
Stand by.
They're coming over tonight.
Anti-aircraft. We've just received news
that tonight's the night.
General call.
Very good, sir.
Boys, get your boots on and get ready
to give old Adolf a kick in the pants.
Yes, sir.
Stand by, boys, to welcome the Nasties.
- Northern Group standing by?
- Northern Group standing by, sir.
- Midland Group all set?
- Midland Group all set, sir.
- Southern Group all standing by?
- Southern Group all ready, sir.
Stand by, everyone. Stand by.
Back at Fighter Command...
..all is ready.
Almost hidden in the darkness,
the British fighters are waiting
for the word to take off.
Anti-aircraft batteries at the ready,
sound detectors strain
to hear the drone of enemy engines.
Searchlights stab the blackness
with a silver sword.
Britain - soldier and civilian -
stands on guard...
..as it was three and
a half centuries ago
when the proud Armada sailed
up the English Channel.
The Armada!
"Night sank upon the dusky beach,
and on the purple sea.
Such night in England ne'er had been,
nor e'er again shall be.
From Eddy stone to Berwick bounds,
from Lynn to Milford Bay,
that time of slumber
was as bright and busy as the day.
For swift to east and swift to west
the ghastly war-flame spread.
Then bugle's note and cannon's roar
the death-like silence broke.
And with one start,
and with one cry, the royal city woke.
And broader still became the blaze,
and louder still the din,
as fast from every village round
the horse came clattering in."
# Fanfare and drum roll
My people.
I am come to live
or die amongst you all.
To lay down for my God and
for my kingdom and for my people
my honour and my blood
even in the dust.
I know I have the body
of a weak and feeble woman,
but I have the heart
and valour of a king...
and of a King of England, too.
Not Spain, nor any prince of Europe shall
dare to invade the borders of my realm.
Pluck up your hearts.
By your peace in camp
and your valour in the field,
we shall shortly have
a famous victory.
Floor, sir. Floor.
First plot coming on the table, sir.
How many and at what height?
Eight...
..at 8,000...
ARP, warn London Area No.1.
Hold on a minute, ARP.
Wash out previous instructions.
Warn all areas.
- London, all areas.
Northern Group...
raids four and
five entering your sector.
Carry on and deal with them.
Midland Group, raid three entering
your area. Carry on and deal with it.
Southern Group... raids one
and two entering your area.
- Carry on and deal with them.
- Yes, sir. Raids one and two.
Two raids are anticipated
in the Southern Group Command.
To them goes the order
to repel the raiders.
Braxted.
Group Command rings
Braxted fighter station.
Station control.
Serial No. 1, Flight A,
Squadron 299, Raid No. 1.
OK.
The arrow representing
the German raid
is transferred from the plotting table
to the action table.
A-Flight, 299.
Take off.
Flight A airborne, sir.
OK. Put B-Flight at readiness.
B-Flight, 299.
Cornflower Red calling station control.
Over to you. Over.
Cornflower Red. Cornflower Red.
80 degrees. 2,000 feet a minute.
Speed 180.
- Got that, Ted?
- Right with you, Bob.
OK, Dopey?
Hey, Dopey. Are you OK?
What? Oh, God, yes. All serene.
Over.
Cornflower Red. Cornflower Red.
80 degrees.
80 degrees. Level. Level.
Keep speed to 360.
OK, gang, let's go.
Alter course, sir.
Over.
Cornflower Red. Cornflower Red.
Alter course. 92 degrees.
92 degrees.
Level. Speed 360.
Cornflower Red. Cornflower Red.
Five bandits six miles south-west.
South-west. Circle.
Should be any minute now.
Go!
Here we go.
Spitfires.
No.1 attack. Go!
All right, you lousy Germans!
You're going to get it now!
Cornflower Red calling Station Control.
Have brought down two bandits.
Remainder proceeding east.
May I continue action? Over to you. Over.
Cornflower Red. Good work. Carry on.
- Two.
- Correct.
Not so dusty.
The first raid has been driven back,
but a second is on the way.
OP127 here.
Enemy aircraft overhead.
Braxted?
Serial number two, Flight B, Squadron 299,
Raid No.2.
Very good, sir.
B-Flight. Raid No.2.
Take off.
Searchlights and
anti-aircraft go into action.
You've got him, Charlie.
- Hold him. Hold him, Charlie.
- Number one, fire!
Number two, fire!
- Come on, throw a double, can't you?
- Right.
John, there's a job
for you on square K29.
Better warn your people
before we cop it from your guns.
- Cease fire.
- Cease fire!
- They would.
The blinkin' RAF swipes all the fun.
It's the worst part
of our job - just waiting.
A-Flight will be back soon.
B-Flight has taken over in the air.
A-Flightreturns to the aerodrome to refuel
and restock with ammunition.
Ground staff are waiting.
They race out to the machines
that have come back for second breath.
In the ghostly shrouded blackness
of the aerodrome,
everything goes with clockwork smoothness,
as if they were working in broad daylight.
Cornflower Blue calling Station Control.
Two bandits down. Two bandits down.
Remaining two have entered clouds
over sea and are heading east.
Two of our aircraft forced to land.
Should we proceed with action?
Over to you. Over.
Been up half an hour.
Must be short of petrol.
Cornflower Blue, Cornflower Blue,
discontinue action and return.
- Any luck?
- No more. Guns ran out.
You did well.
Get your craft available and rest.
They're working on them now.
Ready in 20 minutes.
- Send up my flight again.
- Rest.
- Very good.
- Cheeky devil.
More gallons of petrol go into the
fighters' tanks. Fuel for the engines.
Food for the guns.
The flight commander took a crack
from one of the bomber's guns.
But it only tore the fuselage and he's
ready for duty again when he's wanted.
Now we pick up German raid No.3.
Southern Group.
Raid 3 entering your area.
Is now allocated to you.
Yes, sir. Raid 3.
He's coming into the balloon barrage.
They climb and climb.
They dare not face entanglement
in those awful strands of steel.
The balloons have forced them up too high
for accurate bombing.
They turn and make for home.
Gute Idee.
And their departure
is recorded at Fighter Command.
Heading east.
They're on the run.
Braxted?
Station Control?
Serial number three,
Squadron 301, Raid No.3.
Very good.
About time.
Hello.
Take off.
Yes, they're on the run.
But a new squadron of Spitfires leaves
the drome and hurtles up into the inky sky,
racing out towards the
coast like black bullets.
While every mile
is followed on the chart.
Closing the distance between the fighters
in pursuit and the bombers heading for home.
Over the coastline.
Ah.
Die See.
Out over the sea to home and safety.
But the fighters are coming up fast.
They should be due east,
in front of you.
Can you see anything, Fred?
No.
No luck.
# Where, oh where, is my little baton?
# Oh, where oh where can he be?
What's that on our right?
Sunflower calling Station Control.
Enemy sighted. I am overtaking fast.
Damn good chaps on this station.
Sunflower calling Station Control.
I am about to engage.
No.3 attack, go!
Left his mike on. May hear something.
Sunflower calling Station Control.
Four bandits down.
Four? Good work.
Remainder have escaped in clouds.
No casualties. Repeat, no casualties.
May I have permission to return?
Over to you. Over.
Sunflower, Station Control
calling Sunflower.
Return at once. Good work.
Four! Four!
- What the hell are you doing here?
- Well, I...
I told you to rest.
Yes, sir. That makes
eight for this station, sir.
By Jove! Yes, it does. Eight!
- All clear signal, sir.
- All clear, eh?
- From Commanding-in-Chief.
- Ah.
He's very pleased with
the work of all stations.
I bet none of the others got eight.
All units engaged in tonight's actions
to take their spell of rest off on return.
- Sir.
- That includes you.
Supposing they come back.
- Get out!
- Very good.
- And give her my love.
- Very good, sir.
- Well, your spell off?
- Fine.
Good night. Or good morning.
- Good night, sir.
- Good morning.
Darling.
Hey!
- Where've you been?
- Night shift.
This is a fine war.
Women go out and their husbands
wait at home for them.
- How long have you been waiting?
- It must be a full minute.
How long have you got?
12 hours.
Had a pretty concentrated stretch lately.
- Any luck?
- Went according to schedule.
Very much to schedule.
You must be tired.
I'll get you breakfast
and you can go to bed.
No, no, let's take the car down the river
for a couple of hours first, shall we?
Oh, I'm a selfish pig.
You must be dead beat.
Oh, no, darling.
I was hoping you'd suggest it.
And we've just got enough petrol ration.
Darling.
Isn't it nice to be together again?
To be together again.
Get a warm coat, will you?
Come on.
There.
- Isn't this perfect?
- Mm-hm.
- Darling.
- Mm?
I couldn't help thinking
as I sat in the rest room last night...
Mm-hm.
There was nothing to do.
We're getting used to alarms
with nothing happening.
Only listening to the
drone of our own engines.
Well, I was thinking about women.
How for centuries in this country
they've given their lovers,
husbands, sons
first to the earth
to defend their land,
and then to the sea.
And now they've got
to give them to the air.
They've never complained.
Often and often they've lost the
one man in the world that counted.
That expressed the
whole of life to them.
They've bitterly resented the stupidity
and brutality that made it necessary.
But that it was necessary
they never questioned.
We must keep our land, darling.
We must keep our freedom.
We must fight for what we believe in.
Truth and beauty, and fair play.
And...
And kindness.
So that even if we don't live to
enjoy life founded on the good things,
at least our children may.
Eh, darling?
No longer do we fight wars
for jealousy or greed.
Nor do we fightin anger.
We fight because we must.
For just those things
that we hold so dear.
We can learn from the motto
of the Royal Air Force.
Per ardua ad astra.
Through ordeal to the stars.
Through endeavour to triumph.
Through trial to victory.